<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss/podcast/style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"  xmlns:podcast="https://podcastindex.org/namespace/1.0"  xmlns:googleplay="http://www.google.com/schemas/play-podcasts/1.0"
    xmlns:dc="https://dublincore.org/schemas/xmls/qdc/2008/02/11/dc.xsd" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

<channel>
	<title>Hazard Podcast Feed</title>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
	<atom:link href="https://hazardpodcast.com/rss/podcast" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/</link>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright><![CDATA[]]></copyright>
	<description>Hazard is a new podcast that digs through the muck of different superfund sites accross the US to give a clearer picture of what the threat is and what it will take to clean it up before it's too late. Hosted by journalist Jordan Gass-Poore'</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:51:30 GMT</lastBuildDate>
	<generator>https://11ty.dev/</generator>
	<managingEditor>
		webmaster@hazardpodcast.com (Jordan Gass-Poore)
	</managingEditor>
    <itunes:summary><![CDATA[Hazard is a new podcast that digs through the muck of different superfund sites accross the US to give a clearer picture of what the threat is and what it will take to clean it up before it's too late. Hosted by journalist Jordan Gass-Poore']]></itunes:summary>
    <image>
		<url>https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardCover.jpg</url>
		<title>Hazard Podcast Feed</title>
		<link><![CDATA[https://hazardpodcast.com/]]></link>
	</image>
    <itunes:author>Hazard Podcast Feed</itunes:author>
    <itunes:category text="Science">
        <itunes:category text="Earth Sciences"/>
    </itunes:category>
    <itunes:category text="News"/>
    <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardCover.jpg" />
    <itunes:explicit>clean</itunes:explicit>
    <itunes:owner>
        <itunes:name><![CDATA[Jordan Gass-Poore]]></itunes:name>
        <itunes:email>webmaster@hazardpodcast.com</itunes:email>
    </itunes:owner>
    <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[]]></itunes:subtitle>
    <itunes:type>episodic</itunes:type>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NYC Podcast - Can a Contaminated Creek Come Clean? - Season 2: Episode 1</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-10-nyc-episode-01/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 09:00:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-10-nyc-episode-01/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HAZARD_NYC_3000x3000.png" />
		<description>Newtown Creek is one of the country’s most polluted waterways. Flooding from sea level rise and storms threatens to spread the creek’s contamination and bring pollution from outside the water into it. The feds are figuring out how to include climate change into the clean-up plan they’re developing. THE CITY’s senior reporter Samantha Maldonado and independent journalist Jordan Gass-Pooré dive in on episode one of Hazard NYC, a four-part FAQ NYC Presents limited series exploring the city’s Superfund sites.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Newtown Creek is one of the country’s most polluted waterways. Flooding from sea level rise and storms threatens to spread the creek’s contamination and bring pollution from outside the water into it. The feds are figuring out how to include climate change into the clean-up plan they’re developing. THE CITY’s senior reporter Samantha Maldonado and independent journalist Jordan Gass-Pooré dive in on episode one of Hazard NYC, a four-part FAQ NYC Presents limited series exploring the city’s Superfund sites.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe src="https://fireside.fm/player/v2/OS-Y7tt8+lCLHYJ4L" width="100%" height="200" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
<img width="100%" src="https://i0.wp.com/www.thecity.nyc/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/111523_newtown_creek_walk_3-scaled.jpg?fit=2560%2C1707&ssl=1" alt="A sign warns about sewage discharge in the Newtown Creek Superfund site." decoding="async" />
<p>Newtown Creek is one of the country’s most polluted waterways. Flooding from sea level rise and storms threatens to spread the creek’s contamination and bring pollution from outside the water into it. The feds are figuring out how to include climate change into the clean-up plan they’re developing. </p>
<p>THE CITY’s senior reporter Samantha Maldonado and independent journalist Jordan Gass-Pooré dive in on episode one of Hazard NYC, a four-part FAQ NYC Presents limited series exploring the city’s Superfund sites. </p>
<p>As one scientist puts it, “We cannot accept that there are regions of our city that are so contaminated that we would say, ‘I wouldn't want to touch it.’ Because guess what? It comes for you. That's the reality of climate change and our coastal waterways.”</p>
<p>See and read more about Newtown Creek <a href="https://projects.thecity.nyc/hazard-nyc-newtown-creek/">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>If you like what you’re hearing, please spread the word, and subscribe on </em><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/faq-nyc/id1422065980"><em>Apple Podcasts</em></a><em>, </em><a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/3JBxbVpmfoir1feQ5P9OMY"><em>Spotify</em></a><em>, </em><em> or wherever podcasts are found.</em></p>
<p><em>THE CITY is a nonprofit newsroom that serves the people of New York. <a href="https://projects.thecity.nyc/newsletter-form/">Sign up for our SCOOP newsletter</a> and get exclusive stories, helpful tips, a guide to low-cost events, and everything you need to know to be a well-informed New Yorker.</em></p>
<link rel="canonical" href="https://www.thecity.nyc/2024/02/14/newtown-creek-superfund-pollution-hazardnyc-faqnyc-podcast/" />
<img id="republication-tracker-tool-source" src="https://www.thecity.nyc/?republication-pixel=true&post=35658&ga4=G-1SD504K0YR" style="width:1px;height:1px;" />
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p>**HS VO [PRE-ROLL] **</p>
<p>It’s FAQ NYC PRESENTS, where the only podcast in the only city in the world brings in other voices to dig into what it’s all about.</p>
<p>I’m Harry Siegel, FAQ NYC’s co-host and executive producer, and right now you’re going to hear part 1 of Hazard NYC, a four-part limited series looking at New York’s four federal superfund sites hosted by Samantha Maldonado of The City and independent journalist Jordan Gass-Poore.</p>
<p>Hazard NYC was made possible by support from the Fund for Investigative Journalism. The project was produced in partnership with the McGraw Center for Business Journalism at the CUNY Graduate School of Journalism, and is part of the Pulitzer Center's Connected Coastlines initiative. For more information, go to pulitzer center dot org… forward slash… connected hyphen coastlines.</p>
<p>Hazard NYC is supported in part by Newlab – a platform helping deep-tech startups succeed to address the climate crisis. Learn more at <a href="http://newlab.com/" target="_blank">newlab.com</a>.</p>
<p>Let’s jump right in.</p>
<p><strong>[BOAT TOUR SFX: BOAT BEING LOWERED INTO THE WATER]</strong></p>
<p>**JGP VO [BOAT TOUR] **</p>
<p>I CLIMBED INTO A SMALL BOAT THAT LAUNCHED FROM A DOCK IN GREENPOINT INTO NEWTOWN CREEK.</p>
<p><strong>[BOAT TOUR SFX]</strong></p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **I'll show you real quick on the map, where we're headed here.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>MY GUIDE WAS WILLIS ELKINS. HE’S THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF NEWTOWN CREEK ALLIANCE… HE KNOWS THE HISTORY OF THESE MURKY WATERS…</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **The sediment below us is the most contaminated stuff in the creek.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>AND THE BRIGHT SPOTS.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **It's also an area where there's, like, the most, like, bird wildlife activity.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>FOR NEARLY FOUR MILES… NEWTOWN CREEK SNAKES BETWEEN NORTH BROOKLYN… AND PARTS OF QUEENS.</p>
<p><strong>[SFX: CAR, BRIDGE]</strong></p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>FROM THE BOAT I SAW EGRETS AND CORMORANTS AND WATCHED WAREHOUSES SLIDE BY.</p>
<p><strong>[SFX]</strong></p>
<p>I ALSO SAW WATER THAT REMINDED ME OF PICKLE JUICE. AND THEN FURTHER DOWNSTREAM… IT SMELLED KINDA LIKE ROTTEN EGGS.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX IN: “Hazard NYC Theme”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>I’M JORDAN GASS POORE… AN INDEPENDENT JOURNALIST AND PODCAST PRODUCER.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AND I’M SAMANTHA MALDONADO… A REPORTER WITH THE CITY.</p>
<p>WE’RE BRINGING YOU HAZARD N-Y-C… A MINI SERIES FROM  F-A-Q N-Y-C.</p>
<p>ON THIS EPISODE… WE TAKE A JOURNEY TO NEWTOWN CREEK… ONE OF NEW YORK CITY’S FOUR SUPERFUND SITES.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX OUT: “Hazard NYC Theme”]</strong></p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **I remember when I was a child coming back from vacation, and hitting the Greenpoint Avenue Bridge, in the car, that the smell would literally wake me up. It was like a slap in the face. The smell was so bad that it could make you want to vomit. Sewage, and other chemicals, all kinds of stuff.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>LAURA HOFFMAN, A LIFELONG BROOKLYN RESIDENT, LIVES RIGHT NEAR NEWTOWN CREEK, ONE OF THE MOST POLLUTED WATERWAYS IN THE U-S.</p>
<p>AS A SUPERFUND SITE, IT’S ON THE ROAD TO GETTING CLEANER.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>NEWTOWN CREEK IS PRONE TO FLOODING… WHICH THREATENS TO SPREAD POLLUTION BEYOND THE CREEK… AND BRING MORE POLLUTION INTO IT.</p>
<p>TO UNDERSTAND WHY THE CREEK NEEDS A CLEAN UP… YOU NEED TO KNOW ITS HISTORY.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX IN: “Awful Sad”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>ALMOST TWO HUNDRED YEARS AGO… THE CREEK’S COASTLINE WAS LINED WITH OVER FIFTY OIL REFINERIES… SAWMILLS… AND FACTORIES THAT PRODUCED FERTILIZER AND GLUE… AMONG MANY OTHER THINGS.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>BUT AS MUCH AS MUCH AS THOSE BUSINESSES CONTRIBUTED TO THE CITY’S ECONOMY… THEY ALSO POLLUTED THE CREEK.</p>
<p>FOR DECADES… THESE COMPANIES USED THE WATERWAY AS A DUMPING GROUND FOR CHEMICALS AND FUELS.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>HUMAN WASTE ENTERED THE WATER FROM THE CITY’S SEWER SYSTEM STARTING IN THE MID 18-HUNDREDS.</p>
<p>NOW THE AREA IS STILL PRETTY INDUSTRIAL… AND… THE CONTAMINATION FROM THOSE YEARS REMAINS.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>OIL… METALS LIKE LEAD AND COPPER… AND OTHER CARCINOGENIC CHEMICALS HAVE BEEN FOUND IN THE CREEK’S SEDIMENT.</p>
<p>THE CLEAN UP OF THE SITE COULD TAKE A DECADE — AND THE E-P-A HAS TO FINALIZE ITS PLAN FIRST.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>UNTIL THAT DAY COMES… LOCAL RESIDENTS WILL KEEP PUSHING FOR A CLEANER WATERWAY.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX FADE OUT: “Awful Sad”]</strong></p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **I’m Laura Hoffman. Pain In The Ass. I guess that's my expertise in the neighborhood.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THIS LAURA HOFFMAN… SIXTY FIVE… WHO YOU HEARD EARLIER. SHE’S A BORN AND BRED GREENPOINTER AND A SELF-PROCLAIMED AGITATOR.</p>
<p><strong>Laura Hoffman:</strong> My husband and I are members of practically every organization that begins with the words Newtown Creek.</p>
<p><strong>JGP</strong></p>
<p>EVEN HER HUSBAND’S FAMILY HAS LIVED IN THE AREA FOR GENERATIONS.</p>
<p>WE SAT WITH HER AT HER DINING ROOM TABLE… WHILE HER CAT TRIED TO JOIN THE INTERVIEW.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **Sorry, that's my cat. There we go. There we go. Sorry about that.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>FAMILY PHOTOS HUNG ON HER WALLS… REMINDERS OF LAURA’S DEEP ROOTS IN THE COMMUNITY.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **I had so many aunts and uncles that came from this area that I could practically map out who died from what and connect them with the area and the toxins that they lived near.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>WHEN SHE WAS KID… LAURA SAYS SHE DIDN’T NEED TO SEE THE FILTH ON THE SURFACE OF NEWTOWN CREEK TO KNOW IT WAS POLLUTED…</p>
<p>…SHE COULD SMELL IT.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>BUT MANY PEOPLE DIDN’T KNOW THE EXTENT OF THE CONTAMINATION.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **As we were growing up, my husband and I both have swam in either the Newtown Creek or the East River, played on the barges. I used to play on the salt piles in the industrial area near where the Department of Sanitation is located now. We went crabbing with our kids.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>LAURA AND HER HUSBAND INITIALLY GOT INVOLVED WITH EFFORTS TO CLEAN UP NEWTOWN CREEK AND THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD YEARS AGO. THAT’S WHEN THEY NOTICED STRANGE ODORS WHILE THEIR KIDS WERE PLAYING SOFTBALL.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **We found out that some of the odors that the kids was smelling and things that were happening were because we were located near an oil spill, near a PVC manufacturer, near a sewage sludge tank, near all kinds of industry.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>LAURA WAS IN GREENPOINT IN 19-78… WHEN THE U-S COAST GUARD SPOTTED OIL FLOWING INTO NEWTOWN CREEK.</p>
<p>THEY DISCOVERED ONE OF THE LARGEST OIL SPILLS IN THE COUNTRY’S HISTORY.</p>
<p>IT’S ESTIMATED AT LEAST SEVENTEEN MILLION GALLONS OF OIL HAD LEAKED FROM AN OIL REFINERY AND FUEL STORAGE FACILITIES.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>IN THE EARLY TWO THOUSANDS… A SERIES OF LAWSUITS WERE BROUGHT AGAINST EXXON MOBIL TO GET THE COMPANY TO PAY FOR THE CLEANUP OF THE SPILL…</p>
<p>EXXON SETTLED IN 20-10, THE SAME YEAR THE E-P-A DESIGNATED NEWTOWN CREEK AS A SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>UNDER THAT PROGRAM, THE E-P-A WOULD OVERSEE THE CLEAN-UP AND MAKE THE POLLUTERS PAY.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **You know, one by one different polluters have been getting caught, and, you know, they have their feet being held to the fire and being forced to take responsibility for their actions. The creek is becoming somewhat cleaner, although by somewhat cleaner, you know, I'm using that real loose, because there's a lot to do to get that creek to be healthy and clean.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX IN: “2nd Edit Interstitial Sad or Contemplative”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE E-P-A IS WORKING WITH A GROUP OF COMPANIES THAT BEAR RESPONSIBILITY FOR POLLUTING THE CREEK.</p>
<p>AND THE CLEAN UP CAN’T COME SOON ENOUGH.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>NEIGHBORHOODS AROUND NEWTOWN CREEK …PARTS OF GREENPOINT… EAST WILLIAMSBURG… MASPETH… AND LONG ISLAND CITY… FOR INSTANCE… HAVE A ONE PERCENT CHANCE OF EXPERIENCING A MAJOR FLOOD IN ANY GIVEN YEAR.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AND CLIMATE CHANGE WILL MAKE IT WORSE.</p>
<p>HERE IN NEW YORK SEA LEVELS ARE ESTIMATED TO RISE BETWEEN ABOUT A FOOT AND TWO FEET BY THE 20-50s. THAT’S ACCORDING TO THE NEW YORK CITY PANEL ON CLIMATE CHANGE.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>ON TOP OF RISING SEA LEVELS… CLIMATE CHANGE WILL BRING MORE INTENSE AND FREQUENT STORMS.</p>
<p>HURRICANE SANDY GAVE US A PEEK INTO WHAT CLIMATE CHANGE HAS IN STORE FOR US.</p>
<p>DURING THE 20-12 STORM… NEWTOWN CREEK SURGED PAST ITS BANKS AND INFLICTED FLOOD DAMAGE… UP AND DOWN THE WATERWAY.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX FADE OUT: “2nd Edit Interstitial Sad or Contemplative”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>Gregory O'Mullan:</strong> I've been there in the days following Sandy crawling around in basements where Newtown Creek was in people's homes, it was in the streets, you saw the watermarks, often with the grit associated with it on the buildings.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>GREGORY O’MULLAN IS AN ASSISTANT PROFESSOR AND MICROBIOLOGIST AT QUEENS COLLEGE.</p>
<p>TO HIM… HURRICANE SANDY UNDERSCORES THE IMPORTANCE OF A CLEANUP.</p>
<p>**Gregory O'Mullan: **That waterway will not stay within its bounds, it will not in the climate context that's coming. And therefore the contamination that is in those environments and the sewage that we put into those environments, often associated with the same events that cause it to breach its banks. Those moments we have to be prepared for. And part of that means we cannot accept that there are regions of our city that are so contaminated that we would say I wouldn't want to touch it. Because guess what, it comes for you — that's the reality of climate change and our coastal waterways.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>PAUL PULLO KNOWS THIS ALL TOO WELL. FOR YEARS… HIS FAMILY RAN A HEATING OIL BUSINESS CALLED METRO FUEL. IT SAT ON THE SOUTH BANK OF NEWTOWN CREEK IN GREENPOINT.</p>
<p>HE SOLD THE BUSINESS ABOUT A DECADE AGO… BUT NOT BEFORE SANDY HIT.</p>
<p>**Paul Pullo: **We had four feet of water in the offices. We were prepared for probably two feet but we had four, so everything we did it went over all the, all the preparations that we may never expected it to go that high.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>PAUL SAYS THEY <em>HAD</em> INSTALLED BARRIERS AROUND THE BUILDING TO PREVENT DAMAGE.</p>
<p>**Paul Pullo: **This wasn't the first flood we had. So over the years, being there we knew some of the things we should do.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AFTER THE STORM ENDED… PAUL SAYS HE REMEMBERS THERE WAS SOME NASTY STUFF INSIDE HIS FACILITY THAT HE HAD TO CLEAN UP.</p>
<p><strong>Paul Pullo:</strong> There was some residue on some of the dike walls from floating oil, but there was no contamination that we found.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>PAUL MAY NOT HAVE FOUND ANY CONTAMINATION… BUT THE E-P-A DID.</p>
<p>AFTER SANDY… THE AGENCY SAMPLED THE FLOODWATER. THEY FOUND CHEMICALS… BUT THEY WERE AT SUCH LOW LEVELS THERE WASN’T ANY CAUSE FOR CONCERN.</p>
<p>**Walter Mugdan: **It was very, very low, in many cases negligible or under non-detect levels of the chemical contamination.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THAT’S WALTER MUGDAN. HE’S A FORMER DEPUTY REGIONAL ADMINISTRATOR FOR THE E-P-A.</p>
<p>**Walter Mugdan: **But we did find pathogens bacteria that are associated with sewage. So it wasn't good to have in people's homes. But it wasn't the chemical stuff that's in the bottom of these waterways.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>IN GENERAL… THE E-P-A SAID IT’S MOSTLY FOCUSED ON <em>LONG-TERM</em> EXPOSURE TO CHEMICALS.</p>
<p>CONTAMINATION SPREAD AFTER A FLOOD MAY NOT POSE THAT KIND OF HARM.</p>
<p>HERE’S JOHN PRINCE. HE OVERSEES THE E-P-A’S SUPERFUND PROGRAM IN THE NEW YORK REGION.</p>
<p>**John Prince: **We wouldn't expect an exposure like sediments that might get deposited after a storm to pose that kind of a risk.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>ANOTHER THING TO CONSIDER… WITHOUT PROPER PROTECTION… THE BUSINESSES THEMSELVES COULD CONTRIBUTE TO THE POLLUTION OF THE CREEK WHEN THERE’S A FLOOD.</p>
<p>THAT’S WHAT HAPPENED AFTER SANDY. AROUND THE CREEK…</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **All these trucks got totally flooded. And it's, like, there's oil and other fluids leaking out of those trucks.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THAT’S WILLIS ELKINS AGAIN. HE’S THE ONE WHO TOOK ME ON THE BOAT TOUR AT THE TOP OF THE EPISODE.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **For weeks after Sandy, the creek was a rainbow of chemicals.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>HE REMEMBERS THIS AND WORRIES THAT THE CONTAMINATION FROM THE LAND <em>AROUND</em> THE CREEK WILL GET INTO THE WATER… AND ULTIMATELY MESS UP THE EFFORTS TO CLEAN THE CREEK.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **We're concerned about a remedy that doesn't fully address all those and that for years to come, we still have ongoing sources of pollution that put the ecology and put the community at risk.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THE E-P-A IS STUDYING HOW THE GROUNDWATER AND THE POLLUTANTS MAY BE MOVING AROUND… AND WILL INCORPORATE THE RESULTS INTO ITS CLEANUP PLAN.</p>
<p>THE AGENCY MAY HAVE TO WORK WITH PRIVATE PROPERTY OWNERS TO ADDRESS ANY MOVEMENT OF CONTAMINANTS FROM AREAS AROUND THE CREEK.</p>
<p>THAT’S BECAUSE THE E-P-A’S PURVIEW INCLUDES <em>ONLY</em> THE CREEK ITSELF… NOT THE LAND AROUND IT.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **There's a world outside of Superfunds.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>HERE’S STEPHANIE VAUGHN… AN E-P-A PROJECT MANAGER FOR NEWTOWN CREEK.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **We're going to do as much as we can through Superfund, and then try to work with the other entities to facilitate, encourage increased improvement, investment and best practices, so that the overall health of the creek can improve over time.</p>
<p>**HS VO [MID-ROLL] **</p>
<p>THE CITY's Hazard NYC podcast is supported in part by Brooklyn SolarWorks, a solar design and installation firm dedicated to helping homes and buildings in New York City reduce their energy costs and their carbon footprints. Want to know if your home or building is right for solar? Schedule a free consultation by visiting <a href="http://brooklynsolarworks.com/" target="_blank">brooklynsolarworks.com</a> or calling 347-712-3915</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE ACTUAL PLAN FOR REMEDIATION IS HOTLY ANTICIPATED.</p>
<p>LOTS OF PEOPLE WHO CARE ABOUT NEWTOWN CREEK ARE PRETTY FRUSTRATED BY HOW LONG THE PROCESS IS TAKING.</p>
<p>WILLIS ELKINS BLAMES THE BACK-AND-FORTH BETWEEN THE E-P-A… AND THE PARTIES THE AGENCY IDENTIFIED AS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CREEK’S POLLUTION.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THOSE PARTIES INCLUDE THE CITY OF NEW YORK PLUS…</p>
<p>**David Haury: **Five industrial corporations, Exxon Mobil, National Grid, Phelps, Dodge Refining Corporation, BP, and Texaco.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THAT’S DAVID HAURY [har-ee]… PRINCIPAL OF THE CONSULTING FIRM ANCHOR Q-E-A. HE WAS HIRED BY THOSE FIVE COMPANIES TO DO THE TECHNICAL WORK AT NEWTOWN CREEK.</p>
<p>TOGETHER… THOSE COMPANIES ARE KNOWN AS THE NEWTOWN CREEK GROUP… OR N-C-G.</p>
<p>**David Haury: **Other parties have been identified by EPA and the NCG. But they're not currently participating in any of the studies being done and to pay for the cleanup where they have some responsibility.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>DAVID SAYS THE E-P-A MAKES THE CALLS DURING THE PROCESS.</p>
<p>**David Haury: **It has taken a long time. The schedule is controlled by EPA; they decide what they want to do, and when they want to do it, and we develop work plans and go implement the work.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>SOME IN THE COMMUNITY ARE SKEPTICAL.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **We want to have full faith in EPA that they are driving the show, and then we're gonna get a thorough proper remediation in a timely manner.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>IN THE MEANTIME… THERE’S BEEN LOTS OF SAMPLING… DATA COLLECTION… AND TECHNICAL WORK DONE BY THE E-P-A AND DAVID AND HIS STAFF.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>PART OF WHAT THE E-P-A IS TRYING TO FIGURE OUT IS WHICH CONTAMINANTS PRESENT AT THE SITE POSE AN “UNACCEPTABLE RISK” TO HUMAN HEALTH AND THE ENVIRONMENT.</p>
<p>HERE’S STEPHANIE FROM THE E-P-A AGAIN.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **Those include total PCBs, polychlorinated biphenyls, total pH is hydrocarbons and dioxins interference.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>LET’S BREAK THAT DOWN.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>NEWTOWN CREEK’S TOXIC COCKTAIL IS MADE UP OF MAINLY HUMAN MADE INDUSTRIAL CHEMICALS THAT COULD CAUSE CANCER…</p>
<p>… LONG TERM EXPOSURE TO THESE CHEMICALS COULD CAUSE ORGAN DAMAGE… RASHES… AND CATARACTS.</p>
<p>THE CREEK IS ALSO POLLUTED WITH DANGEROUS HEAVY METALS… INCLUDING LEAD AND COPPER.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **The exposure to the hazardous substances in the creek, it would be primarily through ingestion of fish and crabs from the creek.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>PEOPLE DO GO FISHING IN THE CREEK. AND DESPITE SIGNS WARNING AGAINST EATING WHAT THEY CATCH, IT’S ASSUMED SOME PEOPLE STILL DO.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **From an ecological perspective, we also have the biggest risks are to those little critters that live in the creek.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>SOME OF THOSE CONTAMINANTS COME FROM PAST AND CURRENT INDUSTRIAL USES. OTHER POLLUTION IS FROM THE SEWER. THAT’S WHY THE CITY OF NEW YORK IS IMPLICATED.</p>
<p>HERE’S RIT AGGARWALA… THE COMMISSIONER OF THE CITY DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION.</p>
<p>**Rit Aggarwala: **Part of DEP’s responsibility is to come up with a plan to reduce the combined sewer overflows into Newtown Creek.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX IN: “Interstitial - Fast,Sad,Weird TRACK”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>RIT IS TALKING ABOUT WHAT HAPPENS WHEN RAW SEWAGE IS UNLEASHED INTO THE CREEK.</p>
<p>IN MOST OF THE CITY… THE SEWER SYSTEM’S PIPES CARRY BOTH WATER FROM RAIN AND THE WATER THAT COMES FROM THE TOILETS… SHOWERS… AND LAUNDRY.</p>
<p>AND WHEN IT RAINS… THE SYSTEM GETS OVERWHELMED.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>INSTEAD OF GETTING TO THE TREATMENT PLANT… THIS MIX OF WATER AND WASTE POURS INTO WATER BODIES LIKE NEWTOWN CREEK. THAT’S A COMBINED SEWER OVERFLOW… A C-S-O.</p>
<p>SO WHEN YOU FLUSH DURING RAINY DAYS… WHATEVER’S IN YOUR TOILET HAS A GOOD CHANCE OF ENDING UP IN THE WATER.</p>
<p>BUT THAT’S WHERE THERE’S BEEN SOME REAL MOVEMENT IN RECENT YEARS.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE CITY MADE UPGRADES TO A WASTEWATER TREATMENT PLANT AT NEWTOWN CREEK.</p>
<p>YOU CAN SEE THE PLANT FROM AFAR BECAUSE OF ITS EIGHT GIANT METAL EGGS THAT DIGEST WASTEWATER. THAT’S WHERE MILLIONS OF GALLONS OF THE CITY’S SEWAGE GOES TO GET PROCESSED.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX FADE OUT: “Interstitial - Fast,Sad,Weird TRACK”]</strong></p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **That's resulted in a lot of improvements to water quality in the lower two miles closest to the East River. And that has meant more return of marine wildlife.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>BUT THE CITY HAS TO DO MORE TO REDUCE THE POOP IN NEWTOWN CREEK. THE MAIN WAY THIS WILL HAPPEN IS THROUGH A NEW MASSIVE UNDERGROUND TUNNEL.</p>
<p>THE TUNNEL WILL HOLD THE WASTEWATER DURING A STORM THAT CAUSES THE SEWERS TO REACH CAPACITY… AND WHEN THE STORM ENDS… WHAT GOT CAPTURED WILL GO TO THE TREATMENT PLANT.</p>
<p>**Rit Aggarwala: **Think about what we're talking about: a 39-million-gallon tunnel around and across the creek. That’s a two-and-a-half billion dollar project.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>WHEN THE TUNNEL IS COMPLETE… IT WILL SIGNIFICANTLY DECREASE THE SEWAGE ENTERING THE CREEK.</p>
<p>BUT IT WON’T GET IT DOWN TO ZERO.</p>
<p>STILL… THE E-P-A DETERMINED THAT’S OK.</p>
<p>BUT THERE”S QUESTIONS ABOUT HOW CLIMATE CHANGE COULD PUT SOME OF THAT PROGRESS AT RISK.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **We're facing increasing rainfall. So, we're concerned that the pace going forward for reduction of CSO is not going to be as strong as was originally planned.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>REMEMBER… RAW SEWAGE SPILLS INTO THE CREEK WHEN IT RAINS A LOT.</p>
<p>BUT OFFICIALS SAY THE TUNNEL WILL BE EFFECTIVE EVEN WITH MORE RAIN.</p>
<p>**Rit Aggarwala: **The most harmful CSO events are actually the ones where you have a relatively low rainfall, but we have very little storage capacity and, therefore, you're actually dumping what is a relatively high concentration of sewage into the water.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE WAY THIS WILL WORK IS THE NEW TUNNEL WILL CAPTURE THE NASTIEST STUFF FIRST.</p>
<p>**Walter Mugdan: **It’s called the first flush.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AGAIN… WALTER MUGDAN… FORMERY OF THE E-P-A.</p>
<p>**Walter Mugdan: **So, whatever water is in whatever sewage and in the sewage pipes, sewage, from people's toilets, and showers and dishwashers and everything else, whatever's in the pipes, when the rain starts, is the most concentrated amount of sewage, right? The more it rains, the more diluted it becomes.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE REST OF THE RAIN ALONG WITH SEWAGE WILL STILL ENTER THE CREEK. BUT…</p>
<p>**Walter Mugdan: **It's less and it's cleaner than what's going into the creek today.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX IN: “Interstitial - Thoughtful GTR”]</strong></p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THE TUNNEL WON’T BE DONE UNTIL ABOUT 20-40…</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>CLEANING UP THE WATER IS ONE THING… BUT REMOVING THE CONTAMINATED SOIL ON THE BOTTOM OF THE CREEK IS A SEPARATE CONSIDERATION.</p>
<p>ONE WAY THE E-P-A CAN DO IT… IS TO DREDGE THE SEDIMENT. THAT MEANS SCOOPING OUT THE CONTAMINATED SOIL.</p>
<p>ANOTHER WAY IS CAPPING… WHICH IS COVERING UP THE CONTAMINATED SEDIMENT.</p>
<p>THERE ARE PROS AND CONS TO EACH STRATEGY… IN TERMS OF COSTS… HOW LONG IT WILL TAKE… THE IMPACTS TO THE ENVIRONMENT… AND HOW EFFECTIVE THEY ARE AT KEEPING THE POLLUTION AT BAY.</p>
<p><strong>[MUX FADE OUT: “Interstitial - Thoughtful GTR”]</strong></p>
<p>HERE’S JOHN PRINCE AGAIN FROM THE E-P-A.</p>
<p>**John Prince: **This is a very old waterway in a highly urban environment and it's reasonable for us to assume that remedies are not going to reach some sort of pristine clean level through dredging.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>JOHN SAYS THAT EVEN IF THE TEAM WAS TO DREDGE MANY FEET DOWN… A CAP WOULD PROBABLY STILL BE NEEDED.</p>
<p>**John Prince: **We still need to put a cap on to cover whatever's down there. Whatever the new bottom of the creek is probably likely to still have some level of contamination.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AND CAPS CAN FACE PROBLEMS TOO.</p>
<p>CAPS CAN BE DISTURBED BY TURBULENCE IN THE WATER.</p>
<p>THE E-P-A SAID THEY WOULD TAKE INTO ACCOUNT CREEK CONDITIONS LIKE TIDES… FLOODING… BOATS TRAVELING THROUGH… AND RUNOFF… IN DEVISING A LONG-LASTING CAP.</p>
<p>**John Prince: **Our other expectation is we're not just going to build it and walk away, right? We're going to build it and then expect it to be monitored.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>THAT’S FOR WHATEVER ROUTE THEY END UP TAKING.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>IN THE MEANTIME… THE E-P-A AND THE GROUP OF RESPONSIBLE COMPANIES ARE ALSO WORKING ON AN EARLY PLAN TO TACKLE ONE PART OF THE CREEK: THE EAST BRANCH.</p>
<p>THAT’S A TRIBUTARY OF THE CREEK THAT REACHES OUT TO MASPETH AND EAST WILLIAMSBURG. HERE’S STEPHANIE FROM THE E-P-A.</p>
<p>**Stephanie Vaughn: **This will allow work to start on that portion of the creek while the remedy for the rest of this site is being developed.</p>
<p>**[MUX IN: “1st go Interstitial 4 - Hopeful”] **</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>EVERYTHING IS STILL BEING WORKED OUT AMONG THE COMPANIES AND THE E-P-A … AND THEY MUST PRESENT ANY PROPOSALS THEY COME UP WITH TO THE COMMUNITY FOR FEEDBACK.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>AND THAT’S IMPORTANT. IT’S THE COMMUNITY WHO ARE THE ONES WHO LIVE AND PLAY AND WORK AROUND THE CREEK… IN SPITE OF HOW GROSS IT CAN BE.</p>
<p>THERE ARE BIRDERS WHO APPRECIATE FINDING PEACE ALONG THE WATER… EVEN WITH SOUNDS OF THE HIGHWAY IN THE BACKGROUND. STUDENTS LEARN ALONG THE BANKS AND SEE TINY FISH SWIMMING IN THE WATER.</p>
<p>AND… ALTHOUGH NEWTOWN CREEK IS NO LONGER THE ECONOMIC POWERHOUSE IT ONCE WAS… IT IS STILL AN ACTIVE COMMERCIAL ZONE.</p>
<p>ALL KINDS OF BUSINESSES OPERATE ALONG THE WATER…BEVERAGE DISTRIBUTORS… RESTAURANT SUPPLY COMPANIES… FURNITURE MAKERS… AND MORE.</p>
<p>**[MUX FADE: “1st go Interstitial 4 - Hopeful”] **</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **You know, one thing we're really interested in is, like, how the creek can be an example of both an industrial space that also has significant ecological function and community access and benefit.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>WILLIS AND OTHERS WHO CARE ABOUT NEWTOWN CREEK SEE A FUTURE FOR IT THAT’S NOT SO DIFFERENT FROM HOW IT IS NOW. THEY JUST WANT IT CLEANER AND HEALTHIER.</p>
<p>**Willis Elkins: **We're not just doing this for, like, the residents that live in the surrounding areas or for tourists; it's for also the people that are working here every day that they should deserve to be able to work in a place that doesn't have legacy contamination.</p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong></p>
<p>THAT’S THE IDEAL OUTCOME FOR LAURA HOFMANN. SHE LIVES JUST A FEW BLOCKS AWAY FROM THE CREEK.</p>
<p>LAURA REMEMBERS THE FIRST TIME SHE SAW THE CREEK BY BOAT ABOUT TWO DECADES AGO.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **We went to, like, the most polluted parts and we saw, like, all this black and a black muck on top, and the odor just hit us in the face. And I remember that I got teary eyed, I got angry because this is like being in the belly of the beast. I can't even explain it when you've gone through all of these environmental disorders and, you know, medical issues, this is like being in the belly of the beast. it's just so powerful being there that I just started crying, you know? I carry that with me when I go to different meetings.</p>
<p><strong>SM VO</strong></p>
<p>SHE’S SEEN LOTS OF THINGS AROUND THE CREEK CHANGE FOR THE BETTER OVER THE YEARS.</p>
<p>EVEN AS THE PROGRESS TO FULLY CLEAN UP THE CREEK SEEMS SO SLOW…  KNOWING THAT PEOPLE TAKE TO THE WATER GIVES HER HOPE THAT THE AREA WILL IMPROVE EVEN MORE.</p>
<p>**Laura Hoffman: **I know, a lot of people think that they're crazy for going on the creek in the kayaks and stuff, but they're, like, you know, frontiersman; they're forcing the agencies to look at the quality and the standards for the creek just for the simple fact that they're there and using the creek in that way.</p>
<p><strong>[THEME MUX IN]</strong></p>
<p><strong>JGP VO</strong> <strong>[CREDITS]</strong></p>
<p>THIS HAS BEEN EPISODE ONE OF HAZARD N-Y-C… A SPECIAL FOUR PART LIMITED SERIES FROM F-A-Q N-Y-C.</p>
<p>THE SHOW IS WRITTEN AND HOSTED BY SAMANTHA MALDONADO…</p>
<p>AND ME… JORDAN GASS-POORE… THE CREATOR AND EDITOR OF THE SHOW.</p>
<p>OUR ENGINEERS ARE ADAM CHIMERA AND MARK BUSH… WHO ALSO DID OUR SOUND DESIGN.</p>
<p>MUSIC FOR THE SHOW WAS COMPOSED BY NICK PENNINGTON.</p>
<p>ARTWORK BY MATTHEW FLEMING.</p>
<p>COME BACK TOMORROW TO HEAR EPISODE TWO.</p>
<p><strong>[THEME MUX OUT]</strong></p>
<p>**HS VO [POST-ROLL] **</p>
<p>FAQ NYC is part of The City, a nonprofit, nonpartisan newsroom dedicated to hard-hitting reporting that serves the people of New York. Our work is freely available to everyone, and is supported by listeners and readers like you — go to the city dot nyc slash give if you’d like to pitch in. Harry Siegel is FAQ NYC’s executive producer. The pod also receives support from P&amp;T Knitwear, an independent bookstore, cafe, and event space on Manhattan's Lower East Side with a podcast studio that can be freely reserved for community use. The pod is a proud member of the Brickhouse cooperative of independent journalists, critics and artists, and is affiliated with the Colin Powell School at CUNY’s City College where co-host Christina Greer is one of the Moynihan Public Scholars inaugural fellows.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="42259328" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://aphid.fireside.fm/d/1437767933/77c0e88f-43d7-42c8-9e27-504220a0287b/71348c6f-22aa-4c9e-a62b-9f82ea9abf22.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:17:36</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - New York: Trailer</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-09-hazard-nyc-trailer/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 02:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-09-hazard-nyc-trailer/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HAZARD_NYC_3000x3000.png" />
		<description>New podcast series highlights the intersection of pollution and climate change in the NYC.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[New podcast series highlights the intersection of pollution and climate change in the NYC.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hazard will be exploring NYC soon!</p>
<p>Check out Hazard NYC, a four-part limited series from FAQ NYC that explores how climate change affects the city's Superfund sites. Follow Samantha Maldonado, a senior reporter at THE CITY, and independent journalist Jordan Gass-Pooré on a tour of New York City's dirtiest places and what's at stake with the cleanups—before it's too late. Hazard NYC is produced by the nonprofit news outlet The City. Find Hazard NYC under the FAQ NYC banner.</p>
<video controls="" width="100%">
  <source src="https://hazardpodcast.com/assets/podcasts/Hazard_NYC_Trailer.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
<p>Download the<br />
<a href="https://hazardpodcast.com/assets/podcasts/Hazard_NYC_Trailer.mp4">video</a>.<br />
</p></video><p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="3603968" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://hazardpodcast.com/assets/podcasts//Hazard-NYC-Trailer_MB_FINAL_01102024.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:01:30</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: REWIND: Happy Earth Day from Hazard NJ</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08b-rewind-happy-earth-day-from-hazard/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08b-rewind-happy-earth-day-from-hazard/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Happy Earth Day from Hazard NJ and NJ Spotlight News! Get ready for season 2.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Happy Earth Day from Hazard NJ and NJ Spotlight News! Get ready for season 2.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="REWIND: Happy Earth Day from Hazard NJ" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=jechd-13eb51b-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>Happy Earth Day from Hazard NJ and NJ Spotlight News! Thank you all for taking the time to listen to our podcast, and learn about the ways in which climate change is impacting some of New Jersey’s most toxic places. We’re happy to say that we are already working on our next season, which will take a hard look at a new pollution threat in the Garden State and beyond: PFAS, also called “forever chemicals.” We’ll have more on that soon, but for now, here’s a look back at the second half of Season 1.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="42308970" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/xe9q8x/Hazard-NJ_Bonus-Episode_Earth-Day_Final.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:29:22</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: Small Steps, Big Money for the Passaic</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08a-bonus-small-steps-big-money-for-passaic/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08a-bonus-small-steps-big-money-for-passaic/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>One of the main companies on the hook for the work is pushing hard against a deal the EPA has made with other polluters.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[One of the main companies on the hook for the work is pushing hard against a deal the EPA has made with other polluters.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="BONUS EPISODE: Small Steps, Big Money for the Passaic" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=c62nq-13b2901-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>Small steps forward this week on the clean-up of the lower Passaic River, where past dumping of Agent Orange and other chemicals created a toxic mess that is now one of the nation’s largest Superfund sites. But that progress comes as one of the main companies on the hook for the work is pushing hard against a deal the EPA has made with other polluters.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="9194194" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/ff64ze/Hazard-NJ_Bonus-EP_OxyChem.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:06:22</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - The Resurrection of Price’s Pit - Season 1: Episode 8</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08-the-resurrection-of-price-pit/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 17:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-08-the-resurrection-of-price-pit/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>A once-notorious Superfund site could become a key part of New Jersey’s clean-energy future.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[A once-notorious Superfund site could become a key part of New Jersey’s clean-energy future.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 8: The Resurrection of Price’s Pit" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=xe6x4-1374072-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>The decades-long drip, drip, drip of toxic chemicals from the Price Landfill in South Jersey reached crisis levels in the early '80s when the hazardous plume threatened to taint the water supply for the Atlantic City area.</p>
<p>The site earned an emergency response and a reputation as the most polluted Superfund site in America. Now, more than 40 years later, the Price Landfill has entered a new chapter. And this time it's helping, not harming.</p>
<p>*Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at *<em><a href="http://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host **</p>
<p>FOR FUNDAMENTAL AND DEEPLY ROOTED PSYCHOLOGICAL REASONS... AS WELL AS MORE MUNDANE UTILITARIAN CONSIDERATIONS... IT IS CHARACTERISTIC OF MAN TO BURY THAT WHICH HE FEARS AND WISHES TO RID HIMSELF OF.</p>
<p>IN THE PAST... THIS ENGRAINED PATTERN OF BEHAVIOR HAS GENERALLY PROVEN HARMLESS AND... INDEED... HAS OFTEN LEFT MAN TO RESTORE TO THE EARTH THE SUBSTANCES HE HAD REMOVED FROM IT.</p>
<p>IN TODAY'S INDUSTRIALIZED SOCIETY... HOWEVER... THE ROUTINE PRACTICE OF BURYING HIGHLY TOXIC CHEMICAL WASTES HAS RESULTED IN SERIOUS THREATS TO THE ENVIRONMENT AND TO PUBLIC HEALTH.</p>
<p>THAT WAS PART OF THE CASE OPINION IN 1981 FROM STANLEY BROTTMAN... A FORMER FEDERAL JUDGE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>HE WAS TALKING ABOUT THE PRICES... A FAMILY WHO KNOWINGLY ALLOWED TOXIC CHEMICALS TO BE DUMPED NEAR AN AQUIFER ON THEIR LANDFILL IN PLEASANTVILLE NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>WELL... THE DIRT ON THE PRICES HAD BEEN REPEATEDLY DUG UP... AND FOR DECADES IT SEEMED LIKE THE SCARS WOULD NEVER FADE.</p>
<p>BUT PRICE'S PIT... REFERRED TO AS THE &quot;GRANDFATHER OF SUPERFUND SITES&quot;... WAS NOT ONLY TURNED INTO A MUSICAL... I KID YOU NOT... BUT HAS GOTTEN A MAKEOVER AS A RENEWABLE ENERGY FACILITY THAT COULD ACTUALLY <em>HELP</em> FIGHT CLIMATE CHANGE.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>AS A KID... I WOULD GO TO MY FAMILY'S RANCH IN THE TEXAS HILL COUNTRY DURING THE SUMMER. IT WAS NO LONGER AN OPERATING RANCH... AND THERE WERE NO LONGHORNS... OR HORSES. SORRY.</p>
<p>BECAUSE THE RANCH WAS IN THE MIDDLE OF NOWHERE AT THE TIME... WE WOULD BURN AND BURY OUR TRASH.</p>
<p>SOMETIMES I'D BE DIGGING HOLES AROUND THE PROPERTY... BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT WE DID FOR FUN... AND I'D FIND OLD GLASS BOTTLES... NAILS... AND OTHER STUFF MY ANCESTORS BURIED.</p>
<p>OUR TRASH UNITED US IN THIS STRUGGLE TO... ON ONE HAND... BURY THE PAST... AND ON THE OTHER... LEAVE THESE REMNANTS BEHIND TO BE FOUND LATER AS A REMINDER OF OUR EXISTENCE.</p>
<p>DRIP... DRIP... DRIP.</p>
<p>CHEMICAL WASTE LEACHED FROM THE BOTTOM OF PRICE LANDFILL... THROUGH THE SANDY SOIL UNDERNEATH... AND INTO THE PERSONAL WELLS OF RESIDENTS IN THE SMALL TOWN OF PLEASANTVILLE.</p>
<p>TRACES OF BENZENE... THALLIUM... AND ARSENIC... CREEPED CLOSER AND CLOSER TO THE WELL FIELD THAT SUPPLIED DRINKING WATER TO NEARBY ATLANTIC CITY...</p>
<p>BEFORE CONTAMINATING A SEGMENT OF THE WELL FIELD... A MILE AWAY FROM THE SITE.</p>
<p>THIS IS HOW AN ATLANTIC COUNTY HEALTH OFFICIAL DESCRIBED THE PROBLEM BACK IN 1981.</p>
<p><strong>Alice Gitchell <strong>--</strong> Atlantic County Health Department</strong></p>
<p>It's clear that a large quantity of chemicals is in the ground and is moving in the direction of the Atlantic City well field. And this is certainly extreme cause for concern.</p>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host **</p>
<p>THIS CONTAMINATION WAS SO BAD THAT EVEN DECADES LATER... FORMER NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR... THE LATE JIM FLORIO... CITED IT AS ONE OF THE WORST OF THE WORST.  THIS IS HOW HE DESCRIBED THE SITE TO ME IN AN INTERVIEW BEFORE HE DIED.</p>
<p><strong>Gov. Jim Florio -- D, NJ 1st Congressional District 1975-1990, Governor 1990-1994</strong></p>
<p>Price's Pit, which is down in Atlantic City, which was a plume of pollution that was headed towards the aquifer. And we got to the aquifer, you have bad water for half of South Jersey.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ATLANTIC CITY HAD LITTLE CHOICE BUT TO ABANDON ITS WELLS IN FAVOR OF A NEW FIELD SITE.</p>
<p>MANY RESIDENTS OF THE UNINCORPORATED COMMUNITIES NEAR PRICE LANDFILL WERE NOT HOOKED UP TO ANY MUNICIPAL WATER SYSTEM. INSTEAD... THEY RELIED ON INDIVIDUAL PRIVATE WELLS.</p>
<p><strong>Don Torrance -- New Jersey Nightlight News</strong></p>
<p>So you drink it, and it gives you pain in the stomach?</p>
<p><strong>Gregory Woodson -- Pleasantville Resident</strong></p>
<p>Yeah, right here.</p>
<p><strong>Don Torrance -- New Jersey Nightlight News</strong></p>
<p>Really? Have you been to the doctor?</p>
<p><strong>Gregory Woodson -- Pleasantville Resident</strong></p>
<p>No. It only happens when I drink the water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AT THE TIME... RESIDENTS OF NEARBY EGG HARBOR TOWNSHIP FLEW WHITE FLAGS THREE DAYS A WEEK TO SIGNAL THEIR NEED TO HAVE WATER DELIVERED.</p>
<p>EACH HOUSEHOLD RECEIVED 15 GALLONS OF WATER EACH DELIVERY DAY.</p>
<p>THIS EVENT MAY HAVE HAPPENED IN THE 1980s... BUT THE SITE STILL LEAVES A BAD TASTE IN THE MOUTHS OF SOME LOCALS.</p>
<p>PRICE LANDFILL... AFFECTIONATELY KNOWN AS PRICE'S PIT... WAS ONE OF THE FIRST DESIGNATED SUPERFUND SITES IN THE COUNTRY.</p>
<p>IT'S TAKEN DECADES TO CLEAN UP THE 26-ACRE SITE... AS LAWSUITS WOUND THEIR WAY THROUGH THE COURTS AND A TANGLE OF FEDERAL AND STATE AGENCIES WORKED OUT A PERMANENT FIX TO THE TOXIC STEW.</p>
<p>PRICE LANDFILL WAS STARTED BY CHARLES PRICE AS A SAND AND GRAVEL MINING OPERATION IN 1960... BEFORE IT BECAME A COMMERCIAL SOLID WASTE LANDFILL IN 1971.</p>
<p>COMMON PRACTICE AT LANDFILLS IN THE 1970s WAS TO DUMP CHEMICALS ON TOP OF THE TRASH BECAUSE THE TRASH WOULD ACT AS A FILTER.</p>
<p>THE TRASH... OF COURSE... DIDN'T FILTER ANYTHING.</p>
<p>CHEMICAL WASTE WAS OPENLY POURED FROM AN OPEN SPIGOT ON TANK TRUCKS... AND DRUMS WERE BURIED IN SHALLOW PITS UNDERNEATH THE TRASH. SOME OF THESE DRUMS ARE REPORTED TO HAVE BEEN PUNCTURED.</p>
<p>LIQUID WASTE FROM THE ATLANTIC CITY ELECTRIC COMPANY AND AT LEAST 36 OTHER COMPANIES WAS DISPOSED ON THE SITE FOR EIGHT YEARS.</p>
<p>BY THE TIME THE LANDFILL CLOSED... THE EPA DETERMINED THAT 9 MILLION GALLONS OF TOXIC WASTE HAD BEEN DUMPED.  YES... I SAID 9 <em>MILLION</em> GALLONS.</p>
<p>THE DAMAGE HAD BEEN DONE. AND... ACCORDING TO COURT DOCUMENTS... CHARLES PRICE KNEW ABOUT IT ALL ALONG.</p>
<p>HE WORKED AT THE SITE FROM 1969 UNTIL IT CLOSED IN 1976... SUPERVISING OTHER WORKERS AND DIRECTING THEM TO DISPOSE OF THE WASTE THAT CONTAMINATED THE GROUNDWATER... SOIL... AND NEARBY CREEKS.</p>
<p>CHARLES PRICE... KNOWN TO HIS FAMILY AND FRIENDS AS &quot;BUB&quot;... WAS... AN INTERESTING MAN. I'LL LET HIS NIECE DAWN PRICE BROWN DESCRIBE HIM.</p>
<p><strong>Dawn Price Brown -- Niece of Charles Price</strong></p>
<p>Bub was a jerk. And my whole family was pretty much you know, they were bad, all of them. So, I'm sorry.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DAWN WROTE A SCREENPLAY ABOUT HER FAMILY'S INVOLVEMENT WITH THE SUPERFUND SITE. IT'S CALLED &quot;THE PRICE OF DIRT.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Dawn Price Brown -- Niece of Charles Price</strong></p>
<p>Go to sleep, little town. Wake up tomorrow with no frown. Life is simple, shoot the breeze. Walk to the bay, do as you please. Those who live here, friendly and such, ain't got much money but lot's of luck. Yet, X is waiting.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>&quot;X&quot;... BY THE WAY... IS BUB... CHARLES PRICE. HE'D SIGN HIS NAME WITH AN X.</p>
<p><strong>Dawn Price Brown -- Niece of Charles Price</strong></p>
<p>With no fear -- Money he wants, land to clear. Life's unsure; what will remain? Dump it all, forget the blame; think nothing of it.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THOSE ARE LYRICS FROM ONE OF THE SONGS DAWN WROTE FOR &quot;THE PRICE OF DIRT&quot;... THE MUSICAL WHICH NEVER GOT PRODUCED... BUT DIGGING UP THIS FAMILY HISTORY WAS A FORCED RECKONING FOR DAWN.</p>
<p><strong>Dawn Price Brown -- Niece of Charles Price</strong></p>
<p>The people said they couldn't go outside because they guess they would get sick, they couldn't take a bath. They couldn't wash their clothes because their clothes were yellow. And it said hear that the chickens were dying and the windows were shut because of the stink.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE SEARCH TURNED UP HARD TRUTHS.</p>
<p><strong>Dawn Price Brown -- Niece of Charles Price</strong></p>
<p>Bub would tell these people, like Atlantic City Electric and whatever, to come after nine o'clock, into the pit. And there the entrance was, I think it was on Fire Road in Pleasantville. And they would give him an envelope and he would let them dump their crap in there, their chemicals.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE DUMPING WENT ON FOR YEARS... EVENTUALLY LEAVING WATER UNDRINKABLE FOR DOZENS OF NEIGHBORS. ATLANTIC CITY LEADERS PANICKED ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE RESORT'S WATER SUPPLY.</p>
<p>IN THE END... 49 COMPANIES WERE HELD LIABLE FOR THE DAMAGE DONE AT THE SITE... INCLUDING ATLANTIC CITY ELECTRIC... DU PONT... FORD MOTOR COMPANY... GENERAL MILLS... AND PROCTER AND GAMBLE.</p>
<p>THE CONTAMINATED WELLS... OR THOSE THOUGHT TO BE THREATENED WITH CONTAMINATION... WERE SHUT DOWN. THOSE 37 HOUSEHOLDS SWITCHED FROM WELL TO UTILITY WATER.</p>
<p>THE EPA GOT INVOLVED WITH THE SITE'S CLEANUP IN 1982.</p>
<p>A YEAR LATER... PRICE LANDFILL WAS ADDED TO THE NATIONAL PRIORITIES LIST... BECOMING ONE OF THE COUNTRY'S FIRST SUPERFUND SITES. AND THE EPA'S BEEN CONTINUING TO MONITOR AND TREAT THE GROUNDWATER EVER SINCE.</p>
<p>IN 2013... A 50 MILLION DOLLAR WASTEWATER TREATMENT FACILITY WAS BUILT ACROSS THE STREET FROM THE SITE TO REMOVE THE MAJORITY OF THE TOXIC CHEMICALS FROM THE GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p>IT WORKS BY HAVING WELLS AT VARYING DEPTHS ON THE SITE PUMP THE GROUNDWATER TO THE TREATMENT PLANT. ONCE THERE... THE WATER IS TREATED AND THEN RELEASED INTO THE ATLANTIC OCEAN.</p>
<p>THE EPA ESTIMATES IT'LL TAKE AT LEAST 25 YEARS... AND ABOUT 70 MILLION DOLLARS BEFORE THE GROUNDWATER IS CLEAN.</p>
<p>PERRY KATZ... EPA PROJECT MANAGER FOR PRICE LANDFILL... SAYS THE SITE'S CAP AND WASTEWATER TREATMENT FACILITY HAVE HELPED PREVENT ANY FURTHER CONTAMINATION.</p>
<p><strong>Perry Katz -- Project Manager for Price Landfill, EPA</strong></p>
<p>Nobody's drinking the groundwater. There's no landfill gas emanating from the landfill. You know, vapor intrusion was addressed a while ago by the state of New Jersey, that there's no issue there. So, you know, from our perspective, any potential exposures, you know, they're not there.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MANY OF THE TREATMENT FACILITY'S SYSTEMS ARE AUTOMATED... WHICH MEANS IF ANYTHING GOES HAYWIRE IN THE MIDDLE OF THE NIGHT... STAFF CAN REMOTELY TRY AND FIX IT BEFORE GOING TO THE OFFICE.</p>
<p>THIS FACILITY TREATS ABOUT 10-TO-12 GALLONS OF WATER A MONTH... BREAKING DOWN THOSE TOXIC CHEMICALS FROM THE SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>AS PART OF THE OVERALL CLEANUP... PERRY SAYS THE SITE WAS CAPPED IN 2015 TO KEEP CHEMICALS IN PLACE TO PREVENT THEM FROM SPREADING.</p>
<p><strong>Perry Katz -- Project Manager for Price Landfill, EPA</strong></p>
<p>It's a multi-layer impermeable cap, proven technology, you know, you'd have to have a pretty substantial event to start talking about layers of the cap being disrupted to the point where anything would be exposed. I mean, that's what would have to happen before you start worrying about any of the contents of the landfill moving around.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DECADES AFTER ATLANTIC CITY AVOIDED THE CRISIS OF POISONED DRINKING WATER FROM THE PRICE'S PIT POLLUTION... THE CITY NOW FACES A MORE EXISTENTIAL THREAT... RAPID SEA LEVEL RISE.</p>
<p>THE OCEAN AND BAYS SURROUNDING ATLANTIC CITY ARE CREEPING UP NEARLY TWICE AS FAST AS THE GLOBAL AVERAGE.</p>
<p>THESE DAYS... HIGHWAYS LEADING INTO TOWN REGULARLY FLOOD... AS DO MANY OF THE LOW-LYING NEIGHBORHOODS.</p>
<p>BY 2050... FEDERAL SCIENTISTS PREDICT ATLANTIC CITY WILL FACE UP TO 110 DAYS OF SUNNY DAY FLOODING EACH YEAR.</p>
<p>SLOWING SEA LEVEL RISE MEANS STOPPING CLIMATE CHANGE... AND THE KEY TO THAT IS TO STOP THE BURNING OF FOSSIL FUELS.</p>
<p>IN THIS WAY... PRICE'S PIT MAY BE A BRIGHT SPOT IN THE SUPERFUND PROGRAM.</p>
<p>TODAY... PRICE LANDFILL IS AN INNOCUOUS GRASSY FIELD WITH A FENCE AROUND IT.</p>
<p>IT LOOKS LIKE ANY OTHER SUPERFUND SITE... EXCEPT FOR THE HUNDREDS OF SOLAR PANELS. PRICE'S PIT HAS FOUND NEW LIFE AS A SOLAR FARM, GENERATING SOME OF THE CARBON-FREE ELECTRICITY THAT CLIMATE EXPERTS SAY WE SO DESPERATELY NEED.</p>
<p>THIS IS PART OF A TREND TO REUSE FORMER TOXIC SITES.</p>
<p>PERRY SAYS THE LAND ISN'T SUITABLE FOR MUCH ELSE.</p>
<p><strong>Perry Katz -- Project Manager for Price Landfill, EPA</strong></p>
<p>There's a kind of the greater good benefit where you're using renewable energy to put into the energy grid. There's beneficial reuse to the landfill. We wouldn't be building houses out there, but in the context of what type of beneficial uses available, I mean, from an economic standpoint, this is more beneficial than if it were just a walking trail, which they do at some landfills. You're limited in what you can do once they're cleaned up in the sense that there can, you know, kept and contained. So, you know,  this works all the way around, really, and it doesn't impede anything we're trying to do.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE CONTAMINATED GROUNDWATER STILL AT THE SITE MEANS THAT BREAKING GROUND ISN'T AN OPTION.</p>
<p>BUT IT IS STILL POSSIBLE TO PUT SOLAR PANELS ON TOP OF THE OLD DUMP. THE SOLAR PANELS AT PRICE LANDFILL BEGAN OPERATING IN MID 2020... AND PRODUCE ENOUGH POWER FOR ABOUT 4,020 HOUSEHOLDS EVERY YEAR.</p>
<p>THAT IDEA IS GAINING TRACTION ACROSS NEW JERSEY AND THE U-S. ACCORDING TO THE EPA... AT LEAST 12SUPERFUND SITES IN THE STATE... AND AT LEAST 57 ACROSS THE COUNTRY HAVE BEEN REDEVELOPED AS RENEWABLE ENERGY INFRASTRUCTURE.</p>
<p><strong>Jaclyn Kondrk -- Remedial Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>I'd say definitely a popular one is solar because a lot of these properties are large and flat, and that's really the most feasible property that you're looking at for a solar project.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S JACKIE KONDRK. SHE'S THE EPA'S REMEDIAL PROJECT MANAGER WHO OVERSEES THE REDEVELOPMENT OF SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p><strong>Jaclyn Kondrk -- Remedial Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>Solar is really a great option, because there's not much else you could do with it. We want to use these sites that would otherwise not be used likely at all.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JACKIE SAYS LOCALS BENEFIT ECONOMICALLY FROM PUTTING SOLAR PANELS ON SUPERFUND SITES IN THEIR COMMUNITIES.</p>
<p><strong>Jaclyn Kondrk -- Remedial Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>I think there's multiple benefits. One is a more affordable energy, hopefully. There's also jobs that come in through doing those projects. And there's a program through the Superfund redevelopment program, that actually helps train people to do the cleanup at the sites and to facilitate these types of reuse too.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SUPERFUND SITES DOT THE GARDEN STATE, AND MANY OF THEM ARE BECOMING SOLAR FARMS.</p>
<p>NOT FAR FROM PRICE'S PIT... THE DELILAH ROAD SUPERFUND SITE BECAME HOME TO A SOLAR FARM IN 2016.</p>
<p>SOLAR PANELS NOW COVER LARGE PARTS OF THE INFAMOUS CIBA-GEIGY SITE IN TOMS RIVER.</p>
<p>AND JUST LAST MONTH IN NORTH JERSEY... THE COMBE FILL NORTH SUPERFUND SITE BECAME THE LARGEST LANDFILL-SOLAR CONVERSION IN NORTH AMERICA.</p>
<p>THE SITE HAS MORE THAN 50,000 SOLAR PANELS... ENOUGH TO GENERATE ELECTRICITY TO POWER 4,000 HOMES.</p>
<p>THESE PROJECTS... AND OTHERS LIKE THEM... ARE CRITICAL TO REACHING A NEWLY SET STATE TARGET. THE GOAL IS TO BUILD 40 MEGAWATTS WORTH OF SOLAR POWER ON LANDFILLS AND OTHER CONTAMINATED SITES IN THE NEXT THREE YEARS.</p>
<p><strong>Governor Phil Murphy</strong></p>
<p>For most of its life, this site represented our throwaway culture, with all the long-term challenges that that way of living produced. But today, it represents a more sustainable and energy resilient New Jersey and all the opportunities that we are just beginning to realize.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Composer – Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Art – Matthew Fleming</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="42259328" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/4efhfp/Hazard-NJ_Episode-Eight_MB_FINAL_01242023_16b0eq.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:17:36</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: The Hackensack’s Comeback Moves Ahead</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07b-polluters-pay-up-on-the-passaic/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07b-polluters-pay-up-on-the-passaic/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="BONUS Episode: Polluters Pay Up on the Passaic" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=4zzp3-133e0c4-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>Efforts to clean up the lower stretch of the Passaic River are getting a $150 million boost, thanks to a new settlement between the federal government and 85 likely polluters. This stretch of the river, running through Newark and nearby towns, is coated with a lining of toxic mud, tainted by decades and decades of chemical dumping. Getting it cleaned up will be difficult – and expensive. At roughly $1.8 billion, the Passaic River is estimated to be the costliest project currently facing the EPA’s Superfund program. That makes the settlement a small, but welcome, step forward.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="7081519" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/y66agk/Hazard-N-J-Bonus_Passaic-Settlement.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:04:54</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ Episode Swap: Damages: Wild Rice Goes to Court</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07a-damages-wild-rice-goes-to-court/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07a-damages-wild-rice-goes-to-court/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Damages host Amy Westervelt takes listeners to Minnesota, where the rights of threatened wild rice are considered in the face of efforts to build the Line 3 pipeline.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Damages host Amy Westervelt takes listeners to Minnesota, where the rights of threatened wild rice are considered in the face of efforts to build the Line 3 pipeline.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Damages: Wild Rice Goes to Court" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=tdjb4-13328bc-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>We’re bringing you a special <a href="https://www.drilledpodcast.com/damages/#ep-1-manoomin-v-minnesota" target="_blank">episode from the podcast “Damages”</a>, which examines court cases that matter in the fight against climate change. In this episode, “Damages” host Amy Westervelt takes listeners to Minnesota, where the rights of threatened wild rice (or manoomin in the Ojibwe language) are considered in the face of efforts to build the Line 3 pipeline across the state. Check it out, and <a href="https://www.drilledpodcast.com/damages/" target="_blank">be sure to follow “Damages” wherever you get your podcasts</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="45683770" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/f6aw7r/Hazard-NJ_Damages-Bonus-Episode.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:31:42</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - A Headache on the Hudson - Season 1: Episode 7</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07-a-headache-on-the-hudson-edgewater-mothballs-superfund/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 17:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-07-a-headache-on-the-hudson-edgewater-mothballs-superfund/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>The cleanup of Edgewater drags on and the climate change threat from flooding grows.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[The cleanup of Edgewater drags on and the climate change threat from flooding grows.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 7:  A Headache on the Hudson" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=e4df6-132af49-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>In Edgewater, a bustling urban town across the Hudson River from Manhattan, a polluted lot of a former factory sits right on the water. Today it’s a Superfund site being cleaned up, set to one day become a piece of prime real estate for redevelopment. But that cleanup has created problems of its own, and as the process drags on, the threat of flooding from the river grows.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE SMELL OF MOTHBALLS MYSTERIOUSLY WAFTED THROUGH MUCH OF EDGEWATER, NEW JERSEY IN 2017.</p>
<p>THE SMELL CAUSED SOME PEOPLE TO HAVE HEADACHES... BURNING EYES... AND NAUSEA.</p>
<p>THIS WENT ON FOR MONTHS... UNTIL RESIDENTS DISCOVERED THE SOURCE OF THE ODOR... THE QUANTA SUPERFUND SITE... WHICH SITS JUST FEET AWAY FROM THE HUDSON RIVER.</p>
<p>AND THERE WAS A REASON IT SMELLED LIKE MOTHBALLS.</p>
<p>CONSTRUCTION AT THE QUANTA SITE HAD RELEASED NAPHTHALENE... A HAZARDOUS AIR POLLUTANT... AND THE MAIN INGREDIENT IN... YOU GUESSED IT... MOTHBALLS.</p>
<p>BUT WITH CLIMATE CHANGE INCREASING STORM SURGE FLOODING IN NEW JERSEY... THE SMELL MAY BE THE LEAST OF THIS COMMUNITY'S WORRIES.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>I RECENTLY WENT BACK TO MY HOME STATE OF TEXAS AND VISITED HOUSTON AND SOME OF THE TOWNS NEARBY.</p>
<p>THIS AREA IS OIL COUNTRY... AND THE SMELLS PROVE IT.</p>
<p>DRIVING AROUND WITH THE WINDOWS ROLLED DOWN WAS A BAD IDEA. FIRST IT SMELLED LIKE ROTTING EGGS... THEN WEIRDLY LIKE COTTON CANDY... AND THEN BACK TO ROTTING EGGS.</p>
<p>I'VE HEARD SOME PEOPLE SAY THESE ARE THE SMELLS OF MONEY. I SAY THEY'RE THE SMELLS OF SICKNESS AND DESPAIR.</p>
<p>MOST SUBSTANCES THAT CAUSE FOUL SMELLS OUTDOORS AREN'T AT LEVELS THAT CAN HARM PEOPLE'S HEALTH.</p>
<p>THIS WAS THE CASE FOR THE SMELLS IN EDGEWATER. EPA OFFICIALS SAID AS MUCH BACK IN 2018... WHEN CONTRACTORS WERE OUT THERE DIGGING AROUND IN THE SOIL OF THE QUANTA SITE.</p>
<p>THEY WERE TRYING TO PREVENT COAL TAR AND OTHER OIL BYPRODUCTS FROM MIGRATING INTO THE HUDSON RIVER AND NEARBY PROPERTIES.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>Just because you smell, you know, a garbage truck passing by doesn't necessarily mean that it's harmful to you, it just means that it smells bad.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S MICHELE LANGA... AN ATTORNEY FOR THE NY/NJ BAYKEEPER. THEY'RE THE GROUP THAT ADVOCATES FOR CLEANING UP THE REGION'S WATERWAYS... AND IN EDGEWATER THAT MEANS KEEPING AN EYE ON THE QUANTA SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>The residents around we're having issues with smell, that sort of, like, moth barley kind of smell that comes from the remnants of what was here, and it smells as a nuisance on its own, right? Like, you can't open your windows, you can't really enjoy a breezy day, if it smells so bad that it makes you ill. And they determined that it wasn't anything that is physically harmful, just an odor, but the odor in-and-of itself is an issue too.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>TO CONTROL THE SMELLS... THE EPA AND CONTRACTORS WORKING AT THE QUANTA SITE PUT UP TENTS WHILE THEY CAPPED THE TOXIC MATERIAL IN CONCRETE TO PREVENT IT FROM SPREADING.</p>
<p>BUT THE SITE'S CONTAMINATED SEDIMENT IN THE HUDSON RIVER HASN'T BEEN CLEANED UP YET... AND THERE'S A RISK THAT THOSE TOXIC CHEMICALS WILL SPREAD FROM INCREASES IN STORM SURGES CAUSED BY MAJOR HURRICANES.</p>
<p>THE SITE CONTINUES TO POLLUTE THE HUDSON RIVER. SO MUCH SO THAT THE FISH IN THE WATER ARE UNSAFE TO EAT.</p>
<p>ON TOP OF THAT... THERE ARE ONGOING ISSUES AT THE SITE WITH STORMWATER RUN-OFF.</p>
<p>WITH ALL THAT PAVEMENT NEARBY... THERE'S NO WAY FOR THE WATER FROM RAIN AND SNOW TO SOAK INTO THE GROUND. SO... IT JUST RUNS OFF... INTO THE HUDSON RIVER... CARRYING WITH IT THE OIL THAT LEAKS FROM CARS AND OTHER POLLUTANTS.</p>
<p>THE AREA SURROUNDING THE SITE IS DENSELY PACKED WITH CONDOS... APARTMENTS... AND BUSINESSES... BUILT ON WHAT HAD BEEN AN INDUSTRIAL HUB DATING BACK MORE THAN A CENTURY.</p>
<p>I TOOK THE BUS FROM MANHATTAN TO EDGEWATER AND MET UP WITH TINA MACICA IN HER CONDO NEAR THE QUANTA SITE.</p>
<p>TINA SAYS SHE KNEW ABOUT THE SUPERFUND SITE BEFORE SHE MOVED IN... BUT WASN'T EXPECTING IT TO SMELL SO BAD.</p>
<p><strong>Tina Macica -- Edgewater Resident</strong></p>
<p>It was like mothballs, like an oily mothball smell. It was going on for months. And we were all complaining.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>EPA OFFICIALS SAID THEY DO NOT ANTICIPATE ANY LONG-TERM HEALTH EFFECTS FROM THE NAPHTHALENE VAPORS.</p>
<p>TINA'S CONDO... THE DUNKIN DONUTS I WENT TO AFTER OUR MEETING... THE PARKING GARAGE... THEY'RE ALL BUILT ON TOP OF NEW JERSEY'S LEGACY OF TOXIC INDUSTRY.</p>
<p>STARTING IN THE LATE EIGHTEEN HUNDREDS... THE QUANTA SITE WAS HOME TO VARIOUS COMPANIES THAT MANUFACTURED ROOFING AND PAVING MATERIALS... PRODUCED SULFURIC ACID... STORED AND RECYCLED WASTE OIL...</p>
<p>AND PROCESSED COAL TAR... A THICK... BLACK LIQUID THAT OCCURS WHEN COAL IS BURNED AT VERY HIGH TEMPERATURES.</p>
<p>PRODUCTS MADE FROM COAL TAR ARE USED TO TREAT A VARIETY OF SKIN CONDITIONS... AND AS A WATERPROOFING MATERIAL FOR ROOFS.</p>
<p>BUT SOME OF THE CHEMICALS IN COAL TAR ARE KNOWN TO BE PROBABLE HUMAN CARCINOGENS.</p>
<p>FOR DECADES... ALLIED CHEMICAL CORPORATION... WHICH WOULD BECOME HONEYWELL INTERNATIONAL... OPERATED A COAL TAR DISTILLATION PLANT ON THE SITE.</p>
<p>THE COMPANY SOLD THE PROPERTY IN THE 1970s... AND QUANTA RESOURCES STARTED USING THE SITE TO STORE AND RECYCLE WASTE OIL.</p>
<p>IN 1981... THE NEW JERSEY DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION SHUT DOWN THE COMPANY BECAUSE OF HIGH LEVELS OF PCBs FOUND IN THE STORED WASTE OIL.</p>
<p>THEIR INVESTIGATION FOUND STORAGE TANKS WITH A CAPACITY OF MORE THAN NINE MILLION GALLONS OF OIL... TAR... ASPHALT... SLUDGE... AND OTHER KNOWN AND UNKNOWN LIQUIDS.</p>
<p>SOME OF THESE TANKS HAD OVERFLOWED WITH RAINWATER... OTHERS HAD COLLAPSED AND SPILLED.</p>
<p>UNDER QUANTA'S MANAGEMENT... OIL LEAKED CONSTANTLY INTO THE HUDSON RIVER AND CONTAMINATED THE SOIL.</p>
<p>OVER THE YEARS... THE STATE DEP REMOVED THE STORAGE TANKS THEY COULD FIND... AND STARTED CLEANING UP THE SITE.</p>
<p>BUT THE DAMAGE HAD ALREADY BEEN DONE.</p>
<p>THE SITE LANGUISHED FOR YEARS UNTIL THE EPA TOOK IT OVER AND DESIGNATED IT A SUPERFUND SITE IN 2002.</p>
<p>BY THEN... EDGEWATER HAD TRANSFORMED FROM AN INDUSTRIAL HUB INTO A WEALTHY BEDROOM COMMUNITY.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Fallon -- Reporter, USA TODAY Network New Jersey</strong></p>
<p>So, you have a lot of people living right next to a Superfund site, probably more so than many other Superfund sites, not only in New Jersey, but across the nation.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S SCOTT FALLON... A SENIOR REPORTER WITH THE BERGEN RECORD WHO COVERS THE ENVIRONMENT.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Fallon -- Reporter, USA TODAY Network New Jersey</strong></p>
<p>You know, you think of a Superfund site, you think of a factory or a chemical plant, you know, that was built far away from where people live. That's not the case. People are right on top of it. These are very densely populated places; these homes are right up against a Superfund site. There's very little boundary between someone's bedroom and the pollution.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>EPA OFFICIALS SAID LIVING OR WORKING NEAR A SUPERFUND SITE DOES NOT NECESSARILY POSE A RISK TO PEOPLE'S HEALTH.</p>
<p>IN THE CASE OF THE QUANTA SITE... WHILE THERE IS CONTAMINATION IN THE GROUNDWATER... THE EPA SAID THAT'S NOT A SOURCE OF DRINKING WATER... AND THAT RESIDENTS AREN'T COMING INTO CONTACT WITH IT.</p>
<p>FOUND IN THE GROUNDWATER... SURFACE WATER... AND SOIL OF THE QUANTA SITE ARE LARGE QUANTITIES OF TOXIC CHEMICALS... LIKE ARSENIC AND BENZENE.</p>
<p>AND LIKE MOST OF THE SUPERFUND SITES COVERED ON THIS PODCAST... THE ONLY WAY MOST PEOPLE WOULD KNOW THE AREA IS TOXIC... IS BY READING THE EPA SIGNS ON THE CHAIN LINK FENCE THAT SURROUNDS THE SITE.</p>
<p>IN 2020... THE STATE OF NEW JERSEY SUED HONEYWELL... WHICH INHERITED THE CLEANUP LIABILITY FOR THE SITE... FOR ITS ROLE IN DESTROYING WETLANDS AND POLLUTING THE AREA.</p>
<p>TWO YEARS LATER... THAT CASE IS STILL ONGOING.</p>
<p>BY THE FOLLOWING YEAR... THE EPA REPORTED THAT HONEYWELL HAD CLEANED UP 90% OF THE CONTAMINATED SOIL AND GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>Many, many years ago the cleanup began.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HERE'S MICHELE... TALKING WITH ME ABOUT QUANTA'S CLEANUP HISTORY... RIGHT BY THE SITE ITSELF.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>This is kind of one of those sites where everything is kind of going the way it should be for the most part. So, we're just sort of, like, if there's a meeting we attend, if there's paperwork, we read it, but there hasn't really been a lot of need for intervention.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AS FOR THE POLLUTION SEEPING INTO THE HUDSON RIVER... CLEANUP IS STILL YEARS AWAY. THE EPA SAID IT DOESN'T EXPECT TO FINALIZE A PLAN FOR THAT WORK UNTIL THE FALL OF 2023.</p>
<p>I'VE BEEN TO THE QUANTA SITE TWICE NOW... AND EACH TIME I'VE TAKEN ADVANTAGE OF THE GOOD WEATHER AND WALKED ALONG THE JERSEY SIDE OF THE HUDSON RIVER... LOOKING OUT AT THE MANHATTAN SKYLINE.</p>
<p>I DEFINITELY SEE THE APPEAL OF LIVING NEAR THIS SUPERFUND SITE. IT'S ALSO REALLY CLOSE TO BUS STOPS AND THE FERRY TO NEW YORK CITY.</p>
<p>BUT I CAN'T QUITE GET OVER WHAT I SAW WHEN I LOOKED AT THE WATER NEAR TINA'S HOME... PATCHES OF OILY SHEENS FLOATING ON THE SURFACE OF THE HUDSON RIVER.</p>
<p>MICHELE SAYS A FEW YEARS AGO... THE EPA PUT UP BARRIERS IN THE WATER... SIMILAR TO THE ONES IN A POOL... TO CONTROL THE SPREAD OF OIL.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>The oil tends to sort of flow to the surface, so this just prevents it from flowing out into the main stem of the river, which would then carry it down tide. So, this kind of just keeps it here until somebody can come and, basically, just sort of scoop it out, which is good. I mean, this is the sort of thing that they use for just general, like, oil spill-type response. It just contains it doesn't, you know, remove it or anything like that. It just holds it in.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MICHELE DOES POINT OUT THAT THERE'S A PARKING LOT AND A PARKING GARAGE NEAR THE POLLUTED WATER... SO THE OIL COULD HAVE COME FROM STORMWATER RUNOFF... NOT THE QUANTA SITE.</p>
<p>BUT BECAUSE THE SUPERFUND SITE IS SO CLOSE TO THE HUDSON RIVER... NO ONE IS RULING IT OUT AS THE SOURCE OF CONTAMINATION.</p>
<p>AND AS THE CLIMATE CONTINUES TO CHANGE... STORM SURGES POSE A RISK FOR THE QUANTA SITE... AND THE RESIDENTS NEARBY.</p>
<p>SCOTT SAYS THIS HAS HAPPENED IN EDGEWATER BEFORE... DURING HURRICANE SANDY IN 2012.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Fallon -- Reporter, USA TODAY Network New Jersey</strong></p>
<p>How much did that spread the pollution? EPA has said that it didn't spread it that much, but how much of an investigation really went into that? I don't know. It's pretty much common sense that when you have a major storm event and major flooding events, with pollution that's in a riverbed, and pollution that is on land as well, that water is going to move that stuff. And Sandy happened long before they started work to clean up the Quanta site.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE CLEANUP DONE SO FAR AT THE QUANTA SITE REQUIRED ENTOMBING A CENTURIES' WORTH OF TOXIC CHEMICALS THROUGH A PROCESS THAT INVOLVES COMBINING A CONCRETE MIXTURE WITH CONTAMINATED SOIL.</p>
<p><strong>Tina Macica -- Edgewater Resident</strong></p>
<p>You know, you have a high water table here, we have a lot of local flooding.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>TINA SAYS SHE WOULD HAVE PREFERRED THE CONTAMINATED SOIL TO BE REMOVED FROM THE SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Tina Macica -- Edgewater Resident</strong></p>
<p>We have an issue here where everybody's building lot line to lot line, and not using their setbacks, they're not putting in storm mitigation measures. We're getting a lot more flooding here. So, you know, concrete only lasts for so long. I know they like to say, &quot;Oh, we have a certain strength of concrete,&quot; but over time that will start to break down again and be released into the environment.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WHICHEVER METHOD IS USED TO FINALLY FINISH CLEANING UP THE QUANTA SITE... MICHELE SAYS IT NEEDS TO BE CLEANED UP NOW.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>We're all in the same tight region together, where there's, like, millions of us here. If we don't plan for what's coming, it's really going to make it hard for all of us to live comfortably.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IF CLIMATE CHANGE DOESN'T SPUR CLEANUP EFFORTS... MAYBE DEVELOPMENT WILL.</p>
<p>THERE'S TALKS OF MIXED-USE... LUXURY APARTMENTS BEING BUILT ON THE QUANTA SITE ONCE IT'S CLEANED UP.</p>
<p>THAT MEANS MORE PEOPLE... MORE CARS... MORE POTENTIAL FOR CLIMATE-RELATED DISASTERS...</p>
<p>BUT MICHELLE SAYS IT DOESN'T HAVE TO BE THAT WAY IF COMMUNITIES WORK TOGETHER.</p>
<p><strong>Michele Langa -- Staff Attorney, NY/NJ Baykeeper</strong></p>
<p>You know, the state's been talking about their climate resiliency planning, things like that. You can't just have Edgewater developing, and then, you know, expect, everybody else is just going to do what they're going to do. And then nobody's talking to anybody -- that doesn't work.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Composer – Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Art – Matthew Fleming</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="26006016" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/ivkzif/Hazard-NJ_Episode-Seven.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:13:32</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ Episode Swap: Drilled: Industry Fights Back</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-06a-drilled-industry-fights-back/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-06a-drilled-industry-fights-back/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Drilled host Amy Westervelt takes a look at how the oil and gas industry has pushed to portray environmentalists as idealists detached from reality, in an effort to undercut campaigns against fossil fuels.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Drilled host Amy Westervelt takes a look at how the oil and gas industry has pushed to portray environmentalists as idealists detached from reality, in an effort to undercut campaigns against fossil fuels.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Drilled: Industry Fights Back" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=7zei9-131f1a1-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>We’re bringing you a special episode from the podcast “Drilled”, which scrutinizes the powers that have long profited from unfettered fossil fuel use. In this episode, “Drilled” host Amy Westervelt takes a look at how the oil and gas industry has pushed to portray environmentalists as idealists detached from reality, in an effort to undercut campaigns against fossil fuels. Check it out, and <a href="https://www.drilledpodcast.com/drilled-podcast/" target="_blank">be sure to follow “Drilled” wherever you get your podcasts</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="22966396" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/yyw9u7/Hazard-NJ_Bonus-Episode_Drilled.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:15:56</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - Toxic Sites in a Tinderbox - Season 1: Episode 6</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-06-toxic-sites-in-a-tinderbox-south-jersey-pinelands-wildfire-toxic-dumping/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 04:01:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-06-toxic-sites-in-a-tinderbox-south-jersey-pinelands-wildfire-toxic-dumping/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Climate change is making the wildfire season in the Pinelands more unpredictable.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Climate change is making the wildfire season in the Pinelands more unpredictable.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 6: Toxic Sites in a Tinderbox" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=fd88g-130f3ac-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>The Pinelands, a million-acre swath of pine forest dominating South Jersey, is one of America’s most unique environments. The Pinelands have always been a place prone to catch fire. Today, climate change is making the area’s wildfire season more unpredictable. The fear is not only fire, but its impact on the area’s legacy of illegal toxic dumping.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IT FORMED AT NIGHT... WHEN THEY WERE ASLEEP. CREEPING INTO THEIR HOMES... UNSEEN.</p>
<p>FOR THOSE WHO WERE STILL AWAKE... THE VIEW OUTSIDE THEIR WINDOWS WAS ALMOST ETHEREAL... A SOFT GLOW LIKE A FLAME FROM A CANDLE.</p>
<p>THIS HAPPENED FOR ABOUT AN HOUR-AND-A-HALF A FEW NIGHTS A WEEK... FOR NEARLY TWO YEARS.</p>
<p>DAYLIGHT ERASED THE ORANGE FOG THAT ENVELOPED THE SMALL COMMUNITY OF PEDRICKTOWN NEW JERSEY... NIGHT AFTER NIGHT.</p>
<p>BUT EVEN THOUGH RESIDENTS COULD NO LONGER SEE THE FOG... THE PROOF OF ITS EXISTENCE REMAINED.</p>
<p>THERE WERE UNEXPLAINED HEADACHES... AND PINHOLES IN THE ALUMINUM SIDING OF THEIR HOMES... AS IF THE FOG HAD GOTTEN HUNGRY.</p>
<p>IT WAS LIKE SOMETHING OUT OF A STEPHEN KING NOVEL... EXCEPT THE FOG'S ORIGINS WEREN'T SUPERNATURAL. IT CAME FROM THE SMOKESTACKS OF THE N-L INDUSTRIES PLANT.</p>
<p>IN 19-76... DANIELLE FLOOD WAS A YOUNG REPORTER FREELANCING FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES. A CAB DROPPED HER OFF IN PEDRICKTOWN ONE MORNING TO INVESTIGATE THE ORANGE FOG.</p>
<p><strong>Danielle Flood:</strong> I'm not sure that I remember seeing anything over two stories, I think it was all one stories or small houses around, not close, some were close actually. It looked like the houses were built and then somebody came and put this factory next to them and there was a big dump next to the factory with, I guess, about 500 car batteries dumped there.</p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE N-L INDUSTRIES PLANT RECOVERED LEAD FROM USED CAR BATTERIES. THEY DID THIS BY DRAINING THE BATTERIES OF SULFURIC ACID... AND THEN BREAKING THEM... ON THE GROUND.</p>
<p><strong>Danielle Flood:</strong> I talked to this one guy, he must have been retired or something. He was kind of old. And he was really upset, and I asked him what it was like to live next to, across the street from this factory that was reclaiming lead from car batteries. So, he said that he was not happy at all. And he showed me his car. The hood of his car, the paint had been eaten away.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>A FORMER N-L INDUSTRIES EMPLOYEE TOLD DANIELLE FOR HER ARTICLE THAT THE PLANT STORED THE CAR BATTERIES WAITING TO BE RECYCLED IN A DUMP BEHIND THE BUILDING.</p>
<p>WHEN IT RAINED ON THE BATTERIES... THE FORMER EMPLOYEE TOLD HER THAT LEAD AND SULFURIC ACID COULD LEAK INTO THE GROUND.</p>
<p>AND THAT'S A BIG PROBLEM. THE CAPE MAY AQUIFER LIES UNDER THE SITE... JUST ONE-AND-A-HALF MILES FROM THE DELAWARE RIVER.</p>
<p>JUST TO BE CLEAR... NEARBY WELLS NEVER DREW FROM THIS AQUIFER. INSTEAD... THEY TAPPED INTO DEEPER POCKETS OF WATER.</p>
<p>TODAY... EVEN THOUGH THE PLANT NO LONGER EXISTS... THE GROUNDWATER REMAINS CONTAMINATED WITH LEAD AND CADMIUM... TOXIC METALS THAT CAN CAUSE LEARNING PROBLEMS IN CHILDREN.</p>
<p>SALTWATER IS ALSO CREEPING INLAND AS CLIMATE CHANGE RAISES SEA LEVELS AND AMPLIFIES STORM SURGES AND FLOODING. ACROSS SOUTH JERSEY... THAT SLOW TRICKLE OF SALTWATER IS KILLING FORESTS... THREATENING FARMLAND... AND IMPERILING DRINKING WATER SUPPLIES.</p>
<p>SO... WHAT HAPPENS IF SALTWATER MIGRATES FROM THE OCEAN TO THE GROUNDWATER UNDERNEATH THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE?</p>
<p>IT MIGHT NOT BE A BAD THING. IN FACT... THE SALTWATER COULD HELP <em>LOCK</em> THE POLLUTION IN PLACE... RATHER THAN SPREADING IT.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>WHEN I WAS SIXTEEN... I WAS PART OF THIS LOCAL BEAUTY PAGEANT. IT WAS SOMETHING I WANTED TO DO TO PROVE A POINT. WHAT POINT THAT WAS... I CAN'T REMEMBER.</p>
<p>DURING THE PAGEANT... WE WERE ALL ASKED: WHAT IS THE MOST PRESSING PROBLEM FACING TEENS? MY RESPONSE: DEFORESTATION. THE AUDIENCE WAS SILENT. I DON'T THINK I EVEN GOT A CLAP FROM MY FAMILY WHO WERE THERE.</p>
<p>BELIEVE IT OR NOT... I DIDN'T WIN.</p>
<p>I'M MENTIONING THIS BECAUSE NO ONE BELIEVED ME. THEY DIDN'T THINK DEFORESTATION WAS A PROBLEM... IF THEY EVEN KNEW WHAT THAT WAS. ALL OF THE GREENPEACE STICKERS I STUCK AROUND TOWN COULDN'T CHANGE THEIR MINDS. IF THEY COULDN'T SEE IT... THEY COULDN'T BELIEVE IT.</p>
<p>MUCH LIKE THE ENVIRONMENTAL OFFICIALS IN THE SEVENTIES WHO WENT TO THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE NEAR PEDRICKTOWN NEW JERSEY... AFTER BEING MADE AWARE OF THE ORANGE FOG. THEY TOLD NEW YORK TIMES FREELANCE REPORTER DANIELLE FLOOD THAT THEY HAD TO SEE THE FOG THEMSELVES BEFORE THEY COULD DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT.</p>
<p>OKAY... I'LL JUST GET THIS OUT OF THE WAY: IT WAS NEVER PROVEN THAT N-L INDUSTRIES WAS THE SOURCE OF THE ORANGE FOG.</p>
<p>BUT IN THE EIGHTIES... NEW JERSEY'S DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION STILL FOUND THE COMPANY RESPONSIBLE FOR POLLUTING THE AIR WITH VARIOUS TOXIC CHEMICALS.</p>
<p>THE E-P-A PLACED THE SITE ON THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 19-83... AND THEY GOT TO WORK DEALING WITH THE LEAD IN THE SOIL AND GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p>NEARLY FORTY YEARS LATER... RENEE GELBLAT WITH THE E-P-A SAYS THE CONTAMINATED SOIL HAS BEEN REMOVED... AND NOW THE FOCUS IS ON THE GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> It's not really moving anywhere. It's kind of a big, little lake underneath part of the site. I mean, the water moves, but the lead and cadmium are not. We tested the two streams and it's not there.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>RENEE IS THE REMEDIAL PROJECT MANAGER FOR THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... JUST SOUTH OF PEDRICKTOWN.</p>
<p>SHE SAYS LEAD AND CADMIUM DON'T DISSOLVE IN WATER UNLESS IT'S REALLY ACIDIC. AND THE GROUNDWATER AT THIS FORTY-FOUR-ACRE SITE IS <em>STILL</em> PRETTY ACIDIC.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> It's down around four where it should be somewhere between six and eight. So, what we're doing is injecting, I mean, really simple would be, say, baking soda, it's a little more complicated than that, to bring the pH back toward neutral. And the tricky part is, in order to get the lead out of the water, you actually have to bring it up toward eight or nine. So, we have to make it basic, just to get it to come out of the solution. And then we'll let it go back down to, you know, six to eight, which is what's normal for the groundwater.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S BEING DONE BY INJECTING A PHOSPHATE REAGENT... BASICALLY A SUBSTANCE SIMILAR TO BAKING SODA... LIKE RENEE SAID... INTO THE POLLUTED GROUNDWATER TO RAISE THE P-H AND MAKE THE WATER LESS ACIDIC.</p>
<p>ONCE THE GROUNDWATER'S P-H IS RAISED HIGH ENOUGH... THE TOXIC METALS WILL STICK TO THE SOIL PARTICLES THAT ARE UNDERGROUND AND JUST SIT THERE... SAYS JON GORIN. HE'S THE E-P-A'S CHIEF OF THE SOUTHERN NEW JERSEY REMEDIATION SECTION UNDER THE SUPERFUND AND EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT DIVISION.</p>
<p><strong>Jon Gorin:</strong> What's going to happen is it's going to precipitate out and it's going to bind to the soil itself. The water is contaminated above acceptable levels, but the concentrations you can have on water is much less than you could have in soil. So, if it all binds to the soil, the concentrations in the soil would still be below a soil cleanup level.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JUST <em>SOME</em> LEAD... NOT ENOUGH TO POSE A RISK TO ANYTHING OR ANYONE.</p>
<p>AND SO FAR... JON SAYS... CONTAMINATION HAS MIRACULOUSLY NOT SPREAD TO THE DELAWARE RIVER.</p>
<p>CLEANUP AT THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE SEEMS TO BE RUNNING SMOOTHLY. AND THE STICKER PRICE TO CLEAN IT ALL UP IS RELATIVELY LOW... ABOUT ONE-AND-A-HALF-MILLION DOLLARS.</p>
<p>RENEE AND JON ARE HOPEFUL THAT EVERYTHING CAN BE SAID AND DONE IN A COUPLE OF YEARS.</p>
<p>IF THAT'S THE CASE... UNLESS MOTHER NATURE UNLEASHES A MASSIVE FLOOD AND IT ROLLS THROUGH SOON... CLIMATE CHANGE MAY JUST PASS THIS SUPERFUND SITE OVER.</p>
<p>I MENTIONED SALTWATER INTRUSION EARLIER. THE SITE IS ABOUT HALF A MILE FROM THE DELAWARE RIVER. RENEE SAYS IT WOULD HAVE TO FLOOD AN AWFUL LOT BEFORE SALTWATER FROM THE ATLANTIC OCEAN MAKES ITS WAY UP THE RIVER AND UNDERGROUND TO THE SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> Our big issue here is acidity, right? Not salinity. So even if there was some flooding, and it left some salt behind it, it wouldn't affect anything.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT THERE ARE PROJECTIONS FROM FEMA AND RUTGERS THAT SHOW THAT THE NEARBY STREAMS AND TRIBUTARIES DO PUT THE SITE AT SOME RISK DURING HURRICANES... THIS AS THE DESTRUCTION FROM HURRICANE IAN CONSUMES OUR HEADLINES.</p>
<p>OBVIOUSLY... THIS COULD BE A ONCE-IN-A-LIFETIME EVENT. THOUGH CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING WEATHER JUST A TAD BIT MORE UNPREDICTABLE.</p>
<p>JON SAYS IF A HURRICANE DID SWEEP THROUGH THE SITE BEFORE THEY WERE DONE... THEY'D BE LESS WORRIED ABOUT CONTAMINATION... AND MORE CONCERNED WITH LOGISTICS.</p>
<p><strong>Jon Gorin:</strong> We'd have to shut down the site, call everybody away, tie up the trailers, but, you know, for an injection remedy it's not too difficult. The problem with a big superstorm is if you're doing it, save an excavation, then you have a real headache because you have to control the sediments, and we're not doing that here.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MUCH LIKE DANIELLE IN THE SEVENTIES... I MADE A BRIEF SOJOURN IN PEDRICKTOWN. IT'S AN UNINCORPORATED COMMUNITY WITHIN OLDMANS TOWNSHIP IN SALEM COUNTY.</p>
<p>I LEARNED A FEW THINGS ALONG THE WAY... LIKE THERE ARE NEW JERSEY TOMATOES GROWN LOCALLY AND CREATED BY RUTGERS... AND SELLING FIREWOOD IN THE STATE CAN MAKE PROPERTY AG EXEMPT. ALSO... COFFEE FROM WAWA... IF THAT'S YOUR THING.</p>
<p>THE FIRST STOP IN TOWN... THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE. THE SOUTHERN PORTION OF THE SITE WAS BOUGHT IN 20-16 BY ECRECON. THAT STANDS FOR ECONOMY... RECOVERY... AND CONSERVATION.</p>
<p>IT'S KIND OF FITTING FOR A BUSINESS THAT BUYS AND SELLS USED EQUIPMENT TO BE ON A SUPERFUND SITE. THEY DEAL WITH SOME OF THE SAME INDUSTRIES ASSOCIATED WITH POLLUTING PLACES... LIKE PETROCHEMICAL COMPANIES... WHICH MAKE PESTICIDES AND PLASTICS.</p>
<p>I MET UP WITH ECRECON'S OWNERS... TOM AND NICK BERCUTE ... TO TALK ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE SITE. RENEE WITH THE E-P-A ALSO JOINED US TO PROVIDE SOME CONTEXT.</p>
<p>RENEE SAYS THE E-P-A LOVES SEEING SUPERFUND SITES LIKE THIS ONE GETTING REDEVELOPED. BUT THE AGENCY'S ONLY CONCERN IS MAKING SURE THE SITE GETS CLEAN... NOT WHAT HAPPENS TO IT AFTER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> Don't get in the way of us when we're doing the injections. We don't even go to zoning meetings. They don't get in the way of our remedy, and they don't mess with the remedy itself.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WE ALL MADE OUR WAY OUTSIDE TO TOUR THE FIELD THAT IS THE N-L INDUSTRIES SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>I WAS ASSURED THERE WERE NO ISSUES WITH WALKING AROUND THE SITE... I WASN'T GOING TO TRACK TOXIC DIRT BACK TO PENN STATION.</p>
<p>I'VE SAID IT BEFORE... AND I'LL SAY IT AGAIN... MOST OF THESE SUPERFUND SITES DON'T LOOK LIKE MUCH. THEY'RE MAINLY FLAT PIECES OF LAND WITH PATCHES OF GRASS AND ROCKY SOIL. THEY COULD BE THE PARK I USED TO PLAY IN AS A KID... OR MY OWN CHILDHOOD BACKYARD.</p>
<p>BUT THAT'S WHAT'S SCARY TO ME... I CAN'T SEE THE POLLUTION.</p>
<p>I COULD... HOWEVER... SEE A BUNCH OF WHITE INJECTION PIPES DOTTING THE PROPERTY. THOSE ARE THE PLACES WHERE TRUCKS FULL OF THE REAGENT SOLUTION EMPTIED THE STUFF INTO THE TOXIC GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> I don't know if that's a sampling well or an injection well. And I'm sure those pipes are there to keep people from running into them.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW IT'S A MATTER OF WAITING FOR THE CHEMICAL PROCESS TO PLAY OUT... THEN EXAMINING THE RESULTS TO SEE HOW WELL THE INJECTIONS ARE WORKING.</p>
<p>RENEE SAYS INJECTIONS HAPPENED FROM APRIL TO SEPTEMBER OF LAST YEAR.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> If the metals were truly mobile, and the site was first cleaned up in the '80s, then everything would be gone by now. So, the metals aren't moving but they are in solution. The groundwater moves. And we see the reagents we injected, the stuff we injected moving around, but for some reason the metals are just in too high a concentration or staying in an area.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW REMEMBER THE CREEPING SALTWATER I MENTIONED EARLIER? IT'S TECHNICALLY CALLED SALTWATER INTRUSION... AND IT'S CAUSING HEADACHES FOR SOME AROUND SOUTH JERSEY.</p>
<p>SEE... NEW JERSEY IS EXPERIENCING SEA LEVEL RISE ABOUT TWICE AS FAST AS THE GLOBAL AVERAGE. AND ONE OF THE EFFECTS OF THAT IS THE SPREAD OF SALTWATER UNDERGROUND IN COASTAL AREAS... WHERE IT DISPLACES THE EXISTING FRESHWATER.</p>
<p>LARGE STANDS OF COASTAL FORESTS ALONG DELAWARE BAY ARE DYING OFF BECAUSE THE TREE ROOTS CAN'T HANDLE SALTIER WATER.</p>
<p>THE SAME ISSUE IS THREATENING TO MAKE SOME FARMLAND FALLOW IN CUMBERLAND COUNTY... WHICH IS THE POOREST COUNTY IN THE STATE.</p>
<p>AND IN CAPE MAY... THE MAIN SOURCE OF DRINKING WATER IS AN AQUIFER THAT IS SLOWLY BECOMING SALTIER. CITY OFFICIALS THERE MAY HAVE TO SPEND MORE THAN 30 MILLION DOLLARS BUILDING A NEW DESALINATION PLANT TO KEEP CLEAN WATER FLOWING IN THE FUTURE.</p>
<p>MUCH IS STILL NOT FULLY UNDERSTOOD ABOUT SALTWATER INTRUSION IN SOUTH JERSEY... INCLUDING HOW FAST IT'S HAPPENING AND HOW FAR IT'S SPREADING.</p>
<p>STATE AND FEDERAL SCIENTISTS ARE WORKING ON STUDIES NOW TO ANSWER THOSE QUESTIONS... BUT THAT'S A YEARS-LONG PROCESS.</p>
<p>SO... WHAT DOES THIS SALTWATER INTRUSION MEAN FOR PEDRICKTOWN? WELL... IF SALTWATER DOES ACTUALLY MAKE ITS WAY UP TO THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... IT MIGHT ACTUALLY BE HELPFUL BECAUSE IT WOULD RAISE THE GROUNDWATER'S PH LEVEL.</p>
<p>THAT'S A GOOD THING BECAUSE WE WANT THE SITE'S GROUNDWATER TO BE LESS ACIDIC... SO THOSE TOXIC METALS DON'T DISSOLVE INTO THE WATER.</p>
<p>DIBS SARKAR... A PROFESSOR AT STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY IN THE SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING AND SCIENCE ... SAYS RAISING THE P-H OF THE SITE'S GROUNDWATER WAS A GOOD MOVE ON THE E-P-A'S PART.</p>
<p><strong>Dibs Sarkar:</strong> They didn't go with pump and treat and actually took a pretty bold step of, like, increasing the pH. So, I thought that that was pretty cool of EPA. Typically, they are very risk averse. And they would have, like, again kept on pumping and treating until the time I, at least I was dead, and the site will still not be remediated.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DIBS TEACHES A COURSE ON ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT THAT PARTLY DEALS WITH SUPERFUND SITES. AND HE'S AN EXPERT ON LEAD... WHICH IS GOOD FOR US BECAUSE THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... REMEMBER... REMOVED LEAD FROM OLD CAR BATTERIES.</p>
<p>I'M NO SCIENTIST... SO I ASKED DIBS TO EXPLAIN HOW CHANGING THE GROUNDWATER'S P-H ACTUALLY WORKS.</p>
<p><strong>Dibs Sarkar:</strong> Raising pH is not that easy, yeah? Metals like cadmium and lead, like, they are getting adsorbed on the aquifer materials and soils, okay? Cadmium and lead they actually absorb, specifically that means by forming covalent bonds, okay? So, what is happening there is, like, what was there, like, dissolved cadmium, dissolved lead in water --- happy because, again, it was acidic, like again, there was nothing to hold them, now, they are getting absorbed on the aquifer materials, okay? So, the aquifer materials are effectively working as filter materials now. So, this is basically what's happening in the system.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SECOND STOP ON MY VISIT TO PEDRICKTOWN... THE SALEM COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY TO FIND OUT MORE ABOUT THE HISTORY OF THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... AND USE MICROFICHE FOR THE FIRST TIME.</p>
<p>I REALLY FELT LIKE I WAS IN A HORROR MOVIE... TRYING TO FIND OUT WHY MY HOUSE IS HAUNTED.</p>
<p>REEL AFTER MICROFICHE REEL... I SPUN THROUGH THE SEVENTIES AND EIGHTIES... THE CHURCH BAKE SALES... THE NOT-POLITICALLY-CORRECT OP-EDS... UNTIL THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE MADE HEADLINES...</p>
<p>NATIONAL SMELTING FAILED TO CLEAN UP THE WASTE SITE.</p>
<p>ABOUT FIVE MONTHS AFTER THE SITE WAS ADDED TO THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 19-83... IT WAS BOUGHT BY NATIONAL SMELTING OF NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>THE PLANT HADN'T BEEN IN OPERATION SINCE MAY 19-82 BECAUSE OF THE AIR POLLUTION.</p>
<p>IN MARCH 19-84... TODAY'S SUNBEAM... THE LOCAL PAPER IN SALEM COUNTY AT THE TIME... WROTE ABOUT THE FINE NATIONAL SMELTING RECEIVED FROM THE D-E-P FOR FAILING TO PREVENT THE RELEASE OF LEAD-CONTAMINATED SURFACE WATER FROM THE LANDFILL.</p>
<p>THAT LANDFILL IS ACROSS THE STREET FROM THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE I VISITED BEFORE COMING TO THE HISTORICAL SOCIETY.</p>
<p>I THEN FOUND AN ARTICLE FROM 19-89 THAT TALKED ABOUT TESTS FROM SIX PRIVATE WELLS NEAR THE SITE SHOWING NO MAJOR CONTAMINATION.</p>
<p>MY FINAL STOP ON THE SALEM COUNTY TOUR WAS THE HOME OF FORMER OLDMANS TOWNSHIP MAYOR HARRY MOORE. HE'S THE MAN WHO REALLY KICKED THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE CLEANUP INTO GEAR.</p>
<p>HARRY WAS DOING YARD WORK AND HIS WIFE WAS ON A RIDING LAWNMOWER WHEN I ARRIVED. HARRY WILL BE NINETY THIS YEAR.</p>
<p>HE GOT INTO POLITICS IN 19-91.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I don't know if you call it working your way up or not, but I worked my way up to the mayor, because it's only a three-man committee and it makes a difference who your friends are.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE COMMITTEE WAS TRYING TO GET THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE CLEANED UP... ONCE AND FOR ALL.</p>
<p>HARRY SAYS THE TOWN WENT ROUND-AND-ROUND WITH THE D-E-P AND THE E-P-A AND GOT NOWHERE.</p>
<p>UNTIL HE ENTERED THE PICTURE.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> So, myself and the mayor went to a // welcoming committee and what you might say, for an individual that was nominated to the prosecutor's office. So, I went down for the ceremony. Well, after the ceremony here was Congressman Hughes there. And Congressman Hughes was two grades ahead of me in school.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SO... HARRY WENT UP TO HIM AFTER THAT MEETING IN 19-93 TO SEE IF THE CONGRESSMAN COULD HELP.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> When I walked up to him, he said, &quot;Oh, hi, Harry.&quot; I said, &quot;Hi, Bill.&quot; He said, I shook his hand, and I didn't let go. He looked down. I says, &quot;I'm not letting go of your hand until you tell me what you're going to do with National Lead.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>CONGRESSMAN HUGHES AGREED WITH HARRY THAT SOMETHING SHOULD BE DONE ABOUT THE POLLUTED SITE. SO... HE CONTACTED THE POWERS THAT BE AND THEY GOT TO WORK. THANKS, HARRY.</p>
<p>ORIGINALLY... HARRY SAYS THE E-P-A WANTED TO PUT A CAP ON THE SITE'S CONTAMINATED MATERIALS.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I said, &quot;No, it's not acceptable.&quot; &quot;Well, we'll see what we can do.&quot; And what they did -- so, they contacted chemical companies and they were glad to come down and get it and clean it up a little bit and resell it. They were tickled to death with that. So, that's what they did, so we weren't left with chemicals.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WHEN HUGHES LEFT CONGRESS IN 1995 ... HARRY SAYS A LOCAL GROUP HE WAS A MEMBER OF INVITED HIM AS A GUEST SPEAKER FOR A DINNER IN THE CONGRESSMAN'S HONOR.</p>
<p>DURING THE EVENT... HARRY PRESENTED HUGHES WITH A SPECIAL GIFT.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I went to K-Mart, where they had the display cameras on or display batteries on sale, just plastic, nothing in 'em. So, I told them what I wanted to use them for; they gave them to me. So, I had a company make up a plaque on there, and it went into detail about all relating to a battery, but &quot;we want to thank Congressman Hughes for jumpstarting the cleanup,&quot; and anything related to a battery jumpstart, we laid out the speech to him and gave him this battery. Well, he was overwhelmed. Since he's passed away, but I've been wanting to contact one of his kids to see if that battery is floating around so we can put it in the municipal building.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING HASHTAG HAZARD N-J.</p>
<p>OR... LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... HAZARD AT MY N-J P-B-S DOT ORG.</p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<p>HAZARD N-J IS AN N-J SPOTLIGHT NEWS PRODUCTION.<strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IT STARTED AS A CAMPFIRE... AND GREW INTO THE LARGEST WILDFIRE NEW JERSEY'S SEEN IN MORE THAN A DECADE.</p>
<p><strong>Briana Vannozzi <strong>-- Anchor, NJ Spotlight News</strong></strong></p>
<p>Firefighters in South Jersey are still battling a massive wildfire that broke out Sunday in Wharton State Forest.</p>
<p><strong>Ted Goldberg <strong>--Reporter, NJ Spotlight News</strong></strong></p>
<p>The New Jersey Forest Fire Service says it's finally gotten a handle on the Mullica River fire, that started burning Sunday.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE BLAZE... CALLED THE MULLICA RIVER FIRE... BURNED 15,000 ACRES IN WHARTON STATE FOREST THIS PAST JUNE.</p>
<p>FROM THE SKY IT LOOKED LIKE LIT MATCHES BLOWING IN THE WIND... CASTING A YELLOW HAZE OVER MOST OF SOUTH JERSEY.</p>
<p>THERE WERE NO INJURIES... BUT SEVERAL CAMPGROUNDS AND FARMS WERE THREATENED.</p>
<p>FIRES IN THE PINELANDS GENERALLY DON'T CAUSE CASUALTIES... BUT PROPERTY LOSS CAN AMOUNT TO MILLIONS OF DOLLARS FROM EACH FIRE... ESPECIALLY IF HOMES OR STRUCTURES ARE DAMAGED.</p>
<p>WILDFIRES AREN'T NEW IN THE STATE... BUT CLIMATE CHANGE IS CHANGING THE INTENSITY... DURATION... AND WHEN THEY OCCUR.</p>
<p>WITHIN THE SOUTHERN REACHES OF THE PINES... THE EPA IS TRYING TO WORK AROUND THOSE RISKS AS THEY TRY TO CLEAN UP A TOXIC LANDFILL NEARBY.</p>
<p>BUT ALL IT COULD TAKE IS A SPARK TO HARM THEIR EFFORTS.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>WHEN I WAS A KID... I WAS DEATHLY AFRAID OF FIRE. OVENS... STOVES... MATCHES... YOU NAME IT... ANYTHING THAT COULD LIGHT ON FIRE TERRIFIED ME.</p>
<p>OH... AND I DON'T GO CAMPING BECAUSE OF MOSQUITOES... BUT ALSO BECAUSE BUILDING A CAMPFIRE JUST SOUNDS LIKE A RECIPE FOR DISASTER.</p>
<p>I WOULD WATCH THAT TV SHOW ARE YOU AFRAID OF THE DARK... WHERE THESE KIDS SIT AROUND A CAMPFIRE AND TELL GHOST STORIES... BAFFLED THAT THEY WEREN'T MORE AFRAID OF STARTING A FOREST FIRE.</p>
<p>SMOKEY THE BEAR ALSO REALLY SCARED ME... LIKE... MAN... WHY AM I THE ONLY ONE THAT CAN PREVENT FOREST FIRES? I'M NOT EVEN CAMPING.</p>
<p>PUTTING MY CHILDHOOD NEUROSES ASIDE... I RECENTLY FOUND MYSELF IN THE MIDDLE OF THE NEW JERSEY PINELANDS. TURNS OUT... THAT'S ONE OF THE MOST WILDFIRE-PRONE AREAS IN THE COUNTRY.</p>
<p>I WAS THERE TO VISIT EMMELL'S SEPTIC LANDFILL... A 38-ACRE SUPERFUND SITE IN GALLOWAY TOWNSHIP THAT'S SURROUNDED BY PINE FOREST.</p>
<p>BACK IN THE '60S AND '70S... WHEN THE SITE OPERATED AS A DUMP FOR SEPTIC WASTE... AND... REPORTEDLY... DRUMS OF PAINT SLUDGE... THE FOREST HELPED HIDE THE EMMELL FAMILY'S ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES.</p>
<p>TODAY... THE FOREST AND THE THREAT OF WILDFIRES PUT THE SITE AT RISK.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>What they were supposed to do was to bring in septic waste, they were supposed to pour it out, basically on the ground. And they were supposed to just get in or plow it into the ground. At some point during that operations, they decided to start illegally taking in chemical waste.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JOE GOWERS HAS BEEN THE EPA PROJECT MANAGER FOR THE EMMELL SITE SINCE IT WAS LISTED IN 1999.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>And, ultimately, what we found was about 438 drums of what looked like to be paint sludge was disposed of in the ground at the site and that sort of triggered the contamination problem here because the solvents related to that leach into the groundwater, and then we had groundwater contamination related to the site.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE EPA WAS INITIALLY CONCERNED THAT THE FEW RESIDENTS WHO LIVE NEAR THIS RURAL SITE WERE DRINKING CONTAMINATED WELL WATER... TAINTED BY THAT PAINT SLUDGE.</p>
<p>SO... IN 2003... THE AGENCY CONNECTED RESIDENTS WHO WERE POTENTIALLY THREATENED BY THE POLLUTION TO THE LOCAL WATER COMPANY'S SUPPLY.</p>
<p>AS THEY CONTINUED THEIR INVESTIGATIONS... GOWERS SAYS THEY FOUND MORE CONTAMINATED WELLS.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>In 2008 and 2010, our removal program, once again, came in and basically provided an alternate water supply for those residences, and what they did was install deeper groundwater monitoring wells into an unimpacted aquifer below about 50 to 100 feet of clay out there, and those wells are down about 300 feet.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SINCE 2010... MILLIONS OF GALLONS OF WATER HAVE BEEN TREATED AT THE EPA'S GROUNDWATER EXTRACTION AND TREATMENT FACILITY ON THE SITE.</p>
<p>WHILE THE GROUNDWATER IS THE EPA'S PRIMARY CONCERN... GOWERS SAYS THEY FOUND PCBs... A LIKELY HUMAN CARCINOGENIC... IN SOME OF THE SOIL.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>Those materials were excavated from the site, those materials were more of a direct contact risk, they generally don't get into groundwater and provide risk in that fashion.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>I WALKED WITH GOWERS AROUND PARTS OF THE SITE... A GLORIFIED FIELD THAT... IF YOU DIDN'T KNOW ABOUT THE SITE'S HISTORY... AND DIDN'T SEE THE EPA SIGN... WOULD PROBABLY LET YOUR KIDS PLAY SOCCER ON.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>That area that's fenced off is actually part of the groundwater pump and treat system here, those are recharge basins. So that's where the clean water goes after it's been treated. And, you know, the process of that is basically they re-inject or basically discharge the clean groundwater there, it percolates back down, that causes mounting, which helps push the groundwater towards the extraction well. So it actually helps with the groundwater cleaning process here.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WE WALKED TO A CLEARING... WHERE REPORTS SAY DECADES AGO PEOPLE PAID THE EMMELL'S TO BURY DRUMS OF PAINT SLUDGE WASTE AND DUMP CHEMICALS RIGHT ONTO THE GROUND.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>They began illegally taking in chemical waste, the drums of paint sludge that we found, and that area where that was found was back in this tree line, you can see the cut in the tree line over here. So back in that area was where they had apparently dug a pit and then put in at least 438 drums of paint sludge and then covered that over. So that was basically the way the operations were conducted here. I know that during their operations they even mishandled it seemed the septic waste they got they got cited at least once that I'm aware of, I think it was maybe twice by the state of New Jersey because they were allowing septic waste to be ponded on the site when they were actually, you know, supposed to be plowing that stuff in.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE EPA STARTED TO CLEAN UP THIS LANDFILL SITE IN 1999... AND GOWERS SAYS THE AGENCY WILL TURN OVER OPERATION OF THE PUMP AND TREAT SYSTEM HERE TO THE NEW JERSEY DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AS EARLY AS NEXT YEAR.</p>
<p>OF THE SUPERFUND SITES LOCATED IN THE PINELANDS... EMMELL'S SEPTIC LANDFILL IS ONE OF SEVENTEEN THAT REMAINS ON THE LIST.</p>
<p>AND WITH THAT MANY TOXIC SITES IN THE AREA... IT'S IMPORTANT TO CLEAN THEM UP BEFORE THEY'RE DAMAGED BY WILDFIRES.</p>
<p>CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING THIS AREA MORE SUSCEPTIBLE TO WILDFIRES... AND MORE DIFFICULT FOR FIREFIGHTERS TO FIGHT THEM.</p>
<p>WHEN THERE'S LOW HUMIDITY AND HIGH HEAT... VEGETATION STARTS TO DRY AND WILT. THESE ARE THE KEY INGREDIENTS FOR A WILDFIRE DISASTER... A PERFECT STORM.</p>
<p>NEW JERSEY'S WILDFIRE SEASON HAS HISTORICALLY PEAKED IN THE LATE SPRING AND EARLY SUMMER. BUT NOW... THE SHIFT IN CONDITIONS HAS ALLOWED WILDFIRES TO GET MORE INTENSE... AND SPARK MORE EASILY THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE YEAR.</p>
<p>TO PREVENT A WILDFIRE FROM SWEEPING ONTO THE EMMELL'S SITE... AND DESTROYING WHAT APPEARED TO BE AN EXPENSIVE PUMP AND TREAT FACILITY... GOWERS SAYS THEY KEEP THE AREA AROUND THE BUILDING FREE FROM BRUSH.</p>
<p>IN THE OFF CHANCE A WILDFIRE DID DAMAGE THE FACILITY... HE SAYS THEY'D SHUT IT DOWN UNTIL THE BUILDING COULD BE REPAIRED.</p>
<p>THAT MEANS THE CONTAMINATED GROUNDWATER WOULD BE SITTING IN THE AQUIFER AND COULD MOVE AROUND. BUT GOWERS SAYS HE ISN'T CONCERNED.</p>
<p><strong>Joe Gowers -- Project Manager, EPA</strong></p>
<p>Groundwater contamination down here in Southern Jersey, the type of aquifer you're dealing with, you're looking at groundwater that might move a foot a day. So, if it's shut down for a month, it might move 30 feet. So, once you start the extraction wells up again, it should theoretically pull most of that contamination back.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>EMMELL'S SEPTIC LANDFILL MAY BE THE QUIETEST SUPERFUND SITE I'VE COVERED ON THIS PODCAST... BOTH IN TERMS OF LOCATION... WHERE CICADAS WERE THE ONLY THINGS I HEARD... AND VIRTUALLY NO NEWS COVERAGE.</p>
<p>I COULDN'T FIND OUT MUCH ABOUT THE SITE ONLINE. THERE'S NO COMMUNITY ACTION GROUP MAKING SURE THIS SITE GETS CLEANED UP.</p>
<p><strong>Jaclyn Rhodes -- Assistant Executive Director, Pinelands Preservation Alliance</strong></p>
<p>More people, more exposure, more liability, right? Less people, less exposure, less liability. So, often what my experience has been for Superfund sites, it's typically the community that brings up the issue. And if you don't have a big community that's complaining about it, or you address those that are being exposed because there's a long list of Superfund sites.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S JACLYN RHODES... THE ASSISTANT EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE PINELANDS PRESERVATION ALLIANCE.</p>
<p>I MET UP WITH HER ON THE SITE TO FIND OUT MORE ABOUT ITS HISTORY... AND FUTURE POTENTIAL WILDFIRE RISK.</p>
<p><strong>Jaclyn Rhodes -- Assistant Executive Director, Pinelands Preservation Alliance</strong></p>
<p>You would have to have an exceptional fire, very hot, burning for a long period of time for it to pass through an area that has, you know, essentially almost like a fire break around that typically gets moved out of woody vegetation from coming up.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE GOOD THING ABOUT EMMELL'S... AND OTHER SUPERFUND SITES THAT WERE LANDFILLS... IS THAT THEY HAVE LESS TREES AND MORE OF A GRASSLAND ENVIRONMENT. THIS PROTECTS THE SITE FROM A WILDFIRE GOING STRAIGHT THROUGH THE AREA.</p>
<p>EVEN IF A FIRE DID GO THROUGH THE SITE... THE EPA'S ALREADY REMOVED CONTAMINANTS FROM THE SOIL... SO THERE'S NOT REALLY A RISK OF THESE CHEMICALS BURNING OFF AND EFFECTING THE AIR QUALITY FOR THE SURROUNDING COMMUNITIES.</p>
<p>IN THE PINELANDS... FIRE IS A PART OF LIFE.</p>
<p>BUT THE WILDFIRES THAT HAVE SHAPED THE LANDSCAPE FOR CENTURIES... NOW THREATEN TO DESTROY THE COMMUNITIES WITHIN IT.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>So, this here is the Silas Little Experimental Forest.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>I MET MIKE GALLAGHER AT HIS OFFICE IN NEW LISBON... ABOUT AN HOUR NORTH OF GALLOWAY AND THE EMMELL SITE... ON THE OTHER END OF THE MILLION-ACRE PINELANDS NATIONAL RESERVE.</p>
<p>HE'S A FIRE ECOLOGIST WITH THE US FOREST SERVICE... AND HIS JOB REQUIRES HIM TO INTENTIONALLY START AND STUDY FIRES.</p>
<p>THERE'S A NAME FOR THIS PRACTICE... AND IT DOESN'T INCLUDE THE WORD MANIA.</p>
<p>IT'S CALLED PRESCRIBED BURNING... AND THE IDEA IS TO PURPOSEFULLY SET SMALL... CONTROLLED FIRES TO PREVENT CATASTROPHIC WILDFIRES.</p>
<p>IT WORKS BECAUSE THE CONTROLLED BURNS ESSENTIALLY CLEAN UP THE FOREST... CLEARING OUT BRUSH AND DEAD VEGETATION THAT WOULD OTHERWISE BE PRIME FUEL FOR A FUTURE WILDFIRE.</p>
<p>THIS PRACTICE... THOUGH... DIDN'T START WITH THE US FOREST SERVICE.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>Cranberry growers we're doing that since cranberries started as an industry, really before the 1840s, 1850s and folks were burning around their bogs regularly. But that culture was probably, well, almost inevitably, picked up by the Native Americans who were living here when Europeans got here because this sort of burning really wasn't a big thing in Europe, where a lot of folks came from. And that was adopted and still doing it today.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>I WANTED TO SEE THE EFFECTS OF FIRE MYSELF. SO... MIKE AND I DROVE THE FEW MINUTES DOWN THE ROAD FROM HIS OFFICE TO BRENDAN T BYRNE STATE FOREST.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>On the one side of the road, here, we have a fire-excluded forest. And on the other side of the road, we have this area that was burned in a wildfire last year in 2021.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BLACKENED TREES INDICATED WHERE THE FIRE MOVED IN-AND-OUT OF THE FOREST.</p>
<p>MIKE SAYS PRESCRIBED BURNS HAD TAKEN PLACE IN THIS AREA BEFORE... BUT IT HAD BEEN A WHILE.</p>
<p>PRESCRIBED BURNS ARE TOUGH TO CARRY OUT. THEY'RE COSTLY... LABOR INTENSIVE... AND ARE CONTINGENT ON FAVORABLE WEATHER.</p>
<p>CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING THESE INTENTIONAL BURNS EVEN MORE COMPLICATED TO CARRY OUT.</p>
<p>EVEN THOUGH NEW JERSEY IS SEEING MORE RAIN AND SNOW AS THE CLIMATE CHANGES... THAT PRECIPITATION IS INCREASINGLY CONCENTRATED IN HEAVY STORMS... WITH LONGER DRY SPELLS IN BETWEEN.</p>
<p>THAT MEANS WILDFIRE SEASON IS GROWING LONGER... NARROWING THE WINDOWS FOR PERFORMING PRESCRIBED BURNS SAFELY.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>We're seeing more wet weather in some years during our prescribed burn season. So, either more wet weather or more fire weather. So, what that means is that there's fewer days available to do prescribed burns because either it's too wet and it won't burn or it's too flammable.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NEW JERSEY HASN'T SEEN THE TYPES OF DEVASTATING MEGAFIRES THAT HAVE BECOME COMMON IN WESTERN STATES LIKE CALIFORNIA.</p>
<p>BUT MIKE SAYS THAT DOESN'T MEAN THE GARDEN STATE'S NOT AT RISK OF CATASTROPHIC WILDFIRES... ESPECIALLY AS TOWNS ON THE FOREST FRINGES BECOME MORE HEAVILY DEVELOPED... AND MORE PEOPLE MOVE INTO FIRE-PRONE AREAS.</p>
<p>THOUGH HE NOTES THE FIRES IN NEW JERSEY TEND TO BEHAVE DIFFERENTLY.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>One of the reasons that maybe we don't think about big fires as much here is because our fires do get big and they happen in one operational period, so one shift. Out west, their fires tend to burn a lot longer. Sometimes long enough that people from New Jersey have time to get there and help out. The history, they talk about how little rain they had leading up to some of those big fires. And so, this environment has a predisposition to dry out very quickly, because of its foundation, basically.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE SOIL IN THE PINELANDS IS SANDY... SO WHEN IT RAINS... WATER DOESN'T STICK AROUND. IT GOES DOWN TO THE AQUIFER QUICKLY.</p>
<p>MIKE SAYS THAT MEANS THERE CAN STILL BE A WILDFIRE IN THE AREA THE SAME DAY IT RAINS.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>We can look in the road here, all the sand and cobbles weren't put here to make the road. This is the natural underlying foundation that everything is growing out of and so there's, we're looking at rocks and pebbles and looks like beach sand almost. And so that doesn't hold any, any moisture or not for very long, you know, hold a little bit, but it dries out, it's got big pore space between all the particles, a lot more than, like, a heavy, organic soil. The soil doesn't hold a lot of organic matter, either, so there's no real hope of ever developing a, you know, a really thick, you know, better soil. That was something, you know, going back to the Pine Barrens, the settlers could never get it to really grow their crops, they never could really improve their soil that much for the things that they wanted to grow.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THIS ENVIRONMENT HAS SHAPED INDUSTRY... CULTURE... AND IN THESE PARTS... LEGEND.</p>
<p>LONG AGO... A WOMAN NAMED MRS. LEEDS WAS IN LABOR WITH HER 13TH CHILD.</p>
<p>SHE CRIED OUT IN AGONY... OH... LET THIS ONE BE THE DEVIL.</p>
<p>HER WISH CAME TRUE. THE CHILD RELEASED A HORRIFYING SCREECH... UNFURLED ITS WINGS... AND FLEW OUT OF THE HOUSE THROUGH THE CHIMNEY.</p>
<p>THAT NIGHT... THE JERSEY DEVIL WAS BORN.</p>
<p>OR... SO THE STORY GOES.</p>
<p>BACK IN THE PINELANDS OF THE TWENTY-FIRST CENTURY... THE ONLY DEMONIC THING I SPOTTED WAS WHAT APPEARED TO BE A SNUGGIE SOMEONE DISCARDED WITH BROKEN T-VS AND OTHER TRASH ALONG THE SIDE OF THE ROAD.</p>
<p>THIS PART OF THE PINELANDS ISN'T A LANDFILL LIKE THE EMMELL'S SUPERFUND SITE WAS... DESPITE GARAGE SALE-STYLE ILLEGAL DUMPING.</p>
<p>BUT MIKE SAYS THE PRESCRIBED BURNING GOING ON HERE WILL HELP SIMILAR SUPERFUND SITES LIKE EMMELL'S THAT ARE CONTAMINATED WITH HEAVY METALS.</p>
<p><strong>Mike Gallagher -- Fire Ecologist, US Forest Service</strong></p>
<p>Some species of plants can actually bring up heavy metals that were otherwise in the soil, but were relatively immobile, not going anywhere. Some early woody colonizers, of heavily disturbed areas can, will naturally want to start seeding in in certain types of scenarios and start growing, and they can take up these heavy metals, and then they'll get into their foliage and into their wood, and as the plant loses parts, naturally, leaves and twigs and things, it's starting to bring heavy metals up back into into the system, on the top, where then they can run off with rain or blow around and dust. And so one strategy that's been proposed is to actually use some prescribed fire in Superfund sites like that to actually control the species that would start moving the contamination around. And so the goal for some places might not be to restore it back to a forest because that might be counterproductive for the hazardous part. And so maybe maintaining it as a grassland or something like that with species of plants that aren't going to move the contamination around but still provide ecological opportunity for wildlife and recreation can be good.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Composer – Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Art – Matthew Fleming</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="51618368" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/y9vkdv/Hazard-NJ_Episode-Six_Final_Mix_Mid_Roll_MB_110720228nvho.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:21:30</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ Episode Swap: The Sweaty Penguin: Breaking down the Inflation Reduction Act</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-05a-the-sweaty-penguin-breaking-down-the-inflation-reduction/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-05a-the-sweaty-penguin-breaking-down-the-inflation-reduction/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>The Inflation Reduction Act narrowly passed the Senate. What is it, and how does it connect climate change with inflation?</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[The Inflation Reduction Act narrowly passed the Senate. What is it, and how does it connect climate change with inflation?]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="The Sweaty Penguin: Breaking down the Inflation Reduction Act" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=ki3mb-12f11f3-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>We’re bringing you a special episode from our friends at “The Sweaty Penguin” podcast, which dives deep (with a bit of humor!) on all things climate change. In this episode, “The Sweaty Penguin” crew takes a look at the landmark Inflation Reduction Act, and what it does and does not do for the climate. Check it out, and be sure to follow “The Sweaty Penguin”, another show made possible by the Peril &amp; Promise initiative, wherever you get your podcasts.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="39971142" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/u9vhvm/Hazard-NJ_Sweaty-Penguin-Episode-Swap.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:27:44</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - Orange Fog and Creeping Saltwater - Season 1: Episode 5</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-05-orange-fog-and-creeping-saltwater/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 01:54:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-05-orange-fog-and-creeping-saltwater/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Cleanup is imminent at a site in South Jersey where for years battery acid was haphazardly drained onto the ground.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Cleanup is imminent at a site in South Jersey where for years battery acid was haphazardly drained onto the ground.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 5: Orange Fog and Creeping Saltwater" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=bk5bz-12de82a-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>The National Lead company spent years in the 1970s recycling car batteries at a factory in rural South Jersey, haphazardly draining battery acid onto the ground. The pollution left dangerous heavy metals in the site’s soil and groundwater — a mess that is now on the verge of being cleaned up. But in an area along the Delaware Bay, sea level rise is slowly pushing a new potential problem into the ground.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IT FORMED AT NIGHT... WHEN THEY WERE ASLEEP. CREEPING INTO THEIR HOMES... UNSEEN.</p>
<p>FOR THOSE WHO WERE STILL AWAKE... THE VIEW OUTSIDE THEIR WINDOWS WAS ALMOST ETHEREAL... A SOFT GLOW LIKE A FLAME FROM A CANDLE.</p>
<p>THIS HAPPENED FOR ABOUT AN HOUR-AND-A-HALF A FEW NIGHTS A WEEK... FOR NEARLY TWO YEARS.</p>
<p>DAYLIGHT ERASED THE ORANGE FOG THAT ENVELOPED THE SMALL COMMUNITY OF PEDRICKTOWN NEW JERSEY... NIGHT AFTER NIGHT.</p>
<p>BUT EVEN THOUGH RESIDENTS COULD NO LONGER SEE THE FOG... THE PROOF OF ITS EXISTENCE REMAINED.</p>
<p>THERE WERE UNEXPLAINED HEADACHES... AND PINHOLES IN THE ALUMINUM SIDING OF THEIR HOMES... AS IF THE FOG HAD GOTTEN HUNGRY.</p>
<p>IT WAS LIKE SOMETHING OUT OF A STEPHEN KING NOVEL... EXCEPT THE FOG'S ORIGINS WEREN'T SUPERNATURAL. IT CAME FROM THE SMOKESTACKS OF THE N-L INDUSTRIES PLANT.</p>
<p>IN 19-76... DANIELLE FLOOD WAS A YOUNG REPORTER FREELANCING FOR THE NEW YORK TIMES. A CAB DROPPED HER OFF IN PEDRICKTOWN ONE MORNING TO INVESTIGATE THE ORANGE FOG.</p>
<p><strong>Danielle Flood:</strong> I'm not sure that I remember seeing anything over two stories, I think it was all one stories or small houses around, not close, some were close actually. It looked like the houses were built and then somebody came and put this factory next to them and there was a big dump next to the factory with, I guess, about 500 car batteries dumped there.</p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE N-L INDUSTRIES PLANT RECOVERED LEAD FROM USED CAR BATTERIES. THEY DID THIS BY DRAINING THE BATTERIES OF SULFURIC ACID... AND THEN BREAKING THEM... ON THE GROUND.</p>
<p><strong>Danielle Flood:</strong> I talked to this one guy, he must have been retired or something. He was kind of old. And he was really upset, and I asked him what it was like to live next to, across the street from this factory that was reclaiming lead from car batteries. So, he said that he was not happy at all. And he showed me his car. The hood of his car, the paint had been eaten away.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>A FORMER N-L INDUSTRIES EMPLOYEE TOLD DANIELLE FOR HER ARTICLE THAT THE PLANT STORED THE CAR BATTERIES WAITING TO BE RECYCLED IN A DUMP BEHIND THE BUILDING.</p>
<p>WHEN IT RAINED ON THE BATTERIES... THE FORMER EMPLOYEE TOLD HER THAT LEAD AND SULFURIC ACID COULD LEAK INTO THE GROUND.</p>
<p>AND THAT'S A BIG PROBLEM. THE CAPE MAY AQUIFER LIES UNDER THE SITE... JUST ONE-AND-A-HALF MILES FROM THE DELAWARE RIVER.</p>
<p>JUST TO BE CLEAR... NEARBY WELLS NEVER DREW FROM THIS AQUIFER. INSTEAD... THEY TAPPED INTO DEEPER POCKETS OF WATER.</p>
<p>TODAY... EVEN THOUGH THE PLANT NO LONGER EXISTS... THE GROUNDWATER REMAINS CONTAMINATED WITH LEAD AND CADMIUM... TOXIC METALS THAT CAN CAUSE LEARNING PROBLEMS IN CHILDREN.</p>
<p>SALTWATER IS ALSO CREEPING INLAND AS CLIMATE CHANGE RAISES SEA LEVELS AND AMPLIFIES STORM SURGES AND FLOODING. ACROSS SOUTH JERSEY... THAT SLOW TRICKLE OF SALTWATER IS KILLING FORESTS... THREATENING FARMLAND... AND IMPERILING DRINKING WATER SUPPLIES.</p>
<p>SO... WHAT HAPPENS IF SALTWATER MIGRATES FROM THE OCEAN TO THE GROUNDWATER UNDERNEATH THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE?</p>
<p>IT MIGHT NOT BE A BAD THING. IN FACT... THE SALTWATER COULD HELP <em>LOCK</em> THE POLLUTION IN PLACE... RATHER THAN SPREADING IT.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>WHEN I WAS SIXTEEN... I WAS PART OF THIS LOCAL BEAUTY PAGEANT. IT WAS SOMETHING I WANTED TO DO TO PROVE A POINT. WHAT POINT THAT WAS... I CAN'T REMEMBER.</p>
<p>DURING THE PAGEANT... WE WERE ALL ASKED: WHAT IS THE MOST PRESSING PROBLEM FACING TEENS? MY RESPONSE: DEFORESTATION. THE AUDIENCE WAS SILENT. I DON'T THINK I EVEN GOT A CLAP FROM MY FAMILY WHO WERE THERE.</p>
<p>BELIEVE IT OR NOT... I DIDN'T WIN.</p>
<p>I'M MENTIONING THIS BECAUSE NO ONE BELIEVED ME. THEY DIDN'T THINK DEFORESTATION WAS A PROBLEM... IF THEY EVEN KNEW WHAT THAT WAS. ALL OF THE GREENPEACE STICKERS I STUCK AROUND TOWN COULDN'T CHANGE THEIR MINDS. IF THEY COULDN'T SEE IT... THEY COULDN'T BELIEVE IT.</p>
<p>MUCH LIKE THE ENVIRONMENTAL OFFICIALS IN THE SEVENTIES WHO WENT TO THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE NEAR PEDRICKTOWN NEW JERSEY... AFTER BEING MADE AWARE OF THE ORANGE FOG. THEY TOLD NEW YORK TIMES FREELANCE REPORTER DANIELLE FLOOD THAT THEY HAD TO SEE THE FOG THEMSELVES BEFORE THEY COULD DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT.</p>
<p>OKAY... I'LL JUST GET THIS OUT OF THE WAY: IT WAS NEVER PROVEN THAT N-L INDUSTRIES WAS THE SOURCE OF THE ORANGE FOG.</p>
<p>BUT IN THE EIGHTIES... NEW JERSEY'S DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION STILL FOUND THE COMPANY RESPONSIBLE FOR POLLUTING THE AIR WITH VARIOUS TOXIC CHEMICALS.</p>
<p>THE E-P-A PLACED THE SITE ON THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 19-83... AND THEY GOT TO WORK DEALING WITH THE LEAD IN THE SOIL AND GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p>NEARLY FORTY YEARS LATER... RENEE GELBLAT WITH THE E-P-A SAYS THE CONTAMINATED SOIL HAS BEEN REMOVED... AND NOW THE FOCUS IS ON THE GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> It's not really moving anywhere. It's kind of a big, little lake underneath part of the site. I mean, the water moves, but the lead and cadmium are not. We tested the two streams and it's not there.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>RENEE IS THE REMEDIAL PROJECT MANAGER FOR THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... JUST SOUTH OF PEDRICKTOWN.</p>
<p>SHE SAYS LEAD AND CADMIUM DON'T DISSOLVE IN WATER UNLESS IT'S REALLY ACIDIC. AND THE GROUNDWATER AT THIS FORTY-FOUR-ACRE SITE IS <em>STILL</em> PRETTY ACIDIC.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> It's down around four where it should be somewhere between six and eight. So, what we're doing is injecting, I mean, really simple would be, say, baking soda, it's a little more complicated than that, to bring the pH back toward neutral. And the tricky part is, in order to get the lead out of the water, you actually have to bring it up toward eight or nine. So, we have to make it basic, just to get it to come out of the solution. And then we'll let it go back down to, you know, six to eight, which is what's normal for the groundwater.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S BEING DONE BY INJECTING A PHOSPHATE REAGENT... BASICALLY A SUBSTANCE SIMILAR TO BAKING SODA... LIKE RENEE SAID... INTO THE POLLUTED GROUNDWATER TO RAISE THE P-H AND MAKE THE WATER LESS ACIDIC.</p>
<p>ONCE THE GROUNDWATER'S P-H IS RAISED HIGH ENOUGH... THE TOXIC METALS WILL STICK TO THE SOIL PARTICLES THAT ARE UNDERGROUND AND JUST SIT THERE... SAYS JON GORIN. HE'S THE E-P-A'S CHIEF OF THE SOUTHERN NEW JERSEY REMEDIATION SECTION UNDER THE SUPERFUND AND EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT DIVISION.</p>
<p><strong>Jon Gorin:</strong> What's going to happen is it's going to precipitate out and it's going to bind to the soil itself. The water is contaminated above acceptable levels, but the concentrations you can have on water is much less than you could have in soil. So, if it all binds to the soil, the concentrations in the soil would still be below a soil cleanup level.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JUST <em>SOME</em> LEAD... NOT ENOUGH TO POSE A RISK TO ANYTHING OR ANYONE.</p>
<p>AND SO FAR... JON SAYS... CONTAMINATION HAS MIRACULOUSLY NOT SPREAD TO THE DELAWARE RIVER.</p>
<p>CLEANUP AT THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE SEEMS TO BE RUNNING SMOOTHLY. AND THE STICKER PRICE TO CLEAN IT ALL UP IS RELATIVELY LOW... ABOUT ONE-AND-A-HALF-MILLION DOLLARS.</p>
<p>RENEE AND JON ARE HOPEFUL THAT EVERYTHING CAN BE SAID AND DONE IN A COUPLE OF YEARS.</p>
<p>IF THAT'S THE CASE... UNLESS MOTHER NATURE UNLEASHES A MASSIVE FLOOD AND IT ROLLS THROUGH SOON... CLIMATE CHANGE MAY JUST PASS THIS SUPERFUND SITE OVER.</p>
<p>I MENTIONED SALTWATER INTRUSION EARLIER. THE SITE IS ABOUT HALF A MILE FROM THE DELAWARE RIVER. RENEE SAYS IT WOULD HAVE TO FLOOD AN AWFUL LOT BEFORE SALTWATER FROM THE ATLANTIC OCEAN MAKES ITS WAY UP THE RIVER AND UNDERGROUND TO THE SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> Our big issue here is acidity, right? Not salinity. So even if there was some flooding, and it left some salt behind it, it wouldn't affect anything.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT THERE ARE PROJECTIONS FROM FEMA AND RUTGERS THAT SHOW THAT THE NEARBY STREAMS AND TRIBUTARIES DO PUT THE SITE AT SOME RISK DURING HURRICANES... THIS AS THE DESTRUCTION FROM HURRICANE IAN CONSUMES OUR HEADLINES.</p>
<p>OBVIOUSLY... THIS COULD BE A ONCE-IN-A-LIFETIME EVENT. THOUGH CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING WEATHER JUST A TAD BIT MORE UNPREDICTABLE.</p>
<p>JON SAYS IF A HURRICANE DID SWEEP THROUGH THE SITE BEFORE THEY WERE DONE... THEY'D BE LESS WORRIED ABOUT CONTAMINATION... AND MORE CONCERNED WITH LOGISTICS.</p>
<p><strong>Jon Gorin:</strong> We'd have to shut down the site, call everybody away, tie up the trailers, but, you know, for an injection remedy it's not too difficult. The problem with a big superstorm is if you're doing it, save an excavation, then you have a real headache because you have to control the sediments, and we're not doing that here.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MUCH LIKE DANIELLE IN THE SEVENTIES... I MADE A BRIEF SOJOURN IN PEDRICKTOWN. IT'S AN UNINCORPORATED COMMUNITY WITHIN OLDMANS TOWNSHIP IN SALEM COUNTY.</p>
<p>I LEARNED A FEW THINGS ALONG THE WAY... LIKE THERE ARE NEW JERSEY TOMATOES GROWN LOCALLY AND CREATED BY RUTGERS... AND SELLING FIREWOOD IN THE STATE CAN MAKE PROPERTY AG EXEMPT. ALSO... COFFEE FROM WAWA... IF THAT'S YOUR THING.</p>
<p>THE FIRST STOP IN TOWN... THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE. THE SOUTHERN PORTION OF THE SITE WAS BOUGHT IN 20-16 BY ECRECON. THAT STANDS FOR ECONOMY... RECOVERY... AND CONSERVATION.</p>
<p>IT'S KIND OF FITTING FOR A BUSINESS THAT BUYS AND SELLS USED EQUIPMENT TO BE ON A SUPERFUND SITE. THEY DEAL WITH SOME OF THE SAME INDUSTRIES ASSOCIATED WITH POLLUTING PLACES... LIKE PETROCHEMICAL COMPANIES... WHICH MAKE PESTICIDES AND PLASTICS.</p>
<p>I MET UP WITH ECRECON'S OWNERS... TOM AND NICK BERCUTE ... TO TALK ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THE SITE. RENEE WITH THE E-P-A ALSO JOINED US TO PROVIDE SOME CONTEXT.</p>
<p>RENEE SAYS THE E-P-A LOVES SEEING SUPERFUND SITES LIKE THIS ONE GETTING REDEVELOPED. BUT THE AGENCY'S ONLY CONCERN IS MAKING SURE THE SITE GETS CLEAN... NOT WHAT HAPPENS TO IT AFTER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> Don't get in the way of us when we're doing the injections. We don't even go to zoning meetings. They don't get in the way of our remedy, and they don't mess with the remedy itself.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WE ALL MADE OUR WAY OUTSIDE TO TOUR THE FIELD THAT IS THE N-L INDUSTRIES SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>I WAS ASSURED THERE WERE NO ISSUES WITH WALKING AROUND THE SITE... I WASN'T GOING TO TRACK TOXIC DIRT BACK TO PENN STATION.</p>
<p>I'VE SAID IT BEFORE... AND I'LL SAY IT AGAIN... MOST OF THESE SUPERFUND SITES DON'T LOOK LIKE MUCH. THEY'RE MAINLY FLAT PIECES OF LAND WITH PATCHES OF GRASS AND ROCKY SOIL. THEY COULD BE THE PARK I USED TO PLAY IN AS A KID... OR MY OWN CHILDHOOD BACKYARD.</p>
<p>BUT THAT'S WHAT'S SCARY TO ME... I CAN'T SEE THE POLLUTION.</p>
<p>I COULD... HOWEVER... SEE A BUNCH OF WHITE INJECTION PIPES DOTTING THE PROPERTY. THOSE ARE THE PLACES WHERE TRUCKS FULL OF THE REAGENT SOLUTION EMPTIED THE STUFF INTO THE TOXIC GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> I don't know if that's a sampling well or an injection well. And I'm sure those pipes are there to keep people from running into them.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW IT'S A MATTER OF WAITING FOR THE CHEMICAL PROCESS TO PLAY OUT... THEN EXAMINING THE RESULTS TO SEE HOW WELL THE INJECTIONS ARE WORKING.</p>
<p>RENEE SAYS INJECTIONS HAPPENED FROM APRIL TO SEPTEMBER OF LAST YEAR.</p>
<p><strong>Renee Gelblat:</strong> If the metals were truly mobile, and the site was first cleaned up in the '80s, then everything would be gone by now. So, the metals aren't moving but they are in solution. The groundwater moves. And we see the reagents we injected, the stuff we injected moving around, but for some reason the metals are just in too high a concentration or staying in an area.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW REMEMBER THE CREEPING SALTWATER I MENTIONED EARLIER? IT'S TECHNICALLY CALLED SALTWATER INTRUSION... AND IT'S CAUSING HEADACHES FOR SOME AROUND SOUTH JERSEY.</p>
<p>SEE... NEW JERSEY IS EXPERIENCING SEA LEVEL RISE ABOUT TWICE AS FAST AS THE GLOBAL AVERAGE. AND ONE OF THE EFFECTS OF THAT IS THE SPREAD OF SALTWATER UNDERGROUND IN COASTAL AREAS... WHERE IT DISPLACES THE EXISTING FRESHWATER.</p>
<p>LARGE STANDS OF COASTAL FORESTS ALONG DELAWARE BAY ARE DYING OFF BECAUSE THE TREE ROOTS CAN'T HANDLE SALTIER WATER.</p>
<p>THE SAME ISSUE IS THREATENING TO MAKE SOME FARMLAND FALLOW IN CUMBERLAND COUNTY... WHICH IS THE POOREST COUNTY IN THE STATE.</p>
<p>AND IN CAPE MAY... THE MAIN SOURCE OF DRINKING WATER IS AN AQUIFER THAT IS SLOWLY BECOMING SALTIER. CITY OFFICIALS THERE MAY HAVE TO SPEND MORE THAN 30 MILLION DOLLARS BUILDING A NEW DESALINATION PLANT TO KEEP CLEAN WATER FLOWING IN THE FUTURE.</p>
<p>MUCH IS STILL NOT FULLY UNDERSTOOD ABOUT SALTWATER INTRUSION IN SOUTH JERSEY... INCLUDING HOW FAST IT'S HAPPENING AND HOW FAR IT'S SPREADING.</p>
<p>STATE AND FEDERAL SCIENTISTS ARE WORKING ON STUDIES NOW TO ANSWER THOSE QUESTIONS... BUT THAT'S A YEARS-LONG PROCESS.</p>
<p>SO... WHAT DOES THIS SALTWATER INTRUSION MEAN FOR PEDRICKTOWN? WELL... IF SALTWATER DOES ACTUALLY MAKE ITS WAY UP TO THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... IT MIGHT ACTUALLY BE HELPFUL BECAUSE IT WOULD RAISE THE GROUNDWATER'S PH LEVEL.</p>
<p>THAT'S A GOOD THING BECAUSE WE WANT THE SITE'S GROUNDWATER TO BE LESS ACIDIC... SO THOSE TOXIC METALS DON'T DISSOLVE INTO THE WATER.</p>
<p>DIBS SARKAR... A PROFESSOR AT STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY IN THE SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING AND SCIENCE ... SAYS RAISING THE P-H OF THE SITE'S GROUNDWATER WAS A GOOD MOVE ON THE E-P-A'S PART.</p>
<p><strong>Dibs Sarkar:</strong> They didn't go with pump and treat and actually took a pretty bold step of, like, increasing the pH. So, I thought that that was pretty cool of EPA. Typically, they are very risk averse. And they would have, like, again kept on pumping and treating until the time I, at least I was dead, and the site will still not be remediated.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DIBS TEACHES A COURSE ON ENVIRONMENTAL MANAGEMENT THAT PARTLY DEALS WITH SUPERFUND SITES. AND HE'S AN EXPERT ON LEAD... WHICH IS GOOD FOR US BECAUSE THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... REMEMBER... REMOVED LEAD FROM OLD CAR BATTERIES.</p>
<p>I'M NO SCIENTIST... SO I ASKED DIBS TO EXPLAIN HOW CHANGING THE GROUNDWATER'S P-H ACTUALLY WORKS.</p>
<p><strong>Dibs Sarkar:</strong> Raising pH is not that easy, yeah? Metals like cadmium and lead, like, they are getting adsorbed on the aquifer materials and soils, okay? Cadmium and lead they actually absorb, specifically that means by forming covalent bonds, okay? So, what is happening there is, like, what was there, like, dissolved cadmium, dissolved lead in water --- happy because, again, it was acidic, like again, there was nothing to hold them, now, they are getting absorbed on the aquifer materials, okay? So, the aquifer materials are effectively working as filter materials now. So, this is basically what's happening in the system.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SECOND STOP ON MY VISIT TO PEDRICKTOWN... THE SALEM COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY TO FIND OUT MORE ABOUT THE HISTORY OF THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE... AND USE MICROFICHE FOR THE FIRST TIME.</p>
<p>I REALLY FELT LIKE I WAS IN A HORROR MOVIE... TRYING TO FIND OUT WHY MY HOUSE IS HAUNTED.</p>
<p>REEL AFTER MICROFICHE REEL... I SPUN THROUGH THE SEVENTIES AND EIGHTIES... THE CHURCH BAKE SALES... THE NOT-POLITICALLY-CORRECT OP-EDS... UNTIL THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE MADE HEADLINES...</p>
<p>NATIONAL SMELTING FAILED TO CLEAN UP THE WASTE SITE.</p>
<p>ABOUT FIVE MONTHS AFTER THE SITE WAS ADDED TO THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 19-83... IT WAS BOUGHT BY NATIONAL SMELTING OF NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>THE PLANT HADN'T BEEN IN OPERATION SINCE MAY 19-82 BECAUSE OF THE AIR POLLUTION.</p>
<p>IN MARCH 19-84... TODAY'S SUNBEAM... THE LOCAL PAPER IN SALEM COUNTY AT THE TIME... WROTE ABOUT THE FINE NATIONAL SMELTING RECEIVED FROM THE D-E-P FOR FAILING TO PREVENT THE RELEASE OF LEAD-CONTAMINATED SURFACE WATER FROM THE LANDFILL.</p>
<p>THAT LANDFILL IS ACROSS THE STREET FROM THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE I VISITED BEFORE COMING TO THE HISTORICAL SOCIETY.</p>
<p>I THEN FOUND AN ARTICLE FROM 19-89 THAT TALKED ABOUT TESTS FROM SIX PRIVATE WELLS NEAR THE SITE SHOWING NO MAJOR CONTAMINATION.</p>
<p>MY FINAL STOP ON THE SALEM COUNTY TOUR WAS THE HOME OF FORMER OLDMANS TOWNSHIP MAYOR HARRY MOORE. HE'S THE MAN WHO REALLY KICKED THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE CLEANUP INTO GEAR.</p>
<p>HARRY WAS DOING YARD WORK AND HIS WIFE WAS ON A RIDING LAWNMOWER WHEN I ARRIVED. HARRY WILL BE NINETY THIS YEAR.</p>
<p>HE GOT INTO POLITICS IN 19-91.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I don't know if you call it working your way up or not, but I worked my way up to the mayor, because it's only a three-man committee and it makes a difference who your friends are.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE COMMITTEE WAS TRYING TO GET THE N-L INDUSTRIES SITE CLEANED UP... ONCE AND FOR ALL.</p>
<p>HARRY SAYS THE TOWN WENT ROUND-AND-ROUND WITH THE D-E-P AND THE E-P-A AND GOT NOWHERE.</p>
<p>UNTIL HE ENTERED THE PICTURE.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> So, myself and the mayor went to a // welcoming committee and what you might say, for an individual that was nominated to the prosecutor's office. So, I went down for the ceremony. Well, after the ceremony here was Congressman Hughes there. And Congressman Hughes was two grades ahead of me in school.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SO... HARRY WENT UP TO HIM AFTER THAT MEETING IN 19-93 TO SEE IF THE CONGRESSMAN COULD HELP.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> When I walked up to him, he said, &quot;Oh, hi, Harry.&quot; I said, &quot;Hi, Bill.&quot; He said, I shook his hand, and I didn't let go. He looked down. I says, &quot;I'm not letting go of your hand until you tell me what you're going to do with National Lead.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>CONGRESSMAN HUGHES AGREED WITH HARRY THAT SOMETHING SHOULD BE DONE ABOUT THE POLLUTED SITE. SO... HE CONTACTED THE POWERS THAT BE AND THEY GOT TO WORK. THANKS, HARRY.</p>
<p>ORIGINALLY... HARRY SAYS THE E-P-A WANTED TO PUT A CAP ON THE SITE'S CONTAMINATED MATERIALS.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I said, &quot;No, it's not acceptable.&quot; &quot;Well, we'll see what we can do.&quot; And what they did -- so, they contacted chemical companies and they were glad to come down and get it and clean it up a little bit and resell it. They were tickled to death with that. So, that's what they did, so we weren't left with chemicals.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WHEN HUGHES LEFT CONGRESS IN 1995 ... HARRY SAYS A LOCAL GROUP HE WAS A MEMBER OF INVITED HIM AS A GUEST SPEAKER FOR A DINNER IN THE CONGRESSMAN'S HONOR.</p>
<p>DURING THE EVENT... HARRY PRESENTED HUGHES WITH A SPECIAL GIFT.</p>
<p><strong>Harry Moore:</strong> I went to K-Mart, where they had the display cameras on or display batteries on sale, just plastic, nothing in 'em. So, I told them what I wanted to use them for; they gave them to me. So, I had a company make up a plaque on there, and it went into detail about all relating to a battery, but &quot;we want to thank Congressman Hughes for jumpstarting the cleanup,&quot; and anything related to a battery jumpstart, we laid out the speech to him and gave him this battery. Well, he was overwhelmed. Since he's passed away, but I've been wanting to contact one of his kids to see if that battery is floating around so we can put it in the municipal building.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING HASHTAG HAZARD N-J.</p>
<p>OR... LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... HAZARD AT MY N-J P-B-S DOT ORG.</p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<p>HAZARD N-J IS AN N-J SPOTLIGHT NEWS PRODUCTION.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Associate Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Music composed by Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Artwork by Matthew Fleming</p>
<p>Special thanks to Rae Walzer and Salem County Historical Society</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="52892288" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/4fv5yf/Hazard-NJ_Episode-Five_Final_MIX_MB_100520226ebqj.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:22:02</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: Remembering Jim Florio</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04d-remembering-jim-florio/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04d-remembering-jim-florio/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>We revisit an interview recorded with the former governor earlier this year</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[We revisit an interview recorded with the former governor earlier this year]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="BONUS Episode: Remembering Jim Florio" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=6d5t7-12d7db4-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>Few people have had as much impact on efforts to clean up New Jersey and America’s toxic messes as former New Jersey Gov. Jim Florio, who died on Sept. 25 at age 85. Before he was governor, Florio spent 15 years representing the Camden area in Congress. Arguably his crowning achievement in Washington was writing, and then pushing through, the Superfund law. The measure created the federal program that is dedicated to cleaning up some of the nation’s most hazardous pollution, and does so under the principle that the polluter should pay.</p>
<p>In this bonus episode, Hazard NJ reflects on Florio’s efforts to clean up dangerous pollution by revisiting an interview recorded with him earlier this year.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="31716953" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/pcky8u/Hazard_Florio-Bonus-Episode_V4.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:22:00</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: REWIND: Highlighting the Best of Hazard NJ (So Far)</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04c-rewind-the-best-of/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04c-rewind-the-best-of/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Get ready for the new shows with a look back at some highlights from our first four episodes.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Get ready for the new shows with a look back at some highlights from our first four episodes.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="REWIND: Highlighting the Best of Hazard NJ (So Far)" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=cqsuv-12cb9fb-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>Hazard NJ is returning with four new episodes this fall, to take fresh new looks about the relationship between the Garden State's most toxic Superfund sites and climate change. Get ready for the new shows with a look back at some highlights from our first four episodes, and keep an eye on your podcast feeds: Episode 5 drops on September 28.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="46930418" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/qw2wi2/Revised-Hazard-NJ-Best-Of-Ep.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:32:34</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: The Hackensack’s Comeback Moves Ahead</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04b-the-hackensack-comeback-moves-ahead/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04b-the-hackensack-comeback-moves-ahead/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="BONUS Episode: The Hackensack’s Comeback Moves Ahead" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=36vbq-12bb1b0-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>It’s official: The Hackensack River is New Jersey’s 115th Superfund site. EPA officials gathered with state and local leaders this week to announce the big news, which puts the polluted lower reaches of the river in line for a major cleanup that is expected to cost billions of dollars.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="5701001" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/25hjj6/Hazard_Superfund-Bonus_V3.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:03:56</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard NJ BONUS Episode: Funding Returns for the Superfund</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04a-funding-returns-for-the-superfund/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04a-funding-returns-for-the-superfund/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="BONUS Episode: Funding Returns for the Superfund" allowtransparency="true" style="border: none; min-width: min(100%, 430px);" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=mjwd6-129e1ce-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=&rtl=0&logo_link=&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="300"></iframe>
<p>The Superfund program was designed to be paid for by a tax on chemical and oil companies,  but that tax expired years ago, and the program has been strapped for cash since.</p>
<p>But that has changed in recent months. Last fall, the chemical tax was brought back as part of the massive federal infrastructure bill. And oil tax has returned as part of the Inflation Reduction Act, which was signed today by President Joe Biden.</p>
<p>NJ Spotlight News anchor Briana Vannozzi spoke with Rep. Frank Pallone about the tax's return, and why it matters.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="21346688" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/mzxqu7/Hazard-Bonus-Episode_V2.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:08:53</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - A Comeback on the Hackensack - Season 1: Episode 4</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04-a-comeback-on-the-hackensack-meadowlands-superstorm/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-04-a-comeback-on-the-hackensack-meadowlands-superstorm/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Climate change means that cleanup of the river becomes more critical than ever.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Climate change means that cleanup of the river becomes more critical than ever.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 4: A Comeback on the Hackensack" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=jpcgd-126937a-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<p>The mud lining the Hackensack River is a mysterious mixture known to contain mercury, cadmium, lead, PCBs and plenty more nasty substances. Now the river is on its way to becoming New Jersey’s 115th Superfund site — and that’s not a bad thing.</p>
<p>Superstorm Sandy slammed up the Hackensack and surrounding Meadowlands, flooding towns and wreaking widespread damage. But the area’s wetlands likely blunted the blow, and with climate change intensifying storms, cleanup efforts and restoration work in the area are becoming more critical.</p>
<p><em>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></em></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>CADMIUM.</p>
<p>LEAD.</p>
<p>MERCURY.</p>
<p>DIOXIN.</p>
<p>PCBS.</p>
<p>THESE ARE SOME OF THE INGREDIENTS THAT MAKE UP THE TOXIC STEW THAT'S SIMMERED AT THE BOTTOM OF THE LOWER HACKENSACK RIVER FOR DECADES.</p>
<p>EVERY TIME THE RIVER FLOODS... AND IT DOES QUITE OFTEN... THERE'S A RISK THAT THESE TOXINS WILL SPREAD.</p>
<p>CLIMATE CHANGE IS EXPECTED TO MAKE FLOODING HERE MORE INTENSE... AND MORE FREQUENT.</p>
<p>BUT THERE IS SOME CAUSE FOR CELEBRATION... THE LOWER HACKENSACK RIVER MAY SOON BE NAMED NEW JERSEY'S 115th SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>MY FAMILY LIKES TO GO FISHING. MY FIRST BOYFRIEND LOVED TO FLY FISH. TO THIS DAY... I DON'T UNDERSTAND HOW ANYONE COULD FIND FISHING FUN. BUT I DO ENJOY LISTENING TO THE FOLKLORE.</p>
<p>HAVE YOU HEARD THE ONE ABOUT THE DIVER WHO SAW A CATFISH THE SIZE OF A PICKUP TRUCK?</p>
<p>OR THE ONE ABOUT THE TWO-HEADED TROUT?</p>
<p>WHAT ABOUT THE TALE OF THE BLUE CLAW CRABS THAT HAVE HIGH LEVELS OF CANCER-CAUSING TOXINS BUILT UP IN THEIR TISSUE?</p>
<p>THE SCARY THING ABOUT THAT STORY IS THAT IT'S TRUE.</p>
<p>A CENTURY OF POLLUTION LED THE STATE OF NEW JERSEY TO BAN FISHING AND EATING BLUE CLAW CRABS FROM THE LOWER HACKENSACK RIVER.</p>
<p>I'M IMAGINING THESE LARGE... MUTANT CRABS SCARING SWIMMERS AND JUMPING OUT OF THE WATER ONTO BOATS.</p>
<p>BUT MOST OF THE TIME THEY LOOK JUST LIKE NORMAL CRABS... EXCEPT FOR ALL THAT MERCURY INSIDE THEM THAT CAN CAUSE DAMAGE TO THE NERVOUS SYSTEM.</p>
<p>I WENT TO LAUREL HILL COUNTY PARK IN SECAUCUS TO TAKE A TOUR OF THE FAMED HACKENSACK RIVER.</p>
<p>THERE WERE SIGNS IN DIFFERENT LANGUAGES WARNING PARKGOERS ABOUT THE BAN.</p>
<p>I CAN UNDERSTAND WHY PEOPLE WOULD STILL WANT TO FISH IN THE RIVER... DESPITE THE TOXIC CRABS THAT ARE JUST BEGGING TO HAVE A HORROR MOVIE MADE ABOUT THEM.</p>
<p>THE WATER HAD THIS STRANGE BEAUTY... AND I KEPT GETTING HENRY DAVID THOREAU VIBES.</p>
<p>THOUGH ME BECOMING ONE WITH NATURE WAS SHORT-LIVED BECAUSE OF THE BEEP-BEEPING NOISES FROM THE NEARBY CONSTRUCTION OF A LUXURY APARTMENT BUILDING.</p>
<p>IT WAS A SIMILAR WAY OF THINKING ABOUT &quot;DEVELOPMENT&quot; AND &quot;PROGRESS&quot; THAT LAID WASTE TO THE HACKENSACK RIVER TO BEGIN WITH.</p>
<p>THE EPA FOUND THAT A 19-MILE STRETCH OF THE LOWER HACKENSACK'S RIVERBED IS FILLED WITH CONTAMINANTS.</p>
<p>WALTER MUGDAN WITH THE EPA SAYS THESE TOXINS CAN WASH ASHORE WHEN IT FLOODS AND SPREAD ALL OVER THE PLACE.</p>
<p><strong>Walter Mugdan -- Deputy Regional Administrator, EPA Region 2</strong></p>
<p>So, the biggest concern in that case is that major storms can mobilize the mud, they can re-entrain in the mud into the water. If you have flooding that sediment though that mud that's entrained in the water can get onto the land, it can get into people's homes, into buildings. And it can also move stuff around. So, it gets from an area that maybe has less contamination might be moved to an area excavated the other way around from an area that has more contamination, it might move into areas that were less contaminated and actually make them worse.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THIS SPRING... AFTER YEARS OF STUDY... THE EPA FORMALLY NOMINATED THE HACKENSACK TO THE SUPERFUND LIST. IF THE PROCESS GOES AS PLANNED, THE RIVER WILL BECOME NEW JERSEY'S 115th SUPERFUND SITE IN THE FALL.</p>
<p>BEING A DESIGNATED A SUPERFUND SITE MEANS THE EPA CAN BEGIN THE YEARS-LONG PROCESS OF CLEANING UP THE RIVER.</p>
<p>AND ALTHOUGH THERE'S NO GUARANTEE THE RIVER WILL EVER BE CLEAN ENOUGH TO EAT THE BLUE CLAW CRAB... FOR CAPTAIN BILL SHEEHAN... WITH THE HACKENSACK RIVERKEEPER... IT'S WORTH A TRY.</p>
<p><strong>Bill Sheehan -- The Hackensack Riverkeeper</strong></p>
<p>One of the most natural things that humans can do is catch a fish and eat it. And yet, we're told it's not safe to do that. And if we let this river try to clean itself, and you know, shunting aside climate change and future impacts and everything else, if the river is just left to be itself, it could take 150 to 200 years to get to the point where it would be safe to eat a crab or eat a fish. And that means several generations of people living here will not have full beneficial use of the river. By putting it on the Superfund list, even if it takes 20 or 25 years to get it cleaned up, that's one generation's lifetime.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BILL HAS BEEN PUSHING FOR THE HACKENSACK RIVER TO BE DESIGNATED A SUPERFUND SITE FOR YEARS.</p>
<p>HE WAS BORN AND RAISED ALONG THE RIVER... AND IS THE SON OF A BARGE CAPTAIN.</p>
<p><strong>Bill Sheehan -- The Hackensack Riverkeeper</strong></p>
<p>I was always told, growing up, stay away from the river, it was a mess. And, you know, there's raw sewage and dead animals and all kinds of stuff going on. And as I grew older, I got into fishing.</p>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host    **</p>
<p>WHEN I MET HIM AT THE PARK... HE DEFINITELY LOOKED THE PART OF A CAPTAIN. WHAT STOOD OUT THE MOST TO ME WAS THE SHARK TOOTH NECKLACE. IT REMINDED ME OF MY FAVORITE CHARACTER FROM THE MOVIE &quot;JAWS,&quot; QUINT. HE'S THE ONE THAT GETS EATEN BY THE SHARK ON THE BOAT.</p>
<p>ANYWHO... BILL STARTED THE HACKENSACK RIVERKEEPER IN 1997 TO PROTECT THE RIVER FROM POLLUTERS.</p>
<p><strong>Bill Sheehan -- The Hackensack Riverkeeper</strong></p>
<p>I was just getting an attitude about, you know, the fact that everywhere you look, they were destroying habitat. And I was like, don't complain to me about not being able to catch fish if you're giving people permits to fill in wetlands and destroy fish habitat. And so I had an epiphany one day and said, &quot;Nobody else is doing it. I might as well try.&quot;</p>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host    **</p>
<p>IN APRIL... I GOT TO GO ON A TOUR OF THE &quot;URBAN WILDERNESS&quot; WITH BILL ON A STATE GOVERNMENT BOAT.</p>
<p>WE WERE JOINED BY NEW JERSEY DEP COMMISSIONER SHAWN LATOURETTE... WALTER MUGDAN... WHO'S THE DEPUTY REGIONAL ADMINISTRATOR FOR EPA REGION TWO... AND STATE SENATOR TERESA RUIZ.</p>
<p>COMMISSIONER LATOURETTE SAYS IT'S NOT A BAD THING FOR NEW JERSEY TO ADD ANOTHER SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Shawn LaTourette -- Commissioner, New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection</strong></p>
<p>You'll have many states throughout the country that are reluctant to have an NPL listing because they see Superfund as a stain on the state's reputation, or as an inconvenience or something that might detract from the ability to drive economic growth. We see it just the opposite.</p>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host    **</p>
<p>DURING OUR TRIP... THE NOISES OF THE HIGHWAY... TRAINS... AND AIRPLANES COMPETED WITH THE SOUNDS OF BIRDS.</p>
<p>IT WAS A REMINDER OF THE RIVER'S PAST... AND A PEEK INTO THE FUTURE OF WHAT COULD BE IF THIS AREA IS CLEANED UP.</p>
<p>I'M GOING TO TAKE YOU BACK NOW TO 2015.</p>
<p>THIS WAS THE YEAR THE LOWER HACKENSACK ALMOST MADE THE SUPERFUND LIST.</p>
<p>WALTER MUGDAN WITH THE EPA SAYS THE AGENCY STUDIED THE RIVER TO SEE IF IT MET THE PROGRAM'S CRITERIA.</p>
<p><strong>Walter Mugdan -- Deputy Regional Administrator, EPA Region 2</strong></p>
<p>And we found pretty much what you'd expect. We find a lot of mercury. We found arsenic, we found lead. We found PCBs, polychlorinated biphenyls. We found PAH's, which are polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons. So, we found a whole soup of chemicals.</p>
<p>**Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host **</p>
<p>BUT NEW JERSEY'S THEN-GOVERNOR... REPUBLICAN CHRIS CHRISTIE NEVER ENDORSED THE RIVER TO BE PUT ON THE LIST... EVEN THOUGH THE EPA URGED HIM TO DO SO.</p>
<p>IN 2017... THE EPA'S REPORT ON THE RIVER FOUND WIDESPREAD CONTAMINATION... BUT EVEN THAT WASN'T ENOUGH FOR THE CHRISTIE ADMINISTRATION TO SEEK SUPERFUND STATUS FOR THE RIVER.</p>
<p>THE TIDES SHIFTED JUST A FEW MONTHS LATER, WHEN DEMOCRAT PHIL MURPHY BECAME NEW JERSEY'S GOVERNOR AT THE START OF 2018.</p>
<p>NOW, OFFICIALS IN TRENTON WITH A DIFFERENT WAY OF THINKING ARE ALL-IN ON USING THE SUPERFUND TO FINALLY CLEAN UP THE LOWER HACKENSACK.</p>
<p><strong>Shawn LaTourette -- Commissioner, New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection</strong></p>
<p>Having learned a lot from Superfund sites, including the Passaic River nearby, I think we've got a great set of tools, an incredible set of partners in EPA to move this a hell of a lot faster. So, that's our goal.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NO ONE KNOWS HOW MUCH IT'LL COST TO CLEAN UP THE SITE... BUT POLLUTED WATERWAYS ARE SOME OF THE MOST EXPENSIVE TO CLEAN.</p>
<p>TO GIVE YOU SOME IDEA... AND IN CASE YOU HAVEN'T LISTENED TO THE DIAMOND ALKALI EPISODE OF HAZARD NJ... THE PASSAIC RIVER CLEANUP IS EXPECTED TO COST MORE THAN A BILLION DOLLARS.</p>
<p>THE HACKENSACK RIVER WINDS THROUGH THE HEART OF THE NEW JERSEY MEADOWLANDS.... THAT VAST MARSHLAND LONG KNOWN AS A DUMPING GROUND FOR TRASH... AND SOME BELIEVE THE BODIES OF MOBSTERS.</p>
<p>ACCORDING TO URBAN LEGEND... JIMMY HOFFA... THE INFAMOUS TEAMSTER BOSS... IS BURIED UNDER THE OLD GIANTS STADIUM... NOW DUBBED MET LIFE STADIUM.</p>
<p>JUDITH WEIS IS A RUTGERS-NEWARK PROFESSOR WHO'S SPENT DECADES STUDYING THE BIOLOGICAL EFFECTS OF CONTAMINATION IN THE MEADOWLANDS.</p>
<p><strong>Judith Weis -- Professor Emerita of Biological Sciences, Rutgers University, Newark</strong></p>
<p>I think the wetlands is special because it's particularly urban wetland with a bunch of problems. And it has been abused for many, many years. I mean, all the garbage from New York City and the waste from demolishing Penn Station. So, it was a real mess.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BACK IN THE DAY... PEOPLE THOUGHT THE WETLANDS WERE... WELL, MORE LIKE A WASTELAND THAN A PLACE OF TRANQUILITY.</p>
<p>IT WAS LAND THEY THOUGHT COULDN'T BE USED FOR ANYTHING OTHER THAN A DUMP.</p>
<p>OH, AND THEY DUMPED.</p>
<p>THERE WAS A REASON THIS AREA WAS CONSIDERED THE ARMPIT OF THE NORTHEAST. IN 1970... THERE WERE 51 DIFFERENT LANDFILLS OPERATING IN THE MEADOWLANDS.</p>
<p>BUT IT'S MORE THAN JUST A TRASH PROBLEM. THE MEADOWLANDS IS DOTTED WITH SOME OF THE WORST TOXIC SITES IN THE COUNTRY. AND MUCH OF THE POLLUTION IN THE MEADOWLANDS COMES FROM FIVE NEARBY SUPERFUND SITES.</p>
<p>YOU GOT BERRY'S CREEK... A SIX-MILE TRIBUTARY OF THE HACKENSACK RIVER THAT HAS HAD SOME OF THE HIGHEST MERCURY READINGS IN THE WORLD.</p>
<p>MUCH OF THE TOXINS THERE CAME FROM THE VENTRON/VELSICOL OPERATION IN CARLSTADT AND WOOD-RIDGE. THE COMPANY PROCESSED MERCURY FROM 1929 UNTIL 1974.</p>
<p>THEN THERE'S UNIVERSAL OIL PRODUCTS IN EAST RUTHERFORD... WHERE VARIOUS CHEMICALS WERE PRODUCED FROM 1930 TO 1979.</p>
<p>ALSO... SCIENTIFIC CHEMICAL PROCESSING IN CARLSTADT.... WHERE HARSH CHEMICALS WERE USED AS PART OF DEALING WITH SCRAP AND WASTE.</p>
<p>AND DIAMOND HEAD OIL REFINERY... AKA OIL LAKE... IN KEARNY. THAT ONE... KIND OF SPEAKS FOR ITSELF.</p>
<p>THINGS STARTED TO CHANGE... SLOWLY... FOR THE MEADOWLANDS IN THE '50S, WHEN THE NEW JERSEY TURNPIKE BROUGHT NEW INTEREST TO THE AREA.</p>
<p>STATE LEADERS NOW SAW ECONOMIC POTENTIAL IN THE TRASH-FILLED MARSHES. THE HACKENSACK MEADOWLANDS DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION WAS FORMED IN 1968, AND THE '70S BROUGHT A CRACK DOWN ON ILLEGAL DUMPING.</p>
<p>AS THE DUMPS CLOSED ONE-BY-ONE, NEW DEVELOPMENT SPRUNG UP AROUND THEM. A STADIUM FOR THE NEW YORK GIANTS AND NEW YORK JETS... A HORSE RACING TRACK... AN ARENA FOR THE NEW JERSEY NETS...AND MOST RECENTLY AMERICAN DREAM...THE NATION'S SECOND LARGEST MALL.</p>
<p>TODAY... ALL BUT ONE LANDFILL IN THE MEADOWLANDS HAS BEEN CLOSED. MOST OF THE FORMER DUMPS HAVE BEEN CAPPED TO KEEP THE GARBAGE JUICE FROM LEAKING OUT.</p>
<p>JUDITH SAYS THE FEDERAL CLEAN WATER ACT... PASSED IN 1972, WAS A CRITICAL STEP IN CURBING POLLUTION IN THE MEADOWLANDS.</p>
<p><strong>Judith Weis -- Professor Emerita of Biological Sciences, Rutgers University, Newark</strong></p>
<p>So, the raw sewage wasn't going in there anymore, so the water quality got better. I mean, there's things that I've never seen there before. So, I think, a very helpful place in that you see this huge improvement over something that nobody would have ever wanted to visit 50 years ago. When you stop abusing it, and you stop doing all that bad stuff to it, it comes back.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>EVEN WITHOUT A SUPERFUND DISTINCTION... THE MEADOWLANDS HAVE BECOME ONE OF THE STATE'S MOST SUCCESSFUL ENVIRONMENTAL COMEBACK STORIES.</p>
<p>MANY PEOPLE WROTE OFF THE MEADOWLANDS AS A PLACE THAT WAS LEFT FOR DEAD.</p>
<p>BUT THE CLEANUP EFFORTS HAVE ALREADY BROUGHT THE AREA BACK TO LIFE.</p>
<p>ANIMALS HAVE RETURNED.</p>
<p>AND WHAT MAY BE THE BIGGEST SURPRISE... IS THAT PEOPLE ARE ACTUALLY CHOOSING TO VISIT THE MEADOWLANDS TO BIRDWATCH OR KAYAK... OR DO OTHER OUTDOORSY THINGS THAT MY ALLERGIES PREVENT ME FROM DOING.</p>
<p>ECO-TOURISM IS GREAT. I'M GLAD THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO CAN BE OUT ON THE WATER WITHOUT GETTING MOTION SICKNESS.</p>
<p>BUT RESTORING AND PRESERVING THE MEADOWLANDS PLAYS AN EVEN BIGGER ROLE IN THE STATE'S ECONOMY.</p>
<p>THE AREA'S PREPARING THE STATE FOR RISING SEA LEVELS.</p>
<p>DURING SUPERSTORM SANDY IN 2012... COMMUNITIES IN THE MEADOWLANDS WERE DEVASTATED BY A WALL OF WATER THAT ROSE UP FROM NEWARK BAY AND RUSHED UP THE HACKENSACK RIVER.</p>
<p>THERE'S NOT MUCH THAT COULD HAVE TOTALLY PROTECTED PEOPLE FROM THE EIGHT-FOOT-TALL STORM SURGE.</p>
<p>BUT IT'S LIKELY THE MEADOWLANDS BLUNTED THE BLOW.</p>
<p>THINK OF WETLANDS AS NATURE'S SPONGE. THEY HELP SOAK UP WATER AND SEDIMENT FROM RAIN AND STORM EVENTS.</p>
<p>BECAUSE OF SANDY... THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT GAVE THE MEADOWLANDS A MULTI-MILLION-DOLLAR GRANT TO FIGURE OUT WAYS TO REDUCE THE RISK OF FLOODS AND IMPROVE STORM-WATER DRAINAGE.</p>
<p>IT'S A PROJECT CALLED REBUILD BY DESIGN... AND AFTER YEARS OF DEVELOPMENT OFFICIALS DECIDED TO MOVE AHEAD WITH A PROJECT THAT RELIES IN PART ON RESTORING WETLANDS.</p>
<p>DEVELOPMENT HAS SIGNIFICANTLY REDUCED THE SIZE OF THE MEADOWLANDS MARSHES.</p>
<p>AND AS SEA LEVELS CONTINUE TO RISE... THE REMAINING MARSHES AREN'T ALWAYS ABLE TO KEEP UP.</p>
<p>JUDITH SAYS PARTS OF THE MEADOWLANDS ARE BEING DROWNED AWAY... THAT MEANS THE AREA IS LOSING ITS ABILITY TO ABSORB SURGE WATER FROM EXTREME WEATHER EVENTS.</p>
<p><strong>Judith Weis -- Professor Emerita of Biological Sciences, Rutgers University, Newark</strong></p>
<p>There's still more development going on and losing marshes, and, you know, the marshes are so valuable, and they've lost so many already over the past centuries. You can't make up for it by making a new marsh somewhere else. So, we have greatly reduced the amount of marsh. And if you've built something on a marsh, this should be no surprise that it's going to flood easily.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>CAPTAIN BILL'S NOTICED THE RISE IN SEA LEVEL IN THE MEADOWLANDS.</p>
<p>THE WATER LINE THAT USED TO GO UP TO THE DOCKS AT LAUREL HILL PARK... WHERE I STARTED MY RIVER JOURNEY... IS NOW AT THE EDGE OF THE PARKING LOT WHERE THE HACKENSACK RIVERKEEPER'S KAYAKS ARE STORED.</p>
<p>THE TOWN OF LITTLE FERRY KNOWS THE HACKENSACK RIVER'S BEAUTY... AND ITS POTENTIAL FOR HARM.</p>
<p>MAURO RAGUSEO WAS THE MAYOR OF LITTLE FERRY IN 2012.</p>
<p>THAT SPRING HE AND HIS WIFE HAD MOVED INTO THEIR NEW HOME.</p>
<p>BY THE FALL... IT WAS DESTROYED.</p>
<p><strong>Mauro Raguseo -- Mayor, Little Ferry</strong></p>
<p>It was something you never forget; when you can finally get to your house for the first time, and you look and everything that you own is at the curb.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>LITTLE FERRY WAS SMACKED BY SUPERSTORM SANDY. MORE THAN EIGHTY PERCENT OF THE TOWN WAS UNDER WATER... AND RESIDENTS WERE DISPLACED FOR MONTHS AFTER THE STORM.</p>
<p>JOANN LIBRETTO HAS LIVED IN LITTLE FERRY FOR MOST OF HER LIFE.</p>
<p>THE NIGHT SUPERSTORM SANDY HIT THE TOWN... JOANN WAS STAYING WITH HER SISTER... WHO LIVED ACROSS THE STREET.</p>
<p><strong>Joann Libretto -- Little Ferry Resident and Sandy Survivor</strong></p>
<p>So, the night before the storm. I said to her, &quot;You know, today, I have a bad feeling about this storm. I think I'll sleep by you tonight.&quot; She said, &quot;Come on, we'll have a pajama party.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AROUND TEN O'CLOCK... JOANN SAYS HER SISTER'S NEPHEW CALLED AND TOLD THEM &quot;THE WATER'S COMING.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Joann Libretto -- Little Ferry Resident and Sandy Survivor</strong></p>
<p>And before we knew it, the street was filled. The house was just filling up with water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE NEXT DAY... JOANN SAYS SHE WALKED ACROSS THE STREET TO HER HOME TO INSPECT THE DAMAGE.</p>
<p>SHE COULDN'T BELIEVE HER EYES.</p>
<p><strong>Joann Libretto -- Little Ferry Resident and Sandy Survivor</strong></p>
<p>The water was five feet high. The refrigerator was floating. The dining room chairs were floating. In the back room, everywhere you could look, everywhere you can imagine there was water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE WATER WAS MUDDY AND COATED JOANN'S BELONGINGS.</p>
<p><strong>Joann Libretto -- Little Ferry Resident and Sandy Survivor</strong></p>
<p>It was a very, very, very hard time for me. Very hard. I lost everything. I lost my children's wedding videos, my late husband's pictures, my grandchildren's pictures, my washer, my dryer, my refrigerator. Everything, everything. Everything was out on the curb. And when we walked down the blocked and witnessed all this, you thought to yourself 'What happened? What? Was it a bomb? What happened?' It was horrendous. There's no words. There's no words.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JOANN SAYS EVERY TIME THERE'S A STORM SHE CRINGES.</p>
<p><strong>Joann Libretto -- Little Ferry Resident and Sandy Survivor</strong></p>
<p>I think over the years, the fear that it could happen again, is really bad for us. Yeah, that's how I feel right now. And I guess, I thought time would heal, but it doesn't, because you never know. You just don't know. And now they're predicting all these hurricanes. I mean 14 hurricanes. Are we going to be lucky enough to not have an issue?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MAYOR RAGUSEO AGREES THAT ANOTHER SANDY COULD HAPPEN... IN LITTLE FERRY... AND OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.</p>
<p><strong>Mauro Raguseo -- Mayor, Little Ferry</strong></p>
<p>So, we need to do better as a state and as a nation to prepare for the effects of climate change. Because it's real, it's here and it will happen again.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MAURO IS STILL THE MAYOR OF LITTLE FERRY... AND HAS WATCHED THE TOWN BOUNCE BACK.</p>
<p><strong>Mauro Raguseo -- Mayor, Little Ferry</strong></p>
<p>We are better off than we were 10 years ago, but certainly if another Sandy comes, it'll be the same effect because you cannot stop those sorts of surge events.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HE BELIEVES CLEANING UP THE HACKENSACK RIVER WILL HELP PROTECT THE AREA FROM FUTURE STORMS... AND THE SPREAD OF ANY EXISTING TOXINS.</p>
<p>BUT THERE HAS TO BE MORE TO IT THAN THAT.</p>
<p><strong>Mauro Raguseo -- Mayor, Little Ferry</strong></p>
<p>I think that the wetlands that exist need to be restored, I think they have a purpose and a function, and I think they're necessary. But I also think that we have to look at all the options, not just wetlands restoration. But I'm completely for it. Now, all these homes and all these businesses in the entire region, they're not just going to disappear. So that's why we need to restore what's left. And we need to think of engineering opportunities to protect the area as well from surge events.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING #HAZARD NJ.</p>
<p>OR LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... <a href="mailto:HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG" target="_blank">HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG</a>.</p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Associate Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Additional research by Meril Mousoom</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="51477248" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/z7urzc/HAZARDEP4SSV399yb5.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:21:26</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - Heart of Ringwood - Season 1: Episode 3</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-03-heart-of-ringwood-superfund-site-ford-motor-company-toxic-waste-ramapough-lenape-tribal/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-03-heart-of-ringwood-superfund-site-ford-motor-company-toxic-waste-ramapough-lenape-tribal/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Ford Motor Company turned Ringwood Mines and the area around them into a toxic waste dump in the 60s and 70s. The cleanup goes on.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Ford Motor Company turned Ringwood Mines and the area around them into a toxic waste dump in the 60s and 70s. The cleanup goes on.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 3: Heart of Ringwood" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=fmp2t-1256ad4-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<h2 id="the-hazard-podcast-america's-biggest-crime-scene" tabindex="-1">The Hazard Podcast - America’s Biggest Crime Scene</h2>
<p>In July 2005, Roger De Groat stepped outside his home in the secluded, forested community of Upper Ringwood to find a hole the size of a swimming pool where his backyard used to be. Roger’s home, like the rest in the neighborhood, sits atop an extensive and poorly understood system of abandoned iron mines, and sinkholes like these have opened every so often for decades.</p>
<p>But what’s in the mines is a different kind of lingering threat.</p>
<p>Ford Motor Company turned the mines and the area around them into a toxic waste dump in the ’60s and ’70s, with little regard for the community, which was overwhelmingly Ramapough-Munsee Lenape Nation tribal members, that was being dumped on. Today the community is gripped by cancer and other diseases that residents believe are tied to the chemicals Ford left behind.</p>
<p>When the Environmental Protection Agency put the Ringwood Mines on the Superfund list in 1983, an initial shoddy cleanup left so much pollution behind that the site was put back on the list in 2006. A second try at cleaning up the mess is underway. As climate change brings increasingly heavy rains and other impacts to the area, toxic chemicals tied to the site are known to be in the groundwater and threatening to migrate toward a critical water supply reservoir nearby.</p>
<p>And the Ramapough are still living through it all.</p>
<p>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ROGER DE GROAT, SR. HAD JUST FINISHED MOWING HIS BACKYARD IN UPPER RINGWOOD... A SMALL NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE NORTH JERSEY HIGHLANDS.</p>
<p>HE WENT INSIDE HIS HOUSE FOR A WRENCH TO FIX HIS WEED WACKER.</p>
<p>WHEN HE CAME BACK OUT... HIS BACKYARD WAS GONE.</p>
<p>IN ITS PLACE WAS A CRATER THE SIZE OF A SMALL SWIMMING POOL.</p>
<p>ROGER WAS LUCKY... IF HE WOULD HAVE BEEN OUTSIDE EVEN SECONDS LATER... HE WOULD HAVE FALLEN INTO THE SINKHOLE.</p>
<p>BUT STORIES LIKE THIS ONE FROM JULY 2005 AREN'T ISOLATED EVENTS IN RINGWOOD... AND ARE BECOMING MORE FREQUENT BECAUSE OF EXTREME WEATHER FUELED BY CLIMATE CHANGE.</p>
<p>ROGER'S HOME... AND MANY OTHERS IN THIS NORTH JERSEY NEIGHBORHOOD... ARE LOCATED ON TOP OF THE FORMER RINGWOOD MINES.</p>
<p>IT'S AN UNDERGROUND LABYRINTH OF MINE SHAFTS... SOME CENTURIES OLD... THAT WEREN'T ALWAYS PROPERLY FILLED OR SEALED.</p>
<p>EXPERTS ACKNOWLEDGE THAT SOME OF THE OLDEST MINES... WHICH DATE BACK TO THE 1700s... MAY BE UNMAPPED AND HAD THEIR EXACT LOCATIONS LOST TO HISTORY.</p>
<p>THE FOLKS THAT LIVE IN THIS AREA ARE NOT ONLY IN DANGER OF BEING SWALLOWED BY THE EARTH... OH, IF MOTHER NATURE UNLEASHES HER WRATH THEY MAY BE IMPACTED BY WILDFIRES AND FLOODING AS WELL.</p>
<p>THIS WOULD BE TERRIFYING ALL ON ITS OWN. BUT THE FORMER RINGWOOD MINES... WHERE ABOUT 50 HOMES ARE LOCATED... IS ALSO A SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>JUST ONE OF THESE EXTREME WEATHER EVENTS COULD RE-RELEASE TOXINS INTO THIS COMMUNITY... AND ITS WATERSHED.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>I SPENT MANY SUMMERS AS A KID ON MY FAMILY'S PROPERTY IN THE TEXAS HILL COUNTRY.</p>
<p>MY NANA WOULD FILL UP JUGS WITH WATER FROM THE CREEK FOR US TO DRINK.</p>
<p>I WAS CURIOUS IF THE WATER WAS CONTAMINATED. SO, FOR ONE MIDDLE SCHOOL SCIENCE PROJECT I TESTED THE WATER. MY SCIENCE TEACHER REMARKED THAT THE CREEK WATER WAS CLEANER THAN THE WATER I DRANK IN MY HOMETOWN OF SEGUIN TEXAS. HE ENCOURAGED ME TO KEEP DRINKING THAT CREEK WATER.</p>
<p>MORE THAN A DECADE LATER... THE AREA SURROUNDING MY FAMILY'S PROPERTY HAS BECOME DEVELOPED WITH MCMANSIONS AND SHOPPING CENTERS. I WONDER IF THAT CREEK WATER IS STILL AS CLEAN.</p>
<p>I'M NOT THE ONLY ONE WHO HAS WATER ON THE BRAIN. DRIVING TO RINGWOOD, NEW JERSEY... OKAY, BEING IN THE PASSENGER SEAT WHILE MY COLLEAGUE IS DRIVING US TO RINGWOOD, NEW JERSEY... I SAW NUMEROUS SIGNS ABOUT KEEPING THE AREA'S WATER PURE.</p>
<p>THE IRONY OF THESE SIGNS WASN'T LOST ON ME. SEE, FOR MORE THAN 50 YEARS... RINGWOOD HAS BEEN HOME TO A TOXIC DUMP THAT'S IMPACTED THE LAND AND ITS GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p>WELL, THE DUMP IS SPECIFICALLY IN UPPER RINGWOOD... A COMMUNITY IN THE BOROUGH OF RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>FOLKS IN RINGWOOD ARE PROUD OF THE FACT THAT IRON FROM THEIR MINES HELPED THE AMERICAN ARMY DURING THE REVOLUTIONARY WAR. AND THEY TOLD ME ABOUT HOW GEORGE WASHINGTON VISITED THE AREA.</p>
<p>RINGWOOD MANOR WAS ORIGINALLY BUILT TO HOUSE IRON WORKERS. THE BUILDING LATER BECAME THE SUMMER HOME TO THE WEALTHY COOPER-HEWITT FAMILY. TODAY... ITS VAST GROUNDS ARE PART OF RINGWOOD STATE PARK.</p>
<p>A LOT HAS CHANGED HERE OVER THE CENTURIES... THE MINING STOPPED DECADES AGO... AND MANY PEOPLE HAVE COME AND GONE... THAT IS, EXCEPT A SECT OF THE RAMAPOUGH-MUNSEE LENAPE NATION CALLED THE TURTLE CLAN... WHO CONTINUE TO LIVE IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>THEIR ROOTS IN THE AREA STRETCH BACK TO AT LEAST THE REVOLUTIONARY WAR.</p>
<p><strong>Dennis DeFreese, Sr. -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>Our people went back to the 1700s. And way back even further. Because I remember this area here, it used to be a college called Green Engineering Camp. And I remember all the young teenagers there, I used to hang out with them. And they were college students. And you know, it was nice. It was heaven. Ringwood's beautiful. Ringwood was beautiful. But now I go up and where I was born and raised, I look around. I'm like, man, what the heck happened?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>I MET WITH DENNIS DEFREESE SENIOR... AND HIS NEIGHBOR... VAL GUNN... AT THE CHURCH OF THE GOOD SHEPHERD IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>IT'S A SMALL EPISCOPAL CHURCH THAT'S BEEN A GATHERING PLACE FOR THE RAMAPOUGH FOR A LONG TIME.</p>
<p><strong>Valerie Gunn -- Ringwood resident &amp; Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>This church has been in existence from the 1700s.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S VAL. SHE'S ABOUT TO TURN 70... AND IS A PROUD GRANDMA. WHEN WE MET... SHE WAS WEARING A HOT PINK T-SHIRT THAT READ: &quot;GRANDMA.&quot; WITH THE LIST OF HER GRANDCHILDREN'S NAMES. IT REMINDED ME OF MY NANA.</p>
<p>LIFE FOR VAL'S GRANDCHILDREN IS VERY DIFFERENT FROM WHEN SHE WAS A CHILD.</p>
<p>MANY OF HER CHILDHOOD MEMORIES INCLUDE EXPLORING THE SURROUNDING WOODLANDS.</p>
<p>WHAT STUCK OUT TO HER WAS THE WATER.</p>
<p><strong>Valerie Gunn -- Ringwood resident &amp; Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>We used to walk down the path. And we would get water we would carry water from the spring. And you talk about delicious, absolutely great water. Oh, it was the best in the world. I'm telling you. But we had to carry our water when we were kids growing up, but we did it.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>LIKE VAL... DENNIS GREW UP IN UPPER RINGWOOD. HE REMEMBERS DRINKING THE WATER FLOWING NEAR HIS CHILDHOOD HOME.</p>
<p><strong>Dennis DeFreese, Sr. -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>I drank the water. And I never got sick. All the time. I drank it, me and my brothers.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT IS... UNTIL FORD MOTOR COMPANY STARTED DUMPING THOUSANDS OF TONS OF PAINT SLUDGE AND OTHER WASTE FROM THE COMPANY'S ASSEMBLY PLANT IN NEARBY MAHWAH... INTO --- AND AROUND --- THE ABANDONED MINES OF UPPER RINGWOOD</p>
<p>FOR YEARS IN THE 1960s AND '70s... FORD'S PLANT IN MAHWAH CHURNED OUT HUNDREDS OF CARS IN A DAY</p>
<p>FORD WAS MAKING THE AMERICAN DREAM COME TRUE FOR SOME PEOPLE ACROSS THE COUNTRY... AND CREATING AN AMERICAN NIGHTMARE FOR THE RAMAPOUGH PEOPLE.</p>
<p>-- RANGOON RED</p>
<p>-- BRITTANY BLUE</p>
<p>THESE WERE SOME OF THE COLORS OF PAINT THAT WERE SPRAYED ON FORD'S CARS. THE DROPLETS THAT DIDN'T STICK WOULD COLLECT ON THE GROUND AND IN DRAINS BENEATH THE CARS ON THE ASSEMBLY LINE.</p>
<p>AND THAT EXCESS PAINT WAS MUCH OF WHAT WAS COLLECTED AND DUMPED IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>IN 1984... THE 500-ACRE RINGWOOD MINES SITE WAS ADDED TO THE SUPERFUND LIST.</p>
<p>FORD WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR PAYING TO CLEAN UP THE SITE. AND THEY DID IT IN RECORD TIME.</p>
<p>THE EPA GAVE THE SITE A CLEAN BILL OF HEALTH WHEN THEY DELISTED IT IN 1994.</p>
<p>IT TOOK 11 YEARS TO &quot;CLEAN UP&quot; THE SITE... AND IT'LL TAKE EVEN MORE TIME TO UNDERSTAND HOW IT COULD HAVE GONE SO WRONG.</p>
<p>UNDER NORMAL CIRCUMSTANCES... CLEANING UP A SUPERFUND SITE IS CAUSE FOR CELEBRATION.</p>
<p>BUT RINGWOOD MINES WAS NEVER REALLY CLEANED UP IN THE FIRST PLACE.</p>
<p>EVEN AFTER THE SITE WAS DELISTED... RESIDENTS CONTINUED TO FIND PAINT SLUDGE IN THEIR YARDS AND SCATTERED THROUGHOUT UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>I MET JAN BARRY AT THE RINGWOOD MINES SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Jan Barry -- Former reporter, The Record</strong></p>
<p>What caught my attention, besides the fact that somebody had tied colored ribbons along that whole area, because they were creating a hiking trail. And I said to the EPA person who is there, you know, &quot;There's going to be kids walking down this hiking trail.&quot; No interest. We then went over on the far side of this community, at the end of Cannon Mine Road. There was a house, we go to the front yard, they have paint sludge heaving out of the grass in front of the kids play equipment. It was the same house that had the paint sludge in the backyard some years before. And at that point, frankly, I lost it. I said, &quot;You've got to be kidding me. We're back to the same place that you said you cleaned up.&quot; And at that point, I started writing memos to editors.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JAN WAS ONE OF THE REPORTERS WITH THE BERGEN RECORD THAT... ALONG WITH THE RAMAPOUGH... HELPED EXPOSE THE LARGE AMOUNTS OF POLLUTION THAT REMAINED ON THE SITE IN A SERIES OF ARTICLES CALLED &quot;TOXIC LEGACY.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jan Barry -- Former reporter, The Record</strong></p>
<p>We found internal documents where they say, well, the state probably won't take a close look at this. And then it was a housing organization, nonprofit that built these newer houses over here, and they definitely want to take a close look at this gift to them. &quot;Aren't we so nice, giving them this nice contaminated land?&quot; And they had nasty things to say about these local people using the terminology that only local area people would know to use. So Ford was already into the local prejudice against Ramapough Indians. And I guess that plays a huge part in what's going on here.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE THING ABOUT PAINT SLUDGE IS THAT IT LOOKS LIKE A PLAIN OLE ROCK... NOTHING TO WORRY ABOUT</p>
<p>BUT BREAK OFF A CHUNK... AND IT SMELLS LIKE FINGERNAIL POLISH REMOVER... IT'S THE ACETONE INSIDE THAT'S STILL POTENT.</p>
<p><strong>Jan Barry -- Former reporter, The Record</strong></p>
<p>As you break it open, it's so fresh inside. The core never dried, so the chemical smell just erupts. I had a piece of this stuff on my desk in The Record for a long time. Until I'm at some meeting and somebody said, &quot;You know, there's a chemical thing coming off of this all the time. Stick it into a paper bag and then take a breath.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>PAINT SLUDGE CONTAINS A MIXTURE OF TOXIC CHEMICALS... LIKE LEAD... ARSENIC... AND CHROMIUM... AMONG OTHERS.</p>
<p>LEVELS OF LEAD IN PAINT SLUDGE NEAR HOMES HAVE BEEN FOUND TO BE 100 TIMES THE LEVELS THE EPA CONSIDERS ACCEPTABLE</p>
<p>WAYNE MANN... A RAMAPOUGH COMMUNITY LEADER WHO GREW UP IN UPPER RINGWOOD... SAYS KIDS EVEN PLAYED WITH THE PAINT SLUDGE... NOT KNOWING WHAT IT WAS.</p>
<p>HE REMEMBERS ONE OF THE TIMES OFFICIALS CAME BY UPPER RINGWOOD TO INSPECT THE SITE BEFORE IT WAS PUT BACK ON THE SUPERFUND LIST. THIS IS WHAT THEY SAW.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne Mann -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member, named plaintiff in Mann v. Ford</strong></p>
<p>The one yard where they came, a kid was sitting, banging on something playing with his trucks. What he was banging on was a giant piece of sludge, lead. Another yard, kids were out swinging on a swing set. All around that yard and swing set was all protruding through the ground chunks of lead. It's all Ford's. Well, that was supposed to be all cleaned up.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MANY OF UPPER RINGWOOD'S RESIDENTS SAY CONTAMINATION FROM THE PAINT SLUDGE HAS MADE THEM SICK.</p>
<p>THERE ARE CASES OF SKIN RASHES... SEVERE HEADACHES... BLEEDING FROM THE EYES, NOSE, AND THROAT... AND VARIOUS CANCERS.</p>
<p>SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE CANCER... VAL SAYS... THAT LOCALS CALL VAN DUNK LANE &quot;CANCER ROW.&quot; IT EARNED THE GRIM NICKNAME BECAUSE EACH HOUSE ON THE STREET HAS BEEN IMPACTED BY CANCER IN ONE WAY, SHAPE, OR FORM.</p>
<p>WHEN VAL'S NEPHEW... COLLIN... DIED FROM A RARE FORM OF CANCER IN 2001... THAT'S WHEN LOCALS REALLY STARTED TO NOTICE HOW WIDESPREAD THE HEALTH ISSUES WERE IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p><strong>Valerie Gunn -- Ringwood resident &amp; Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>My nephew, my brother's son, developed, it was called Ewing's Sarcoma when he was 10. And he developed that, and that's how everything started. He died a year later; he lived for one year from the time that he developed it. And then after that, it was like, everybody started getting cancer.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DESPITE THIS... NO ONE HAS BEEN ABLE TO FIND A DIRECT LINK BETWEEN THE PAINT SLUDGE AND THESE REPORTED DISEASES.</p>
<p>IN 2006... THE NEW JERSEY DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND SENIOR SERVICES AND THE FEDERAL AGENCY FOR TOXIC SUBSTANCES AND DISEASE REGISTRY RELEASED A REPORT ON THE HEALTH CONCERNS RELATED TO THE SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>THE AGENCIES FOUND THAT FROM 1979 THROUGH 2002... OVERALL CANCER INCIDENCE WAS NOT ELEVATED IN THE AREA OR IN RINGWOOD BOROUGH AS A WHOLE... COMPARED TO NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>SHORTLY BEFORE THE REPORT WAS RELEASED... THE RINGWOOD MINES WAS PUT BACK ON THE SUPERFUND LIST -- A FIRST FOR THE EPA.</p>
<p>WHILE EVERY SUPERFUND SITE NEEDS TO GET CLEANED UP QUICKLY... RINGWOOD MINES... IF I HAD TO MAKE A PRIORITIES LIST... WOULD BE NEAR THE TOP.</p>
<p>I'M NOT PICKING FAVORITES OR ANYTHING... BUT THERE'S JUST SO MANY DIFFERENT WAYS SEVERE WEATHER CAUSED BY CLIMATE CHANGE CAN STILL IMPACT THIS SUPERFUND SITE... AND WREAK HAVOC ON THE RESIDENTS OF UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>TO MAKE THINGS EASIER ON ALL OF US... I'M GOING TO BREAK DOWN EACH OF THE POTENTIAL CLIMATE IMPACTS AS SUCCINCTLY AS I CAN.</p>
<p>MORE PREVALENT... AND INTENSE FOREST FIRES MEANS DANGEROUS TOXINS COULD BE RELEASED IN THE AIR.</p>
<p>DOCTOR JUDITH ZELIKOFF... AN NYU RESEARCHER... LED A STUDY IN 2021 THAT FOUND MUCH HIGHER RATES OF ASTHMA AND BRONCHITIS AMONG THE RAMAPOUGH WHO USED TO OR CURRENTLY LIVE NEAR THE MINES.</p>
<p>WILDFIRES AND DROUGHT WILL ONLY MAKE THESE HEALTH PROBLEMS WORSE.</p>
<p><strong>Judith Zelikoff -- Professor of Environmental Medicine, NYU Grossman School of Medicine</strong></p>
<p>Not only do you have PCBs generated, you're going to have lots of metals, you're going to have polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon carcinogens. So you're going to have if anyone treated their couches or their furniture, you know, with these treatments. So they're all going to be in the air.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JUDITH MENTIONED PCBs. THAT'S A GROUP OF HUMAN-MADE CHEMICALS THAT WERE BANNED IN THE U.S. IN THE LATE 1970s.</p>
<p>EVEN THOUGH THE PRODUCTION OF PCBs IS BANNED... THESE CHEMICALS ARE STILL PRESENT IN OUR AIR... WATER... AND SOIL.</p>
<p>CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING RAINSTORMS MORE INTENSE... AND FREQUENT.</p>
<p>WHEN THAT HEAVY RAINFALL COMES DOWN... THE WATER MAY RUSH THROUGH THE OLD MINES... FAULT LINES... AND CRACKS IN THE ROCK.</p>
<p>IF THIS HAPPENS... THE WATER COULD FLUSH CONTAMINATED GROUNDWATER INTO NEARBY STREAMS AND RIVERS.</p>
<p><strong>Wenke Taule -- Former Mayor of Ringwood</strong></p>
<p>Ringwood sits on what's called fractured bedrock. And no one can tell you where the contaminated water is going to go. It's impossible. Ford says they know. They just can't know.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S WENKE TAULE. SHE BECAME THE BOROUGH'S FIRST WOMAN MAYOR IN 2005... AND WAS IN OFFICE WHEN RINGWOOD MINES WAS PUT BACK ON THE SUPERFUND LIST.</p>
<p><strong>Wenke Taule -- Former Mayor of Ringwood</strong></p>
<p>If something should occur, you know, an event with climate change, flooding, whatever, it could flush this contamination through the fractures.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW... IF UPPER RINGWOOD WAS NOT ON TOP OF MINES... THERE'D BE LESS CONCERN ABOUT THESE FRACTURES IN THE GROUND.</p>
<p>BUT ALEC GATES... A GEOLOGIST WITH RUTGERS-NEWARK WHO SPENT MUCH OF HIS CAREER WORKING IN THE RINGWOOD AREA... SAYS THE MINING HAS PRETTY MUCH STRIPPED AWAY THE GROUND'S NATURAL FILTRATION SYSTEM... POTENTIALLY EXPOSING PEOPLE TO CONTAMINATED WATER.</p>
<p><strong>Alexander Gates -- Distinguished Service Professor of Earth &amp; Environmental Sciences, Rutgers -- Newark</strong></p>
<p>So, if you have bad things on the surface, as long as you have that thick, black layer, they're all anything that comes through, it will tend to filter it out. If you don't have it there, like you do around a mine area, it'll just go straight into the groundwater system without any filtering.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>PEOPLE HAVE BEEN DRINKING THE WATER IN UPPER RINGWOOD FOR A VERY LONG TIME... WAY BEFORE FORD STARTED DUMPING CHEMICALS THERE.</p>
<p>BUT THE POLLUTION HAS GOTTEN SO BAD THAT NO ONE DRINKS IT ANYMORE. AND THEY MAY NEVER DRINK IT AGAIN.</p>
<p>ALEC SAYS THERE'S NO WAY ALL OF THE GROUNDWATER IN THE AREA CAN BE TREATED.</p>
<p><strong>Alexander Gates -- Distinguished Service Professor of Earth &amp; Environmental Sciences, Rutgers -- Newark</strong></p>
<p>They can't even get all the sludge out, it's in the cracks. How are you going to do that? So you would have to, like, excavate the whole area. That's tough rock. That's not going to be easy to excavate. And then how are you going to clean it out?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HEAVY RAINFALL MAY QUICKLY FLOW THROUGH THE SUPERFUND SITE'S FRACTURED BEDROCK... SPREADING ALREADY POLLUTED GROUNDWATER IN WAYS THAT GEOLOGISTS AND ENGINEERS DON'T FULLY UNDERSTAND.</p>
<p>THAT PUTS NEARBY BODIES OF WATER AT RISK... INCLUDING THE WANAQUE RESERVOIR... WHICH SUPPLIES DRINKING WATER TO MORE THAN THREE MILLION PEOPLE ACROSS NORTH JERSEY WHEN DEMAND FOR WATER IS AT ITS PEAK.</p>
<p>I WENT TO THE NORTH JERSEY DISTRICT WATER SUPPLY COMMISSION TREATMENT PLANT IN WANAQUE, JUST SOUTH OF RINGWOOD, TO SEE THE RESERVOIR FOR MYSELF.</p>
<p>WHILE I WAS THERE... I TALKED WITH THE COMMISSION'S EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR... TIM EUSTACE... ABOUT THE RISKS THE RINGWOOD MINES SUPERFUND SITE POSES TO THE RESERVOIR.</p>
<p><strong>Timothy Eustace -- Executive Director, North Jersey District Water Supply Commission</strong></p>
<p>The mine is two-and-a-half miles from here. So, I just want to make sure if anything happens that I can address it a mile away, that it never reaches this body of water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>INCREASINGLY HEAVY RAINS ON THE RINGWOOD MINES SITE COULD SPREAD CONTAMINATION DOWNHILL... WHERE THE RESERVOIR SITS.</p>
<p><strong>Timothy Eustace -- Executive Director, North Jersey District Water Supply Commission</strong></p>
<p>My concern was the fault lines because there's a fault line under the reservoir and there's a fault line along the mountain range where the mines are the end, the geologists say the fault lines do not run the way that I should have concerns. I think the fault lines run east west, and they'd have to be north south for it to create runoff coming down here. So I'm somewhat quelled by that geology report. But you know, Earth doesn't always do what we think it's going to do. So I'm almost comfortable with that report.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>&quot;ALMOST COMFORTABLE.&quot;</p>
<p>THERE'S ONE PESKY CONTAMINANT THAT KEEPS TIM UP AT NIGHT. THAT'S 1,4-DIOXANE... A COLORLESS SOLVENT USED BY INDUSTRIES TO DISSOLVE OILY OR GREASY SUBSTANCES</p>
<p>1,4-DIOXANE WAS FIRST FOUND IN GROUNDWATER AT THE SITE IN THE SPRING OF 2015.</p>
<p>BUT RESIDENTS WEREN'T TOLD UNTIL THE RECORD BROKE THE NEWS NEARLY A YEAR LATER. IN A PUBLIC MEETING AFTER THE FINDINGS WERE MADE PUBLIC, EPA OFFICIALS SAID THEY REGRETTED NOT ANNOUNCING THEM SOONER.</p>
<p>THE CHEMICAL HAS SINCE BEEN FOUND IN SALLY'S POND, A SMALL WATERBODY IN RINGWOOD STATE PARK JUST DOWNHILL OF THE MINES.</p>
<p>THE WATER IN SALLY'S POND EVENTUALLY FLOWS INTO THE WANAQUE RESERVOIR, BUT SO FAR, THE EPA SAYS NONE OF THE CHEMICAL HAS BEEN DETECTED DOWNSTREAM OF THE POND SINCE TESTING BEGAN IN 2016.</p>
<p>TIM SAYS THE EPA TOLD HIM THERE'S &quot;VERY LITTLE CHANCE&quot; OF THE WANAQUE RESERVOIR BEING CONTAMINATED.</p>
<p><strong>Timothy Eustace -- Executive Director, North Jersey District Water Supply Commission</strong></p>
<p>I want no chance of this happening. So, it's my overabundance of caution. And the commissioners here agree with me about that, that we want to be ahead of anything that happens.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT JUST TO BE ON THE SAFE SIDE... TIM SAYS THE RESERVOIR IS ROUTINELY TESTED FOR ONE-FOUR DIOXANE... AND OTHER HAZARDOUS CHEMICALS.</p>
<p>TIM TOOK ME ON A TOUR OF THE COMMISSION'S BIG TREATMENT PLANT TO SHOW ME WHERE THE TESTING HAPPENS.</p>
<p>IT WAS LOUD AND SMELLED LIKE A HIGH SCHOOL GYM.</p>
<p>EVEN THOUGH THE EPA NOW CONSIDERS 1,4-DIOXANE TO BE A &quot;LIKELY HUMAN CARCINOGEN&quot;... IT'S NOT CURRENTLY REGULATED BY THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.</p>
<p>THE SCARY PART IS... ONCE 1,4-DIOXANE IS IN WATER... IT'S LIKELY TO STAY THERE AND DOESN'T BREAK DOWN</p>
<p>AT THE RINGWOOD MINES SUPERFUND SITE... THERE'S ALSO THE INCREASED RISK OF MORE FREQUENT SINKHOLES... LIKE WHAT ROGER DE GROAT, SR. EXPERIENCED IN 2005</p>
<p>WENKE REMEMBERS GETTING A PHONE CALL ONE NIGHT FROM VIVIAN MILLIGAN... A FORMER RAMAPOUGH LEADER...</p>
<p><strong>Wenke Taule -- Former Mayor of Ringwood</strong></p>
<p>There's a gigantic hole in Roger's yard. I said, &quot;What is it, the septic?&quot; &quot;Oh, no. This is something very different.&quot; As it turned out, it was a mine hole that had supposedly been closed in the 1800s that opened up because of water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IF THE RINGWOOD MINES SITE ISN'T CLEANED UP SOON... ALEC SAYS HEAVY AND MORE FREQUENT RAINFALL CAUSED BY CLIMATE CHANGE MAY INCREASE THE RISK OF SINKHOLES IN THE AREA.</p>
<p><strong>Alexander Gates -- Distinguished Service Professor of Earth &amp; Environmental Sciences, Rutgers -- Newark</strong></p>
<p>Obviously, if you do any construction on these mines -- they're extremely dangerous. Because you're going to open things up; the construction equipment falling or you can build something on top of a place that you really shouldn't.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE CLIMATE CONCERNS ALEC... WENKE... AND TIM HAVE FOR UPPER RINGWOOD AREN'T SHARED BY RINGWOOD BOROUGH MANAGER SCOTT HECK.</p>
<p>LET'S SEE, GOING THROUGH OUR LIST HERE...</p>
<p>ON WILDFIRES: SCOTT SAYS...</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>With the exception of a fire that we had, I think a year or two ago, that was a result of the power lines that was in and around the Superfund site, we really have not seen any. We have had a few fires in Upper Ringwood, also, relative that were home fires. But our response is relatively quick to all of those situations, so it's not a big concern for us because we do watch that and we haven't had many at all.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>FLOODING AND GROUNDWATER CONTAMINATION AREN'T GOING TO BE AN ISSUE SCOTT SAYS BECAUSE PART OF THE SITE'S CLEANUP PLAN... WHICH INVOLVES CAPPING THE CONTAMINATED AREA... ADDRESSES THESE CONCERNS.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>The capping calls for a pullback of the waste from the edges and consolidating it away from the brook, so that it minimizes and reduces any chance of that getting into the water stream.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AND SINKHOLE SCHMINKHOLES... SCOTT SAYS THERE'S ONLY ONE AREA &quot;IN-AND-AROUND THE SUPERFUND SITE&quot; THAT'S SUSCEPTIBLE TO THIS PROBLEM.</p>
<p>TO HELP PREVENT THE GATES OF HELL FROM OPENING UP AGAIN... THE BOROUGH'S ENGINEER'S DID A &quot;LOT OF EXTENSIVE RESEARCH&quot; TO ENSURE THAT RESIDENTS STAY SAFE.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>So, we had geotechnical individuals come in and do all kinds of extensive studies. We did borings down to bedrock throughout the entire area. The one area where there was a subsidence in the road we filled in, we remediated. And we have conducted a study throughout the entire area to identify, using mining maps and drilling and borings, to determine where there might be voids. And the engineer has determined that it is safe. And we have addressed any areas of concern.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SCOTT ISN'T ALONE HERE... THE NEW JERSEY DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION TOLD ME THAT THE RINGWOOD AREA HAS A LOW LEVEL OF SINKHOLE RISK COMPARED TO THE REST OF THE STATE.</p>
<p>AND THE EPA SAYS THE NEW CLEANUP PLAN HAS BEEN DESIGNED TO PROTECT AGAINST POTENTIAL SINKING OR CAVING</p>
<p>THE DECADES-LONG SAGA BETWEEN THE RAMAPOUGH AND FORD IS A CLASSIC DAVID AND GOLIATH STORY.</p>
<p>THIS CAPTURED THE ATTENTION OF HBO. THEY SPENT YEARS CHRONICLING THE CLASS-ACTION LAWSUIT FILED BY THE RAMAPOUGH AGAINST FORD FOR DUMPING TOXIC CHEMICALS ON THEIR LAND.</p>
<p>THE DOCUMENTARY'S CALLED MANN V. FORD... NAMED AFTER WAYNE MANN... WHO BECAME A LEADER IN THE FIGHT TO HOLD FORD RESPONSIBLE FOR THE POLLUTION.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne Mann -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member, named plaintiff in Mann v. Ford</strong></p>
<p>In the filming of the documentary, 55 people died in the five years that was being filmed. So there's not as many people there as it used to be that even knows the woods anymore. You know what I mean? Because it's like, it's probably out there. But even more than just the sludge. It's what's in the mines that you're going to never fully investigate because they know, they know what's down there. Or they surmise what's down there. They don't, it's a can of worms, as I was told at one meeting, that doesn't want to be opened.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WAYNE AND I MET UP AT RINGWOOD STATE PARK TO TALK ABOUT HIS PAST EXPERIENCES AS A COMMUNITY LEADER... WHAT HE'S LEARNED... AND WHAT HE PLANS TO DO NEXT.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne Mann -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member, named plaintiff in Mann v. Ford</strong></p>
<p>I stood my ground. And I stood the ground for the people that I loved. And I stood ground for people that I'll never meet that may even dislike me, because maybe they'll say, &quot;Oh, he started trouble.&quot; But I started trouble because you're drinking the water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>YEARS AFTER WAYNE AND OTHER MEMBERS OF THE RAMAPOUGH FILED SUIT... FORD... THEIR CONTRACTORS... AND THE BOROUGH OF RINGWOOD SETTLED WITH THEM FOR $11 MILLION.</p>
<p>MANY FAMILIES ONLY RECEIVED ABOUT $8,000 EACH.</p>
<p>SOME OF THE RAMAPOUGH MAINTAIN MANY OF THEIR TRADITIONS: THEY HUNT DEER AND FISH IN THE NEARBY STREAMS FOR FOOD. THEY GROW VEGETABLES IN THEIR YARDS.</p>
<p>LIVING OFF THIS LAND BEFORE IT WAS KNOWN TO BE A SUPERFUND SITE MAY HAVE EXPOSED THEM TO TOXINS AND HARMED THEIR HEALTH.</p>
<p>AND WHILE VAL STILL LIVES IN UPPER RINGWOOD... DENNIS AND MANY OTHERS HAVE LEFT THEIR ANCESTRAL LAND FOR FEAR THEY'D DIE FROM THE CONTAMINANTS.</p>
<p>NOW THERE'S ONLY A FEW PEOPLE LEFT TO PASS DOWN THE RAMAPOUGH TRADITIONS.</p>
<p>WAYNE SAYS UPPER RINGWOOD... WHERE THE MINES ARE... IS THE HEART OF RINGWOOD. IT STILL BEATS... JUST NOT AS FAST ANYMORE.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne Mann -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member, named plaintiff in Mann v. Ford</strong></p>
<p>You took care of all the treasures surrounding the heart, you let the heart be poisoned. Because why? Because we lived there. You know, but we absorbed it, we accepted it. We stayed. We fought, we didn't want to go anywhere.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE FEAR IS THAT ONE DAY SOON... THE ONLY LIVING REMINDERS OF THE RAMAPOUGH WILL BE THE RECREATIONAL SPACES NAMED BY EUROPEAN COLONISTS: THE RAMAPO MOUNTAINS AND THE RAMAPO RIVER.</p>
<p>AND DESPITE THE BATTLE WITH TOXINS... AND CLIMATE CHANGE... AND LAWSUITS WITH COMPANIES... THE BIGGER FEAR IN THIS REGION IS THAT PEOPLE WILL FORGET THE PEOPLE THESE PLACES ARE NAMED AFTER.</p>
<p>RAMAPOUGH CLAN MOTHER VIVIAN MILLIGAN WAS UPPER RINGWOOD'S UNOFFICIAL HISTORIAN.</p>
<p>VIVIAN SPOKE WITH THE RINGWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY'S ORAL HISTORY PROJECT.</p>
<p>HERE SHE IS TALKING ABOUT THE ORIGINS OF THE LAST NAME VAN DUNK.</p>
<p><strong>Vivian Milligan -- Lifelong Ringwood resident</strong></p>
<p>Supposedly, a Dutch name because a lot of Dutch settlers did come right up the Hudson, far and wide, along with the Native Americans, and they settled along the Hudson.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>VAN DUNK LANE... AKA CANCER ROW... IS NAMED AFTER THESE FOLKS</p>
<p>VIVIAN LIVED IN THE AREA HER ENTIRE LIFE... AND SPENT YEARS TRYING TO GET FORD TO CLEAN UP THE MINES.</p>
<p>IN 2016... SHE GOT DOWN ON HER KNEES AT A PUBLIC MEETING WITH AN EPA OFFICIAL AND BEGGED THEM TO REMOVE THE WASTE... INSTEAD OF CAPPING IT</p>
<p>VIVIAN DIED LAST AUGUST, BEFORE SHE COULD SEE THE RINGWOOD MINES CLEANED UP. BUT HER LEGACY LIVES ON.</p>
<p>TO MANY RAMAPOUGH... THEIR CONCERNS HAVE FALLEN ON DEAF EARS.</p>
<p>THEIR STORY IS ONE THAT'S HISTORICALLY BEEN TOLD BY PEOPLE WHO AREN'T RAMAPOUGH.</p>
<p>RACIST MYTHS ABOUT THE COMMUNITY HAVE CAUSED THEM TO BE DEMONIZED. RESIDENTS TOLD US STORIES OF RACISM THEY'VE BEEN SUBJECTED TO... AND THERE'S A BELIEF THAT FORD PICKED THEIR HOMES TO DUMP ON AS A FORM OF DISCRIMINATION.</p>
<p>IN 1980... THE RAMAPOUGH WERE RECOGNIZED AS A TRIBE BY THE STATE OF NEW JERSEY. BUT... DESPITE NUMEROUS EFFORTS... THE TRIBE STILL ISN'T RECOGNIZED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT</p>
<p>THE RAMAPOUGH DON'T HAVE TIME TO WAIT AROUND FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO CHANGE THEIR MIND.</p>
<p>INSTEAD... SOME MEMBERS ARE RECLAIMING THE TRADITIONS FORD AND THE BOROUGH OF RINGWOOD STOLE.</p>
<p>I VISITED THE MUNSEE THREE SISTERS MEDICINAL FARM IN ANDOVER TOWNSHIP... ABOUT AN HOUR AWAY FROM RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>IT WAS A DAY TOO HOT FOR MY BLACK CARDIGAN... AND THE GROUND WAS TOO MUDDY FOR MY BLACK FLATS. JUST GOES TO SHOW THAT IT'S BEEN A LONG TIME SINCE I WAS ON A FARM.</p>
<p>I WAS THERE TO MEET VINCENT MANN... CHIEF OF THE RAMAPOUGH'S TURTLE CLAN... AND CO-FOUNDER OF THE FARM.</p>
<p>CHIEF MANN CO-CREATED THE FARM IN 2019 TO ADDRESS FOOD INSECURITY IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p><strong>Vincent Mann -- Turtle Clan Chief, Ramapough Lenape Nation</strong></p>
<p>It's not just about providing food to our community who shouldn't be growing vegetables where they are in the Superfund site, but it's also about food sovereignty. We grew up in a pretty crappy society, but in the same breath, you know, we're still here. And, you know, while we held on to a lot, you know, including our identity, people are now beginning to wake up to that fact even more so, right?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT CHIEF MANN'S ULTIMATE GOAL IS TO HAVE THE RESIDENTS OF UPPER RINGWOOD RELOCATED... PERMANENTLY... TO A NEW COMMUNITY THAT WOULD BE BUILT ON NEARBY COUNTY PARK LAND.</p>
<p>IT'S AN IDEA THAT HAS COME UP IN PUBLIC MEETINGS IN THE PAST... BUT CHIEF MANN IS NOW READY TO REALLY START PUSHING IT.</p>
<p>JUST LAST MONTH... CHIEF MANN MET WITH EPA AND STATE OFFICIALS... PLUS CONGRESSMAN FRANK PALLONE AND JOSH GOTTHEIMER... TO MAKE HIS LATEST PITCH</p>
<p>THIS WAS LAID OUT IN A POWERPOINT PRESENTATION THAT WAS SHARED WITH NJ SPOTLIGHT NEWS AFTERWARDS.</p>
<p>IN THE POWERPOINT... CHIEF MANN ASKED FOR 300 RESIDENTS... CURRENTLY LIVING IN 50 HOMES... TO BE MOVED INTO 100 NEW HOMES ON TRANQUILITY RIDGE. THAT LAND'S NOT FAR FROM THE EXISTING NEIGHBORHOOD IN UPPER RINGWOOD.</p>
<p>THE COST? AT LEAST $50 million</p>
<p>THIS ISN'T UNHEARD OF. THE SUPERFUND LAW ALLOWS THE EPA TO PAY FOR TEMPORARY OR PERMANENT RELOCATION IF IT'S DEEMED NECESSARY TO PROTECT PUBLIC HEALTH</p>
<p>BUT THIS HAS ONLY HAPPENED 33 TIMES... AND ONLY 11 OF THOSE RELOCATIONS WERE PERMANENT.</p>
<p>ONE OF THOSE WAS THE GRAND STREET MERCURY SITE IN HOBOKEN... WHERE FREE-FLOWING MERCURY WAS FOUND DRIPPING BETWEEN THE FLOORS OF AN OLD INDUSTRIAL BUILDING.</p>
<p><strong>Walter Mugdan -- Deputy Regional Administrator, EPA Region 2</strong></p>
<p>Literally liquid mercury was found when they were doing reconstruction. It was found in the walls, it was dripping down to the ceilings, it was in the closets falling on to people. So, the County Health Department actually made the decision there, literally overnight, that people had to move out of the building.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>RIGHT NOW... THE EPA IS NOT CONSIDERING RELOCATION AS AN OPTION IN RINGWOOD</p>
<p>WALTER MUGDAN... THE DEPUTY REGIONAL ADMINISTRATOR FOR EPA REGION 2... SAYS RELOCATION IS ONLY CONSIDERED WHEN ALL OTHER CLEANUP OPTIONS HAVE BEEN EXHAUSTED.</p>
<p><strong>Walter Mugdan -- Deputy Regional Administrator, EPA Region 2</strong></p>
<p>Relocation is considered an extraordinary remedy. And one that is considered to be appropriate when there's an immediate threat to residents that can't be addressed through other less intrusive means.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>STILL... EPA DID COMMIT AT THE MEETING TO TAKE ANOTHER LOOK AT THE RELOCATION OPTION... AT CHIEF MANN'S REQUEST.</p>
<p>IT DOESN'T HELP THAT WITHOUT FEDERAL RECOGNITION, THE RAMAPOUGH DON'T HAVE THE SAME INFLUENCE OVER THE SUPERFUND PROCESS THAT ANOTHER TRIBE MIGHT.</p>
<p>CHIEF MANN SAYS AFTER THE DECADES OF DUMPING... AND THE BOTCHED CLEAN UP... THE RAMAPOUGH OF UPPER RINGWOOD DESERVE THE CHANCE TO START OVER WITH A CLEAN SLATE.</p>
<p><strong>Vincent Mann -- Turtle Clan Chief, Ramapough Lenape Nation</strong></p>
<p>It's not just because we want a shiny new house, and it isn't because relocating our community now is going to stop, you know, the health ailments, the cancers, and the deaths right now. But we don't think about just tomorrow, we think about the next seven generations. We need to bring our community back together. We have, you know, hundreds of people who moved away from there, thinking that they were going to protect themselves, except for the fact that because their parents were exposed to these toxic chemicals, they too, no matter how far away they move, they can move all the way to the moon, and they're still going to have those health ailments.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT VAL... WHO I MET UP WITH AT THE CHURCH OF THE GOOD SHEPHERD IN RINGWOOD... DOESN'T WANT TO LEAVE.</p>
<p><strong>Valerie Gunn -- Ringwood resident &amp; Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member</strong></p>
<p>Well, I'm not gonna lie to you. I love it here. You know, I'm not gonna say &quot;Oh, yeah, you know.&quot; I absolutely love it here. It's just things have to be done right. Things have to be done better.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WAYNE MANN SAYS THERE ARE PEOPLE LIKE VAL AND HIS SISTER WHO WANT TO STAY BECAUSE OF THEIR FAMILIAL CONNECTION WITH THE LAND.</p>
<p><strong>Wayne Mann -- Ramapough Lenape Turtle Clan member, named plaintiff in Mann v. Ford</strong></p>
<p>For my sister, she already told me when she goes, she's going like her parents did. You know, and it's home. It's the only home that they know. I can't answer that for the rest of the community, because that's Vincent's job. He speaks for them. I speak for the environment.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AND ANGEL STEFANCIK, A 22-YEAR-OLD WHO HAS SPENT HER ENTIRE LIFE IN UPPER RINGWOOD AND IS NOW RAISING A FAMILY THERE, THINKS THAT LEAVING WOULD BE THE OPPOSITE OF THE GOAL OF DECOLONIZATION. TO HER, LAND BACK MEANS STAYING ON THE LAND THEY'RE CURRENTLY ON.</p>
<p><strong>Angel Stefancik -- Ramapough Lenape Nation Turtle Clan member and Ringwood resident</strong></p>
<p>You're giving them what they want. They want us to just uproot and just go. That's they're whole sole purpose because once they get their hands on our land, guess what? It's free game.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SO, WHAT HAPPENS NOW FOR THE RAMAPOUGH?</p>
<p>IT'S CLEAR THAT CHIEF MANN FACES A TOUGH ROAD AHEAD IN CONVINCING BOTH THE GOVERNMENT AND HIS OWN COMMUNITY IN RELOCATING THE RESIDENTS OF UPPER RINGWOOD. AND THAT WORK IS JUST BEGINNING.</p>
<p>BUT BACK ON THE FARM... HE REMAINS OPTIMISTIC THAT THE TURTLE CLAN'S BEST DAYS LIE AHEAD.</p>
<p>SURROUNDED BY ACRES OF SPROUTING CROPS AND A PAIR OF PLAYFUL DOGS... CHIEF MANN SAYS HE FINDS HOPE AND INSPIRATION IN WHAT'S ALREADY BEEN ACCOMPLISHED.</p>
<p>AND THAT FUELS A DETERMINATION TO MOVE AHEAD.</p>
<p><strong>Vincent Mann -- Turtle Clan Chief, Ramapough Lenape Nation</strong></p>
<p>You know, my grandfather always told me that the sun is always shining somewhere. Doesn't matter if it's night or day. Doesn't matter right now. It always is shining. And I just thought when I was younger, that that meant that the sun was always shining. Which was a metaphoric thing. But I didn't really understand that, you know. But I do. The sun is literally shining, all the time.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE EPA REACHED A $21 MILLION SETTLEMENT WITH FORD IN 2019 TO CAP THE SITE. THIS MONEY WOULD ALSO HELP PAY TO REMOVE CONTAMINATED SOIL FROM AROUND THE OPENING OF ONE OF THE MINE'S PITS</p>
<p>THIS IS A CONTROVERSIAL MOVE BECAUSE IT MEANS TONS OF THE POLLUTED SOIL WILL STILL REMAIN ON SITE UNDER AN ASPHALT BARRIER... AND ACROSS THE STREET FROM MANY OF THE RAMAPOUGH'S HOMES.</p>
<p>FORD'S NOT THE ONLY ONE ON THE HOOK FOR THE CLEANUP.</p>
<p>THE BOROUGH OF RINGWOOD OWNED THE LAND THE COMPANY DUMPED ON... AND BECAUSE OF THAT THE EPA HAS DETERMINED THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT IS PARTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MESS.</p>
<p>SCOTT SAYS OVER THE YEARS THE BOROUGH HAS APPEALED THE EPA'S DECISION THAT MAKES THEM PARTIALLY LIABLE FOR THE SITE'S POLLUTION.</p>
<p>HE SAYS THERE HAVE EVEN BEEN POINTS WHERE THE BOROUGH'S DISAGREED WITH FORD. BUT THERE WAS NO WAY AROUND THE BOROUGH PAYING SOMETHING TO CLEAN UP THE SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>At some point you have to determine, &quot;Listen, the EPA said we're a responsible party and there's a percentage that has been agreed upon that we're going to be compensating the Ford Motor Company because there was also many, many years ago dumping there both acknowledged or known about by the borough of Ringwood as well as the state of New Jersey.&quot; So, are we a responsible party? We accept that we are only because we own the property and there was some knowledge back then, theoretically; I still don't understand why, when the state is in the exact same party, why they're not a responsible party.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE EPA HAD ORIGINALLY PLANNED TO HAVE THE BOROUGH AND FORD PAY MORE THAN $32 MILLION TO REMOVE THE CONTAMINATION FROM JUST ONE PART OF THE SITE.</p>
<p>BUT THAT CHANGED WHEN FORD AND THE BOROUGH PITCHED A NEW PLAN TO ONLY REMOVE SOME OF THE POLLUTION AND PUT A PROTECTIVE CAP OVER THE REST.</p>
<p>THIS PLAN ALLOWS THE BOROUGH TO BUILD A NEW... LARGER... RECYCLING CENTER ON TOP OF THE CAPPED SOIL... AND ACROSS THE STREET FROM THEIR CURRENT RECYCLING CENTER.</p>
<p>THE MOVE LOWERED THE CLEANUP COSTS TO A LITTLE OVER $5 MILLION... AND HAD A MIXED REACTION FROM RINGWOOD RESIDENTS.</p>
<p>THOSE WHO WANTED THE POLLUTION REMOVED WERE OUTRAGED. OTHERS... WHO WORRIED A MORE EXPENSIVE CLEANUP WOULD RAISE THEIR PROPERTY TAXES... SUPPORTED THE CONSTRUCTION OF A NEW RECYCLING CENTER.</p>
<p>THE EPA WENT ALONG WITH THE NEW PLAN BECAUSE, THEY SAID, IT STILL PROTECTS PUBLIC HEALTH ... AND BECAUSE, OF COURSE, THEY DON'T HAVE ANY CONTROL OVER HOW A TOWN WANTS TO USE THEIR LAND.</p>
<p>THIS IS DESPITE THE FACT THAT THE AGENCY ORIGINALLY WANTED TO GET RID OF THE TOXIC SOIL.</p>
<p>SCOTT SAYS CAPPING THE SITE WAS IN THE BEST INTERESTS OF &quot;ALL INVOLVED.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>I mean, think about it, to excavate all this material out, the plan was for 13,250 truck trips out of the neighborhood. What would that do to the folks that are living in and around there? I mean, 13,250 truck trips; it would have significantly increased the amount of time that this cleanup would take. It would significantly impact their day-to-day lives for a long time. What risks are associated with moving that type of material? What risks are associated to the children in the neighborhood? And what risks are associated with digging it out for that length of time and impacting a stream while you're digging out?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MOST OF THE CLEANUP IS COMPLETE, SCOTT SAYS.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>I think that the excavation is substantially complete. And I don't know exactly the ultimate percentage but I think that you'll see that in the next coming months that'll be wrapped up significantly.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>FORD DECLINED TO ANSWER SPECIFIC QUESTIONS THAT WE SENT THEM.</p>
<p>INSTEAD... A COMPANY SPOKESPERSON SENT US THIS:</p>
<p><em>&quot;Ford Motor Company takes its environmental responsibility seriously and has shown through its actions a commitment to addressing the issues in Upper Ringwood that are related to Ford.  Ford continues to work cooperatively with the Borough of Ringwood, the United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection (NJDEP).  Contractor activities to remedy the three soil areas requiring remediation started in late fall of 2021.&quot;</em></p>
<p>WHAT COULD BE THE FINAL CLEANUP AT RINGWOOD MINES BEGAN EARLIER THIS YEAR.</p>
<p>SCOTT'S HOPEFUL THIS WILL BE THE LAST TIME RINGWOOD MINES WILL BE ON THE SUPERFUND LIST BECAUSE THE CLEANUP AREA HAS BEEN EXPANDED.</p>
<p><strong>Scott Heck -- Ringwood Borough Manager</strong></p>
<p>I'm hoping that they have learned from their errors of the past that this is the last remediation, although I have to tell you, from my perspective, watching what went on, and they did really go above and beyond to ensure that there's not a third cleanup so, so they maybe they have corrected some of those issues in the past. And I think we're going to get a good cleanup and the residents are going to be better off for it.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING HASHTAG #HazardNJ.</p>
<p>OR LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... <a href="mailto:HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG" target="_blank">HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG</a>.</p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Associate Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Additional research by Mer Mousoom</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Audio Recording Engineer – Frank Brown</p>
<p>Music composed by Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Artwork by Matthew Fleming</p>
<p>Animated trailer created by Everest Strayer</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="97183808" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/web/8ew9df/Hazard-Episode-Three_Ringwood-Mines_V2_MB_06202022.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:40:29</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - America’s Biggest Crime Scene - Season 1: Episode 2</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-02-passaic-river-industrial-pollution-dioxin-agent-orange-diamond-alkali-americas-biggest-crime-scene/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-02-passaic-river-industrial-pollution-dioxin-agent-orange-diamond-alkali-americas-biggest-crime-scene/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>Toxic mud at the bottom of the lower Passaic River, from decades of industrial dumping, remains exposed to storms made increasingly severe by climate change.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[Toxic mud at the bottom of the lower Passaic River, from decades of industrial dumping, remains exposed to storms made increasingly severe by climate change.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 2: America’s Biggest Crime Scene" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=trgwz-123c7d3-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<h2 id="the-hazard-podcast-america's-biggest-crime-scene" tabindex="-1">The Hazard Podcast - America’s Biggest Crime Scene</h2>
<p>The chemical company Diamond Alkali, one of the nation’s main producers of Agent Orange, spent years dumping chemical waste into the Passaic River and polluting Newark’s Ironbound neighborhood. Dioxin, a dangerous byproduct of the company’s work, was found in high levels in the neighborhood in the early ’80s, spurring emergency government action and leaving residents concerned about the safety of their homes and front yards.</p>
<p>State and federal authorities pledged to clean the mess up but today, nearly 40 years later, toxic mud still lies beneath the water — a 17-mile-long stretch of river that U.S. Sen. Cory Booker has called “America’s biggest crime scene.” Now the cleanup is facing a $1.8 billion price tag, an uncertain timeline, and the growing threat that intense storms fueled by climate change could stir the pollution up out of the river and back into the neighborhood.</p>
<p>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>TORRENTIAL RAINS.</p>
<p>HOWLING WINDS.</p>
<p>WIDESPREAD FLOODING.</p>
<p>IN 2012... HURRICANE SANDY WAS ONE OF THE MOST DESTRUCTIVE STORMS TO MENACE THE EAST COAST IN DECADES.</p>
<p>THE STORM SLAMMED INTO THE NEW JERSEY COASTLINE... CREATING A TIDAL SURGE THAT FORCED THE PASSAIC RIVER AND NEWARK BAY OVER THEIR BANKS AND INTO NEWARK'S IRONBOUND NEIGHBORHOOD.</p>
<p>THIS SMALL GRID OF STREETS IS SURROUNDED BY TOXIC SITES: FACTORIES... A POWER PLANT... WAREHOUSES... CHEMICAL REFINERIES... NEW JERSEY'S LARGEST TRASH INCINERATOR... AND THE DIAMOND ALKALI SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>THAT LAND, WHICH ONCE HELD AN AGENT ORANGE FACTORY, IS JUST ONE PART OF THE TOXIC SITE. THE REST IS A GOOEY MIXTURE OF MUD... SAND... AND CHEMICALS AT THE BOTTOM OF THE PASSAIC RIVER.</p>
<p>TERRIFIED RESIDENTS WERE FORCED TO FLEE AFTER SANDY FILLED THEIR HOMES WITH POLLUTED WATER.</p>
<p>CLIMATE CHANGE HAS SET THE STAGE FOR MORE SANDY-SIZE MEGA-STORMS IN YEARS TO COME... AND THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT THE PASSAIC RIVER WILL FLOOD AGAIN.</p>
<p>WHEN IT DOES... THERE'S A RISK OF THESE CHEMICALS BEING STIRRED UP.</p>
<p>IF THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE IS NOT CLEANED UP SOON... THIS TOXIC NIGHTMARE WILL CONTINUE.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS.</p>
<p>I'VE NEVER BEEN IN A HURRICANE... BUT WHEN I WAS EIGHT YEARS OLD THERE WAS A MASSIVE FLOOD IN MY HOMETOWN OF SEGUIN TEXAS.</p>
<p>I REMEMBER WATCHING REFRIGERATORS FLOAT DOWN THE RIVER AND WONDERING WHAT KINDS OF CHEMICALS COULD BE LEACHING INTO THE WATER AND INTO PEOPLE'S HOMES.</p>
<p>AFTER THE FLOOD... NO ONE REALLY TALKED ABOUT THE POTENTIAL HEALTH EFFECTS OF DRINKING OR SWIMMING IN FREON-CONTAMINATED WATER. THERE WERE RUMORS THOUGH OF THREE-EYED FISH.</p>
<p>THE IRONBOUND ... WITH ABOUT FIFTY-THOUSAND RESIDENTS... HAS MORE PEOPLE THAN SEGUIN.</p>
<p>WHEN I VISITED THE NEIGHBORHOOD... I DIDN'T HEAR ANY STORIES OF THREE-EYED FISH... BUT I WAS TOLD NOT TO EAT ANYTHING THAT COMES OUT OF THE PASSAIC RIVER.</p>
<p>THERE ARE SIGNS ALL AROUND RIVERFRONT PARK WARNING GUESTS NOT TO CATCH AND EAT CRAB AND FISH FROM THE RIVER.</p>
<p>THIS HAS TO DO WITH THE AREA'S INDUSTRIAL LEGACY... AND SERVES AS A STARK REMINDER THAT THE IRONBOUND IS STILL EXTREMELY POLLUTED.</p>
<p>NEARLY A DECADE AFTER SANDY... RESIDENTS OF THE IRONBOUND ARE STILL AFRAID OF THE LONG-TERM HEALTH CONSEQUENCES OF THE TOXINS THAT SPILLED INTO THEIR HOMES.</p>
<p>AND THEY HAVE A GOOD REASON TO BE.</p>
<p>JUST A FEW FEET AWAY IS A SUPERFUND SITE. AND NOT JUST ANY SUPERFUND SITE... ONE OF THE LARGEST AND MOST EXPENSIVE ON THE LIST.</p>
<p>THE DIAMOND ALKALI SUPERFUND SITE SITS AT THE HEART OF THE IRONBOUND.</p>
<p>IT WAS A FORMER FACTORY WHERE THE DEADLY HERBICIDE AGENT ORANGE WAS MANUFACTURED THROUGHOUT THE VIETNAM WAR.</p>
<p><strong>Maria Lopez-Nuñez -- Deputy Director of Organizing and Advocacy, Ironbound Community Corporation</strong></p>
<p>So, the Diamond Alkali site, it was the largest producer of Agent Orange in the world, and everyone talks about this one thing: a white powder that, like, covered the whole factory, you know, like, everything was covered in this white dust, and it was, like, a sticky dust. So, if you walked in, you would get it all over your shoes and that dust was dioxin. And so, it was being carried all over the neighborhood.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MARIA LOPEZ-NUNEZ IS LEADING THE FIGHT FOR ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE AS AN ORGANIZER WITH THE IRONBOUND COMMUNITY CORPORATION... OR ICC.</p>
<p>THE ICC WAS STARTED 52 YEARS AGO WHEN RESIDENTS CREATED A DAYCARE CENTER.</p>
<p>THEY LATER FOUGHT AGAINST THE CONSTRUCTION OF A GARBAGE INCINERATOR FROM COMING INTO THE NEIGHBORHOOD.</p>
<p>AND IT'S BEEN A WILD RIDE EVER SINCE.</p>
<p>AGENT ORANGE... NAMED FOR THE ORANGE IDENTIFICATION STRIPES PAINTED ON ITS BARRELS... CONTAINED DIOXIN. THAT'S A HIGHLY TOXIC CHEMICAL THAT HAS NO COLOR OR ODOR.</p>
<p>DIOXIN WAS AMONG THE TOXIC CHEMICALS FOUND IN 1978 AT ONE OF THE MOST NOTORIOUS SUPERFUND SITES... LOVE CANAL.</p>
<p>IN 1983... 14 YEARS AFTER DIAMOND ALKALI CLOSED... DIOXIN WAS FOUND IN THE IRONBOUND.</p>
<p><strong>Nancy Zak -- Ironbound resident and activist</strong></p>
<p>In the swimming pool there was dioxin discovered.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S NANCY ZAK.</p>
<p>SHE'S TALKING ABOUT THE HAYS PARK SWIMMING POOL. DIOXIN WAS FOUND AROUND A DRAIN THERE WHEN OFFICIALS WERE TESTING THE AREA FOR THE CHEMICAL.</p>
<p><strong>Larry Stuelpnagel -- New Jersey Nightly News, 1983</strong></p>
<p>The dioxin was discovered as technicians looked for the possible spread of contamination from the former Diamond Alkali plant one-half mile away.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BEFORE THE DISCOVERY... THERE WERE REPORTS THAT SOME OF THE CHILDREN WHO SWAM THERE DEVELOPED SKIN RASHES.</p>
<p>NANCY AND HER HUSBAND... ARNOLD COHEN... HAVE BEEN ACTIVISTS IN THE IRONBOUND FOR DECADES.</p>
<p>ARNOLD SAYS THE DISCOVERY OF DIOXIN IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD DIDN'T COME AS A COMPLETE SURPRISE.</p>
<p><strong>Arnold Cohen -- Ironbound resident and activist</strong></p>
<p>On the one hand, you knew there's a lot of toxic industries along the river, but yet the extent of it was unbelievable that, you know, you're talking about, could talk about the largest concentrations of dioxin found anywhere in soil blocks away from where we lived was completely shocking.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE IRONBOUND IS A TIGHT-KNIT COMMUNITY THAT'S ALREADY FACED A DISPROPORTIONATE NUMBER OF ENVIRONMENTAL HAZARDS.</p>
<p>IT'S NOT A COINCIDENCE THAT LOW-INCOME AND MINORITY COMMUNITIES ARE THE ONES LIVING NEXT TO THESE HAZARDOUS SITES THAT NO ONE WANTS IN THEIR BACKYARD.</p>
<p>ADVOCATES CALL THIS ENVIRONMENTAL RACISM.</p>
<p>WITHIN THE TANGLE OF ROADS... RAILWAYS... AND HIGHWAYS... THERE ARE PEOPLE... JUST TRYING TO LIVE THEIR LIVES.</p>
<p>RESIDENTS OF THE IRONBOUND ARE PREDOMINANTLY HISPANIC... AND THE NEIGHBORHOOD HAS LONG BEEN AN IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY.</p>
<p>UNFORTUNATELY... THIS ISN'T SURPRISING. MOST OF NEW JERSEY'S SUPERFUND SITES ARE IN THE BACKYARDS OF LOW-INCOME... OR MINORITY COMMUNITIES WHO ALREADY FACE A GREATER RISK OF HEALTH PROBLEMS.</p>
<p>AND NOW... CLIMATE CHANGE THREATENS TO DAMAGE SUPERFUND SITES LIKE DIAMOND ALKALI... AND SPREAD POLLUTION EVEN FURTHER.</p>
<p><strong>Sen. Cory Booker -- D, New Jersey</strong></p>
<p>I'm one of the, I would imagine, few senators that lives in a city that has the number of Superfund sites this one has and surprise, surprise, I'm a senator, I think the only senator who lives in a low-income black and brown community.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE INEQUITIES ARE FRUSTRATING FOR MANY OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN LEADING THE CHARGE TO CLEANUP DIAMOND ALKALI.</p>
<p>NANCY AND ARNOLD ORGANIZED DEMONSTRATIONS IN THE 1980S.</p>
<p>THEY BROUGHT THE COMMUNITY TOGETHER TO PROTEST AGAINST THE STATE'S HANDLING OF THE DIOXIN CONTAMINATION... AND TO STOP FUTURE POLLUTION.</p>
<p><strong>Nancy Zak -- Ironbound resident and activist</strong></p>
<p>It's always important; how many people you have involved and how many are calling up their councilman and stuff like that. So, we would have big demonstrations where people could come out. And that gave us, you know, just having those numbers is very important when you're dealing with any politicians of any kind.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AS A CHILD... DOCTOR ANA BAPTISTA AND HER FAMILY PARTICIPATED IN SOME OF THESE EVENTS.</p>
<p><strong>Ana Baptista -- Co-Chair, Passaic River Superfund Community Advisory Group</strong></p>
<p>My parents bought a house down on the industrial end of town and my neighbor down the street, June, like, was knocking on all the neighbor's doors; she saw that we had moved in. And my parents, you know, don't speak English. So, she's, like, &quot;We're fighting the incinerator, so tell your parents to come to this meeting at the Rec Center.&quot; And they had like a little flyer in Portuguese and Spanish and English. And I told my parents about it. And I would go with them to these meetings to translate. And I was like, maybe 10, 9, 10 years old. I'm sure I did a terrible job translating. But there I was.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ANA SAYS HER PARENT MOVED TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD FROM PORTUGAL IN THE 1980S. THEY GOT INVOLVED WITH THE ICC EARLY ON AND AS ANA GREW OLDER... SHE JOINED IN THE FIGHT.</p>
<p><strong>Ana Baptista -- Co-Chair, Passaic River Superfund Community Advisory Group</strong></p>
<p>It was a very intergenerational fight. You know, the timeline also feels, like, impossibly long. But, like most things, you just have to keep showing up for them to come to life.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>GROWING UP... ANA SAYS SHE STAYED AWAY FROM THE PASSAIC RIVER.</p>
<p><strong>Ana Baptista -- Co-Chair, Passaic River Superfund Community Advisory Group</strong></p>
<p>The little you knew about the river was don't get near it. Don't go in it. Definitely don't touch it, like, everybody knew, like, it was a dirty river, very polluted.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SHE SHOWED ME AROUND RIVERFRONT PARK... ONE OF THE FEW GREENSPACES IN THE AREA.</p>
<p>THE PARK OPENED IN 2013 AND EXPANDED A FEW YEARS LATER.</p>
<p>RIVERFRONT PARK SHOULDN'T BE HERE. THAT IS... IF ESSEX COUNTY AND THE CITY OF NEWARK HAD THEIR WAY IN THE '90S.</p>
<p>THE PARK WAS SUPPOSED TO BE A MINOR LEAGUE BASEBALL STADIUM. BUT THE IRONBOUND COMMUNITY CORPORATION DID WHAT THE ORGANIZATION HAS ALWAYS DONE BEST... FOUGHT TOOTH AND NAIL ON BEHALF OF RESIDENTS.</p>
<p><strong>Ana Baptista -- Co-Chair, Passaic River Superfund Community Advisory Group</strong></p>
<p>So, that just shows you that back then there was not much of a premium or value put to parks, especially on a waterfront that was really contaminated. They just didn't see the value of it. But residents, you know, kept it alive.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ANA AND OTHER LONG-TIME RESIDENTS OF THE IRONBOUND REMEMBER PLAYING IN AND AROUND THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE AS CHILDREN.</p>
<p>THEY ATE FOOD GROWN IN SOIL THAT MAY HAVE BEEN TAINTED WITH DIOXIN.</p>
<p>TRUCKS COMING IN-AND-OUT OF THE FACTORY TRACKED DIOXIN THROUGHOUT NEWARK.</p>
<p>COULD THESE EXPERIENCES BE THE CAUSE OF BIRTH DEFECTS AND CANCER?</p>
<p>MAYBE. THERE AREN'T MANY STUDIES LOOKING AT THE LONG-TERM HEALTH EFFECTS OF DIOXIN.</p>
<p><strong>Melissa Miles -- Executive Director, New Jersey Environmental Justice Alliance</strong></p>
<p>It wasn't until my own family was impacted by the sort of things that we know happen, you know, when you live in a neighborhood with pollution.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>MELISSA MILES IS THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR FOR THE NEW JERSEY ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE ALLIANCE.</p>
<p><strong>Melissa Miles -- Executive Director, New Jersey Environmental Justice Alliance</strong></p>
<p>When you're pregnant and you live too close to roadways that have diesel pollution, when you have children in a community that has an issue with lead in the water, like, these things started to manifest in my own family and that's when it really became more of a mission for me to make sure that other parents in this community, you know, knew what was happening and that they had a voice and that they could stand up and fight for their community that they lived in.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SHE WAS INVOLVED IN THE PASSAGE OF THE STATE'S LANDMARK ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE BILL IN 2020.</p>
<p>THE BILL REQUIRES COMPANIES TO GET APPROVAL FROM THE STATE DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION BEFORE BUILDING... EXPANDING... OR RENEWING PERMITS IN LOW-INCOME NEIGHBORHOODS.</p>
<p>COMPANIES ALSO HAVE TO HOLD PUBLIC HEARINGS AND PROVIDE A STATEMENT ON HOW THE PROJECT'S GOING TO IMPACT RESIDENTS BEFORE THEY GET APPROVED.</p>
<p>THIS IS ALL WELL AND GOOD NOW... BUT THINGS LIKE IMPACT STATEMENTS AND APPROVAL FROM THE DEP JUST WEREN'T TOP OF MIND WHEN THE DIAMOND ALKALI PLANT CLOSED IN 1969.</p>
<p>IT WAS THE MORNING OF JUNE 3... THEN-GOVERNOR TOM KEAN DECLARED A STATE OF EMERGENCY.</p>
<p><strong>Gov. Tom Kean -- R, Governor of New Jersey 1982-1990. Speaking in 1983.</strong></p>
<p>We've asked the EPA to immediately begin cleaning the street in question. The dirt may be contaminated with dioxin. We expect that cleanup, which will consist of large-scale vacuuming with special equipment, will begin today, and all the homes so far sampled in the entire area have come back showing now dioxin contamination. It appears the contaminated dirt is not finding its way into residences</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE ORDER STOPPED TRAIN TRAFFIC... EXPANDED AN EXISTING BAN AGAINST EATING CRAB AND FISH FROM THE PASSAIC... AND SHUT DOWN THE NEWARK FARMERS' MARKET... WHERE MANY RESIDENTS BOUGHT THEIR FOOD.</p>
<p>GOVERNOR KEAN OFFERED TEMPORARY HOUSING AT THE NEWARK YMCA FOR PEOPLE WHO LIVED WITHIN 300 YARDS OF THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE.</p>
<p>FOR EVERYONE IN THE CITY... HE ADVISED THEM TO STAY INDOORS DURING THE CLEANUP.</p>
<p>THE NEXT DAY... RESIDENTS SAW PEOPLE IN &quot;MOON SUITS&quot; WITH HEADGEAR AND RESPIRATORS DIGGING AROUND THEIR FRONT YARDS.</p>
<p><strong>Bob Schapiro -- New Jersey Nightly News, 1983</strong></p>
<p>Federal environmental officials went door-to-door in Newark's Ironbound neighborhood today. They wanted the contents of people's vacuum cleaner bags. To find out if traces of deadly dioxin may have drifted a block or two from the original site at 80 Lister Avenue.</p>
<p>PHOTOS FROM THE TIME SHOW EPA WORKERS VACUUMING UP DIRT TO TEST IT FOR DIOXIN.</p>
<p>MARIA LOPEZ NUNEZ WITH THE ICC REMEMBERS HEARING THESE STORIES FROM RESIDENTS WHO LIVED IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD AT THE TIME OF THE &quot;INVASION.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Maria Lopez-Nuñez -- Deputy Director of Organizing and Advocacy, Ironbound Community Corporation</strong></p>
<p>You hear, especially from folks that have lived here their whole lives, that they were sitting there in their T-shirts because this was happening in the summer there in tank tops and shorts sitting on the porch being like, &quot;Why do you need a Hazmat suit?&quot; You know, like that contrast of the government workers looking like they were on the moon, but they were just in the Ironbound.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>DIOXIN HAD MOVED FROM THE DIAMOND ALKALI PLANT AND SPREAD THROUGHOUT THE NEIGHBORHOOD... MUCH FURTHER THAN WHAT GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS ORIGINALLY TOLD THEM.</p>
<p>RESIDENTS FELT LIKE THEY NEEDED TO TAKE MATTERS INTO THEIR OWN HANDS. SO... THEY FORMED THE IRONBOUND HEALTH ADVISORY COMMISSION.</p>
<p>THE ORGANIZATION DEMANDED HEALTH CHECKS FOR RESIDENTS... MORE TESTING FOR DIOXIN AND OTHER TOXIC CHEMICALS... AND COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT IN DECISION MAKING.</p>
<p>THERE WERE GOOD REASONS FOR RESIDENTS TO NOT TRUST THE GOVERNMENT.</p>
<p>OFFICIALS WITH THE STATE OF NEW JERSEY HAD RECEIVED A FEDERAL REPORT THAT THERE WAS LIKELY DIOXIN AT THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE... THREE YEARS BEFORE ANY TESTS WERE CONDUCTED.</p>
<p>SOME HOMEOWNERS THOUGHT THE WHOLE THING WAS JUST A RUSE BY THE GOVERNMENT TO TAKE AWAY THEIR HOMES IN ORDER TO MAKE WAY FOR NEW BUSINESS.</p>
<p>TO MAKE MATTERS WORSE... FOR NEARLY 20 YEARS... DIAMOND ALKALI DUMPED AN ESTIMATED 700,000 GALLONS OF DIOXIN INTO THE PASSAIC RIVER.</p>
<p>THE TRICKY THING ABOUT DIOXIN IS THAT IT CAN ATTACH ITSELF TO PARTICLES... LIKE DUST... AND SPREAD EASILY. IT'S ALSO DIFFICULT TO DISSOLVE IN WATER.</p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE EPA CLAIMED THEY DIDN'T KNOW HOW DANGEROUS DIOXIN REALLY WAS.</p>
<p>RITA M. LAVELLE... FORMER HEAD OF THE SUPERFUND PROGRAM... TOLD REPORTERS IN 1983</p>
<p>&quot;IT GETS ME THAT SOME SCIENTISTS ARE SAYING DIOXIN IS THE MOST DEADLY CHEMICAL KNOWN TO MAN. THAT'S NOT TRUE. IT DEPENDS ON THE CONCENTRATION. IN THE RIGHT CONCENTRATION, TABLE SALT IS JUST AS DEADLY.&quot;</p>
<p>LAVELLE WAS LATER FOUND TO HAVE MISUSED SUPERFUND DOLLARS DURING HER TIME WITH THE EPA.</p>
<p>SCIENTISTS KNEW THE CHEMICAL WAS AN INDUSTRIAL BY-PRODUCT. BUT THE ONLY EVIDENCE THEY HAD OF DIOXIN'S HARMFUL EFFECTS WAS CAUSING THE SKIN CONDITION CHLORACNE... WHICH RESEMBLES SEVERE ACNE.</p>
<p>LATER IT WAS DISCOVERED THAT A RARE FORM OF CANCER CALLED SOFT-TISSUE SARCOMAS IS LINKED TO DIOXIN EXPOSURE.</p>
<p>SOFT-TISSUE SARCOMAS ARE AN AGGRESSIVE FORM OF CANCER THAT DEVELOPS IN THE BODY'S CONNECTIVE TISSUES.</p>
<p>EIGHT CASES OF CANCER WERE REPORTED BY DIAMOND ALKALI WORKERS. NONE WERE IDENTIFIED AS SOFT-TISSUE SARCOMAS.</p>
<p><strong>Michael Gordon -- Environmental Lawyer</strong></p>
<p>They had literally every conceivable environmental threat going on in the Ironbound community at the time. And lo and behold, the next thing that happened was the discovery of the highest levels of dioxin ever found anywhere in the world in the Ironbound on the plant site. So, there was literally pandemonium.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THAT'S ATTORNEY MICHAEL GORDON. HE SPENT MUCH OF THE 1980S TRYING TO FIND PROOF THAT DIAMOND ALKALI KNEW DIOXIN WAS A PROBLEM AND DIDN'T DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT.</p>
<p>IT WASN'T EASY. BUT ONE DAY IN 1986 GORDON FOUND INTERNAL MEMOS BETWEEN A DIAMOND ALKALI EMPLOYEE AND OFFICIALS AT A CHEMICAL COMPANY IN GERMANY.</p>
<p><strong>Michael Gordon -- Environmental Lawyer</strong></p>
<p>They sent around their experience to all of the manufacturers of Agent Orange in America at the time, which was Diamond Alkali, Dow, Monsanto, a number of, Hercules, and they described what they had to do from an outbreak of illness amongst their workers to prevent the formation of dioxin which greatly reduced the threat of illness to the workers. And they described controlling the temperature and the pressure when you made this product.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE DOCUMENTS PROVED THAT DIAMOND ALKALI KNEW FOR YEARS THAT DIOXIN POSED A HEALTH RISK TO ITS WORKERS... BUT DIDN'T DO ANYTHING ABOUT IT FOR ECONOMIC REASONS.</p>
<p><strong>Michael Gordon -- Environmental Layer</strong></p>
<p>And they did not convert to that process, because they had a small, older plant. And the government was literally buying everything they could produce for a period of time for use in Vietnam. And they did not want to delay production, shut down, reconfigure or rebuild the plant. So, they chose not to incorporate those measures. And that's why they produced some of the highest levels of dioxin found in the Agent Orange product.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>GORDON FINALLY HAD A CASE AGAINST THE COMPANY.</p>
<p>IN 1986... FORMER WORKERS SUED THE COMPANY FOR DAMAGES. THEY ALSO SUED THE STATE'S DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION IN THE HOPE THAT THEY'D BE FORCED TO CLEAN UP THE SITE.</p>
<p>AFTER THE SEVENTH WEEK OF THE TRIAL... DIAMOND ALKALI AGREED TO A $1 MILLION DOLLAR SETTLEMENT.</p>
<p>ABOUT A YEAR AFTER DIOXIN WAS DISCOVERED IN THE IRONBOUND... THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE WAS ADDED TO THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 1984.</p>
<p>OVER THE YEARS... THE BUILDINGS ON THE PROPERTY WERE DEMOLISHED... AND SOME OF THE TOXIC WASTE WAS BURIED THERE UNDERGROUND.</p>
<p>THE PROPERTY ITSELF WAS CAPPED WITH CONCRETE AND GRAVEL.</p>
<p>BUT... A 17-MILE STRETCH OF THE PASSAIC RIVER REMAINS SO POLLUTED THAT EVEN TRYING TO CLEAN IT UP MAY PROVE TO BE DISASTROUS.</p>
<p>A THICK LAYER OF DIOXIN FROM THE FACTORY IS BURIED TWELVE FEET IN THE RIVER. LOCALS CALL THIS STICKY SLUDGE &quot;BLACK MAYONNAISE.&quot;</p>
<p>TRYING TO GET DOWN TO THIS LAYER OF DIOXIN COULD CAUSE THE CHEMICAL TO SPREAD UP AND DOWN THE RIVER.</p>
<p>THERE'S A LOT OF TALK ABOUT WHETHER OR NOT THIS SEDIMENT SHOULD BE REMOVED... AND IF IT IS REMOVED... IF IT CAN BE DONE SAFELY.</p>
<p>RIGHT NOW... CLEANUP PLANS CALL FOR DREDGING SOME OF THE CONTAMINATED SEDIMENTS FROM THE RIVER. THAT MUCK WOULD THEN BE TREATED AT A FACILITY THAT HASN'T BEEN BUILT YET IN THE IRONBOUND.</p>
<p>THE REMAINING SEDIMENT WOULD BE CAPPED WITH A THICK LAYER OF SAND. CAPPING IS A COMMON WAY OF CLEANING UP SUPERFUND SITES. THE IDEA IS TO PREVENT ANOTHER STORM FROM KICKING UP THE CONTAMINATED SEDIMENT.</p>
<p>THIS PLAN HAS MIXED REVIEWS.</p>
<p>WHILE THE EPA SAYS THE CAP'S DESIGN TAKES CLIMATE CHANGE AND EXTREME WEATHER EVENTS INTO ACCOUNT... OTHERS ARE CONCERNED THAT THE MODELS USED ARE OUTDATED.</p>
<p>THERE'S ALSO THE WORRY THAT ONCE CLEANUP BEGINS... THE CONSTRUCTION COULD CAUSE DIOXIN-LACED DUST TO SPREAD FURTHER.</p>
<p>MARIA LOPEZ-NUNEZ WORRIES ABOUT WHAT COULD HAPPEN TO THE IRONBOUND IF THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE IS IMPACTED BY RISING SEA LEVELS AND MORE HURRICANES.</p>
<p><strong>Maria Lopez-Nuñez -- Deputy Director of Organizing and Advocacy, Ironbound Community Corporation</strong></p>
<p>Anybody who lives here can tell you it's getting rainier and rainier. So, I actually think the geography of the Ironbound is gonna change, like, the way it looks. The space that the river occupies is gonna change. And I'm not sure... I worry, right? When I look on a map, I worry about where the Diamond Alkali site is, and that increased rain, that river depth, that river boundary. I worry the river will take the Diamond Alkali site with it and what that will mean, you know, will the cap hold?</p>
<p>REGARDLESS OF THE CLEANUP METHOD... SOMEONE'S GOING TO HAVE TO PAY FOR IT.</p>
<p>THE PRICE TAG RIGHT NOW IS $1.8 BILLION... THE MOST EXPENSIVE CLEANUP IN THE HISTORY OF THE SUPERFUND PROGRAM.</p>
<p>DIAMOND ALKALI IS LARGELY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE RIVER'S POLLUTION. BUT OTHER COMPANIES POLLUTED THE RIVER TOO.</p>
<p>THAT'S ONE OF THE REASONS WHY IT'S TAKEN SO LONG TO CLEAN UP THE SITE... NO ONE THINKS THEY'RE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE POLLUTION AND WANTS TO PAY.</p>
<p>FORMER NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR JIM FLORIO SPEARHEADED THE SUPERFUND LAW WHILE HE WAS IN CONGRESS IN 1980.</p>
<p><strong>Gov. Jim Florio -- D, NJ 1st Congressional District 1975-1990, Governor 1990-1994</strong></p>
<p>One of the principles we built into the law was that the polluters should pay, and it would be the mantra. And we've changed things. And my grandchildren, to this day, they're adults now, but they mention, &quot;Pop Pop was in charge of getting the dolphins back.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>FLORIO... NOW AN ENVIRONMENTAL LAWYER... HAS SUPPORTED EFFORTS TO REINSTATE A TAX ON THE OIL AND CHEMICAL INDUSTRIES. THIS TAX EXPIRED IN 1995.</p>
<p>MONEY FROM THE TAX WOULD GO INTO THE SUPER...FUND TO HELP PAY FOR THE CLEANUP OF &quot;ORPHAN&quot; SITES. THESE ARE TOXIC PLACES WHERE THE POLLUTER IS UNKNOWN OR UNABLE TO PONY UP THE FUNDS TO CLEAN UP THE MESS.</p>
<p>IN THE PAST FEW YEARS... SENATOR CORY BOOKER... FORMER MAYOR OF NEWARK... AND REPRESENTATIVE FRANK PALLONE HAVE PUSHED TO REINSTATE THE TAX ON OIL COMPANIES.</p>
<p><strong>Sen. Cory Booker -- D, New Jersey</strong></p>
<p>Well, you have these polluting companies, chemical companies, oil companies that we know, are offsetting a lot of their costs onto society. And it's about putting a very small tax on those companies that then is directed towards Superfund cleanup. And what we've seen since the Superfund tax was eliminated the number of Superfund sites in America has actually gone up, not down. And so it yields enough money to really start focusing and getting some of this cleanup done on these orphan sites where we can't hold someone accountable.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>BUT SO FAR... THE BILL HAS STALLED IN CONGRESS.</p>
<p>REPRESENTATIVE PALLONE SAYS THERE'S ONE WAY TO GET THE POLLUTERS TO PAY.</p>
<p><strong>Rep. Frank Pallone -- D, NJ 6th Congressional District</strong></p>
<p>The majority of the cleanup is done by the polluter or paid for by the polluter under direction of the EPA. And so, you just have to constantly push and embarrass them and, you know, sometimes bring people to public hearings where they criticize the proposed plans that they have for cleanup because they're not adequate. So that's the kind of thing that I do.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>LAST YEAR... PRESIDENT BIDEN'S INFRASTRUCTURE PACKAGE INCLUDED THE REINSTATEMENT OF THE SUPERFUND TAX ON SOME CHEMICAL COMPANIES... BUT NOT OIL AND GAS.</p>
<p>I'M A HUGE HORROR FAN... SO WHEN I THINK OF SUPERFUND SITES... I THINK OF THAT MONSTER FROM THE MOVIE JEEPERS CREEPERS.</p>
<p>OKAY... BEAR WITH ME HERE. SO IN THE MOVIE JEEPERS CREEPERS...</p>
<p>SOME OF THE TOWNSPEOPLE WHERE THE MOVIE TAKES PLACE KNOW ABOUT THE MONSTER.</p>
<p>THEY KNOW IT COMES OUT EVERY 23rd SPRING FOR 23 DAYS, YOU KNOW, TO EAT PEOPLE.</p>
<p>BUT THE FEW PEOPLE WHO HAVE TRIED TO GET RID OF IT HAVEN'T BEEN SUCCESSFUL... SO THEY JUST LIVE WITH THIS KNOWLEDGE THAT EVENTUALLY THE MONSTER WILL COME BACK AND WREAK HAVOC.</p>
<p>IT'S THIS IDEA OF THE MONSTER LURKING IN THE BACKYARD THAT I'M DRAWN TO... AND SUPERFUND SITES ARE THOSE MONSTERS.</p>
<p>THEY MAY NOT HAVE WINGS... IN THE CASE OF THE JEEPERS CREEPERS MONSTER... BUT THEY HAVE THE POTENTIAL TO BE EVEN MORE DANGEROUS WHEN IMPACTED BY CLIMATE CHANGE.</p>
<p><strong>David Robinson -- New Jersey State Climatologist</strong></p>
<p>We've seen sea levels rise and the rise is accelerating, the pace of the increase is accelerating. And areas that are very close to sea level are getting inundated with a frequency we've not seen previously.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>QUOTES LIKE THAT FROM DAVE ROBINSON... NEW JERSEY'S STATE CLIMATOLOGIST... REALLY UNDERSCORE THE NEED TO CLEAN UP SUPERFUND SITES LIKE DIAMOND ALKALI... NOW.</p>
<p><strong>David Robinson -- New Jersey State Climatologist</strong></p>
<p>I think we have to look to what the future may hold for all of these threats. And they're a little bit grim. So, we better be prepared and be able to adapt and accommodate these changes when it comes to Superfund sites or everyday life.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IT'S HARD FOR ME TO STAY OPTIMISTIC WHEN THE CLEANUP OF THE DIAMOND ALKALI SITE IS STILL YEARS AWAY.</p>
<p>AND NO ONE KNOWS IF IT'LL EVER BE SAFE TO SWIM OR FISH IN THE PASSAIC.</p>
<p>BUT I CAN'T HELP REMEMBERING SOMETHING ANA TOLD ME DURING OUR TIME AT THE PARK.</p>
<p><strong>Ana Baptista -- Co-Chair, Passaic River Superfund Community Advisory Group</strong></p>
<p>You can almost imagine a river with, teeming with oysters and clams, and it wasn't even tidal back then in the 1600s, we turned it tidal. We messed with it so much. But one day, we won't get back there, but we'll get back to something, something so that at least people can enjoy the river to some extent more than they are now even.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING HASHTAG HAZARD NJ.</p>
<p>OR LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... <a href="mailto:HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG" target="_blank">HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG</a></p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Associate Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Additional research by Betsy Laikin</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Audio Recording Engineer – Frank Brown</p>
<p>Music composed by Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Artwork by Matthew Fleming</p>
<p>Animated trailer created by Everest Strayer</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="68271488" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/web/3qtnyc/Hazard-Episode-Two_Diamond-Alkali_MB_05312022.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:28:26</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - On Thin Ice - Season 1: Episode 1</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-01-bridgewater-nj-american-cyanamid/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 14:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/episode-01-bridgewater-nj-american-cyanamid/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>At the toxic American Cyanamid Superfund site in Bridgewater, floodwaters are a constant concern.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[At the toxic American Cyanamid Superfund site in Bridgewater, floodwaters are a constant concern.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Episode 1:  On Thin Ice" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?i=6auwc-122b5d1-pb&from=pb6admin&pbad=0&square=1&share=1&download=1&rtl=0&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<h2 id="the-hazard-podcast-on-thin-ice" tabindex="-1">The Hazard Podcast - On Thin Ice</h2>
<p>Growing up in Bridgewater, New Jersey, Peggy Fussell has fond memories of ice skating on a local pond. That is, until she discovered that the pond was a toxic waste site.</p>
<p>Decades after chemical producer American Cyanamid ceased its Bridgewater operations, and was declared a Superfund site, its toxic legacy is precariously contained in local waste ponds. As climate change fuels more intense storms in the region, these ponds risk flooding and spilling over into the nearby community.</p>
<p>With a cleanup that has dragged on for decades and has no clear end in sight, what will it take to avoid catastrophe?</p>
<p>Support for Hazard NJ is provided by Peril and Promise, a public media reporting initiative covering the human stories of climate change and its solutions, with major funding provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos. You can learn more at <a href="https://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a></p>
<h3 id="read-the-episode-transcript-below:" tabindex="-1">Read the episode transcript below:</h3>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>--BENZENE</p>
<p>--TOLUENE</p>
<p>--XYLENE</p>
<p>--NAPHTHALENE</p>
<p>--HYDROGEN SULFIDE</p>
<p>--SULFUR DIOXIDE</p>
<p>--MERCAPTANS</p>
<p>--CARBON DISULFIDE</p>
<p>THIS WITCHES BREW OF CHEMICALS WERE MIXED TOGETHER BY AMERICAN CYANAMID IN BRIDGEWATER, NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>THE COMPANY'S CAULDRON OF CHOICE WAS TWO LARGE HUMAN-MADE PONDS NEAR THE RARITAN RIVER.</p>
<p>SHROUDED BY TREES AND AWAY FROM ONLOOKERS... THESE PONDS SAT STILL BY THE RIVER'S EDGE FOR DECADES.</p>
<p>UNTIL RECENT FLOODING SHOWED US WHAT COULD HAPPEN IF SITES LIKE AMERICAN CYANAMID AREN'T CLEANED UP.</p>
<p>EVERY TIME WE GET A MAJOR STORM WE RUN THE RISK OF TOXINS SEEPING INTO OUR WATERWAYS.</p>
<p>AND CLIMATE CHANGE IS MAKING THINGS WORSE.</p>
<p>THIS IS HAZARD... A LIMITED SERIES ABOUT THE IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON SUPERFUND SITES HERE IN NEW JERSEY.</p>
<p>I'M JORDAN GASS-POORE'... AN INVESTIGATIVE JOURNALIST FROM TEXAS. I GREW UP HEARING STORIES ABOUT THREE-EYED FISH IN THE RIVER AND WONDERING WHY THE TAP WATER I WAS DRINKING WAS ORANGE.</p>
<p>I WAS THAT KID WHO STOOD UP IN FRONT OF CLASS AND ASKED PEOPLE TO SIGN MY PETITION TO SAVE THE RAINFOREST.</p>
<p>IT'S GOTTEN SLIGHTLY EASIER OVER THE YEARS TO GET PEOPLE TO CARE ABOUT THE ENVIRONMENT... ESPECIALLY WHEN I'M TALKING ABOUT HAZARDOUS SUPERFUND SITES.</p>
<p>THOSE ARE THE MOST TOXIC SITES IN THE COUNTRY... AND NEW JERSEY IS HOME TO 114 OF THEM. THAT'S THE MOST OUT OF ANY STATE.</p>
<p>AMERICAN CYANAMID IS A TRIPLE THREAT: IT'S LOCATED IN A FLOODPLAIN... REGULARLY FLOODS... AND IS VULNERABLE TO HURRICANES.</p>
<p>SO... IT'S NOT HARD TO SEE WHY MARK SCHMIDT IS CONCERNED. HE'S THE EPA PROJECT MANAGER FOR THE SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Mark Schmidt -- EPA Remedial Project Manager</strong></p>
<p>Could these impoundments erode? Could all the infrastructure, you know, we have a groundwater treatment facility, electrical infrastructure, could all that be washed away?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>I RECENTLY VISITED AMERICAN CYANAMID.</p>
<p>IT WAS SO... INNOCUOUS. AND PEACEFUL. THE SILENCE WAS OCCASIONALLY PIERCED BY A HORN AND THE RATTLE OF AN NJ TRANSIT TRAIN... DELIVERING COMMUTERS TO THEIR HOMES NEARBY.</p>
<p>MY NERVES DIDN'T KICK IN UNTIL I GOT HOME THAT EVENING AND NOTICED SOME LIGHT BROWN DUST ON MY BOOTS. I NOW CALL THESE SHOES MY &quot;SUPER BOOTS.&quot;</p>
<p>BACK ON THE SITE... WITH MY &quot;SUPER BOOTS&quot; AND SHOTGUN MIC... I SAW WHITE SIGNS ON SUPPORT POLES THAT SHOWED HOW HIGH THE FLOODWATERS GOT DURING:</p>
<p>--TROPICAL STORM DORIA IN 1971... NEARLY 38 FEET.</p>
<p>--HURRICANE FLOYD IN 1999... SLIGHTLY OVER 42 FEET.</p>
<p>--HURRICANE IRENE IN 2011... RIGHT AROUND 42 FEET.</p>
<p>--AND TROPICAL STORM IDA... A RECORD 43 FEET.</p>
<p>AMID THE DOOM AND GLOOM... A FEW THINGS STOOD OUT TO ME:</p>
<p>THERE WAS A WOODPECKER ON AN ELECTRICAL POLE...</p>
<p>...AND DUCKS IN THE PONDS.</p>
<p>THESE SIGNS OF LIFE ARE ENCOURAGING... AND GIVE ME HOPE THAT ONE DAY THE SITE WILL BE A LOVELY... WHOLE FOODS.</p>
<p>THE NEXT TIME IT FLOODS... WILL HAZARDOUS WASTE LEAK OUT OF THE AMERICAN CYANAMID SITE AND SNEAK INTO THE RARITAN RIVER?</p>
<p>OR COULD IT SEEP INTO THE BRUNSWICK AQUIFER... NEW JERSEY'S SECOND LARGEST SOURCE OF DRINKING WATER?</p>
<p>THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ACCOUNTABILITY OFFICE... OR THE GAO... MADE SEVERAL RECOMMENDATIONS IN 2019 TO MAKE SURE THIS DOESN'T HAPPEN.</p>
<p><strong>Alfredo Gomez -- GAO Director, Natural Resources and Environment team</strong></p>
<p>So, what we learned was that people wanted more direction. They wanted sort of forward-looking climate information, so they can make better decisions about risk responses, about risk assessments.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ALFREDO GOMEZ IS A DIRECTOR WITH THE GAO'S NATURAL RESOURCES AND ENVIRONMENT TEAM.</p>
<p>HIS TEAM FOUND THAT MORE THAN 60% OF THE COUNTRY'S SUPERFUND SITES ARE IN PLACES VULNERABLE TO CLIMATE CHANGE.</p>
<p><strong>Alfredo Gomez -- GAO Director, Natural Resources and Environment team</strong></p>
<p>Now, interestingly, in New Jersey, that percentage was a lot higher, it was 88% of the Superfund sites are located in places that may be affected by one or more of these climate change effects.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE REPORT DIDN'T LOOK INTO HOW CLIMATE CHANGE MAY IMPACT CLEANUP EFFORTS.</p>
<p>AS LONG AS THE POLLUTION REMAINS, HURRICANES AND FLOODING ARE A MAJOR THREAT TO SITES LIKE AMERICAN CYANAMID... AND TO OUR HEALTH.</p>
<p>IF THIS SITE ISN'T SECURED BEFORE ANOTHER HURRICANE OR FLOOD... IT COULD SPREAD CHEMICALS THROUGH THE RIVER AND WIND. IF CHEMICALS GET IN THE GROUNDWATER... IT CAN BE DIFFICULT TO TRACK.</p>
<p><strong>Mark Schmidt -- EPA Remedial Project Manager</strong></p>
<p>So, based on what has happened, we're concerned with the flooding events. We've been fortunate that nothing has happened. But, you know, what's the future gonna look like?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ALRIGHT... I JUST SPENT THE PAST FEW MINUTES THROWING AROUND A LOT OF TERMS I RECENTLY LEARNED HOW TO PRONOUNCE CORRECTLY... AND SERVED UP A HEARTY HELPING OF ACRONYM SOUP.</p>
<p>SO... I'M GOING TO TAKE A STEP BACK AND BREAK DOWN THE BASICS.</p>
<p>SUPERFUND... EMPHASIS ON FUND... NOT FUN... WAS A PROGRAM CREATED BY THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IN 1980 TO HELP PAY FOR THE CLEANUP OF HAZARDOUS WASTE SITES.</p>
<p>AT THE TIME... THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY... OR EPA... THOUGHT THERE WERE RELATIVELY FEW TOXIC SITES IN THE COUNTRY.</p>
<p>BUT OFFICIALS SOON DISCOVERED THOUSANDS OF CONTAMINATED SITES. SO, THEY CREATED A NATIONAL PRIORITIES LIST TO FIGURE OUT WHICH PLACES NEEDED TO BE CLEANED UP FIRST.</p>
<p>IT DIDN'T TAKE LONG FOR THE AMERICAN CYANAMID SITE TO BE INCLUDED ON THIS LIST.</p>
<p>SOME OF THE CHEMICALS THE COMPANY MADE ARE NOW KNOWN CARCINOGENS. THIS LINK WAS MADE BACK IN 1978... WHEN MORE THAN 1,000 WORKERS AT THE BRIDGEWATER PLANT WENT ON STRIKE.</p>
<p><strong>Rebecca Sobel -- New Jersey Nightly News, 1978</strong></p>
<p>More than 300 -- 1,300 workers at American Cyanamid's Bridgewater plant walked out on strike today, protesting low wages and poor safety conditions. Local 111 of the International Chemical Workers Union claims the company has ignored complaints of high rates of bladder cancer and lung disease among workers. Cyanamid wouldn't comment on that charge, but a spokesman says the company can't grant the 75-cent-an-hour pay hike because, said the Union, it exceeds President Carter's wage and price guidelines.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>IN SEPTEMBER 1983... AMERICAN CYANAMID WAS ONE OF THE FIRST PLACES TO BE DESIGNATED A SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p>THAT'S NO REAL SURPRISE.</p>
<p>FOR NEARLY A CENTURY... NUMEROUS COMPANIES USED THIS 575-ACRE SITE FOR CHEMICAL AND PHARMACEUTICAL MANUFACTURING.</p>
<p>THE TOXIC WASTE FROM THIS PRODUCTION WAS STORED IN HUMAN-MADE PONDS CALLED IMPOUNDMENTS. EVENTUALLY... THE PONDS LEECHED CHEMICALS IN THE SOIL AND GROUNDWATER.</p>
<p>THERE ARE 27 OF THESE PONDS AT AMERICAN CYANAMID... AND THE EPA SAYS 16 OF THESE BAD BOYS HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO THE POLLUTION ON THE PROPERTY.</p>
<p>BUT THE GRANDDADDY OF THEM ALL ARE IMPOUNDMENTS 1 AND 2. THE EPA GAVE THE PONDS NUMBERS TO KEEP TRACK OF THEM ALL.</p>
<p>THESE TWO PONDS ARE CONSIDERED BY THE EPA TO HAVE THE HIGHEST CONCENTRATIONS OF HAZARDOUS MATERIALS.</p>
<p>THEY CONTAIN ACID TAR SLUDGE. THAT'S A BYPRODUCT OF THE SITE'S DAYS AS AN OIL REFINERY.</p>
<p>JUST GOES TO SHOW... SOMETIMES THE PAST STICKS WITH YOU.</p>
<p>AMERICAN CYANAMID IS ONE OF THE MORE COMPLEX SUPERFUND SITES IN TERMS OF CLEANUP.</p>
<p>AND MARK SAYS THE PONDS ARE PART OF THE PROBLEM.</p>
<p><strong>Mark Schmidt -- EPA Remedial Project Manager</strong></p>
<p>Each of these impoundments had different waste. Back in the, you know, early days, the '40s and the '50s, there wasn't a lot of thought about what would happen if you put waste into these impoundments.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>EVEN WHILE CHEMICAL WASTE WAS BEING DUMPED NEXT TO THE RARITAN RIVER... SOMEONE UNDERSTOOD THAT THE SITE WAS ON A FLOODPLAIN AND TOOK ACTION.</p>
<p>IN THE 1930S... PONDS WERE CREATED ON THE SITE TO TRAP CHEMICAL WASTEWATER AND PREVENT THE TOXIC SOUP FROM POURING INTO THE RIVER.</p>
<p>DECADES LATER IN 2011... HEAVY RAINS FROM HURRICANE IRENE FLOODED PART OF THE SITE.</p>
<p>IMPOUNDMENTS 1 AND 2 WERE HIT HARD. THE TEMPORARY CAPS THAT HAD BEEN INSTALLED ON THESE SPOTS WERE DAMAGED.</p>
<p>CAPPING IS ONE WAY OF CLEANING UP A SUPERFUND SITE. THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO KEEP CHEMICALS IN PLACE TO PREVENT THEM FROM SPREADING. BUT IN THIS CASE... IT DIDN'T WORK.</p>
<p>THE CAPS COULDN'T WITHSTAND THE FLOODING AND SOME OF THAT ACID TAR SLUDGE WAS EXPOSED.</p>
<p>TO PREVENT THIS FROM HAPPENING IN THE FUTURE... THE EPA NOW REQUIRES THAT ALL FUTURE CAPS BE DESIGNED TO WITHSTAND THE EFFECTS OF MORE FREQUENT FLOODING</p>
<p>THEN LAST  SUMMER... HURRICANE IDA HAMMERED DOWN ON THE SITE... AND FLOOD LEVELS SET A NEW RECORD.</p>
<p>LUCKILY... EPA TESTS AFTER BOTH FLOODS SHOWED NO SIGNIFICANT RELEASE OF TOXINS IN THE RARITAN RIVER.</p>
<p>FOR NOW.</p>
<p>AT ITS PEAK... THE AMERICAN CYANAMID COMPLEX SPREAD OVER 600 ACRES ACROSS BRIDGEWATER AND BOUND BROOK.</p>
<p>THE COMPANY WAS ONCE ONE OF SOMERSET COUNTY'S LARGEST EMPLOYERS. THEY HIRED MORE THAN 5,000 PEOPLE WHO PRODUCED DYES... PIGMENTS... AND OTHER CHEMICALS BY THE TRAINLOAD.</p>
<p>PEGGY FUSSELL'S GRANDMOTHER WORKED FOR AMERICAN CYANAMID AS A TELEPHONE SWITCHBOARD OPERATOR.</p>
<p>FOR HOURS A DAY... HER GRANDMOTHER... ANNE FUSSELL... WOULD WATCH FOR CALLS THAT APPEARED AS LIGHTS ON A BOARD.</p>
<p>AT THE END OF HER SHIFT... SHE WOULD WALK THE FEW MINUTES TO HER HOME.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>She was what was called a hard luck story because she was a single mom, three kids. And so the corporation, the company, subsidized her housing. So we lived on a street that was for people who had fallen on hard times.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ONE OF HER CHILDREN WAS PEGGY'S DAD... WHO ENDED UP WORKING ODD JOBS AT AMERICAN CYANAMID... AND LIVING RIGHT NEXT TO HIS MOM.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>The reason I grew up there was because my dad grew up there. And then when my mother was pregnant with me, he was visiting his mother and found out that someone was moving out. And he said, &quot;I am looking for housing now. Can I live in this house until I find something better, until the baby's born?&quot; That baby was me.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>ON THE SURFACE... THE TWO-BEDROOM... ONE BATH BUNGALOW ON MIDLAND AVENUE SEEMED LIKE AN IDYLLIC PLACE TO GROW UP.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>One of the perks of living there was that we had a backyard and then behind the yard were fields and woods, and lots of places to play. I felt like I grew up in the country, even though I was in pretty much suburban New Jersey.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore'</strong></p>
<p>PHOTOS OF PEGGY AS A CHILD SHOW HER STANDING IN HER BACKYARD.</p>
<p>IN ANOTHER ONE... SHE'S WEARING SUNGLASSES AND TAKING HER DOLLS FOR A STROLL DOWN THE BLOCK.</p>
<p>THE SEASONS CHANGE... SHE'S TALLER... WITH LONGER HAIR... BUT THE ONE CONSTANT IN THIS SCRAPBOOK IS THE AMERICAN CYANAMID FACTORY... LOOMING LARGE OVER PEGGY'S CHILDHOOD.</p>
<p>IN THE WINTER... PEGGY SAYS SHE WOULD ICE SKATE ON THIS BEAUTIFUL FLAT POND NEAR HER HOUSE.</p>
<p>OTHER PONDS HAD LEAVES AND OTHER VEGETATION IN ITS WATERS... BUT NOT THIS ONE.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>The ponds were just murky. You know, they didn't look like they would make you sick or anything, they just looked like murky ponds.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THOSE PONDS STORED HAZARDOUS WASTE FOR AMERICAN CYANAMID.</p>
<p>PEGGY SAYS HER SKATING DAYS ENDED EARLY WHEN HER PARENTS REALIZED WHAT WAS GOING ON.</p>
<p>EVEN SO... IT WAS HARD TO ESCAPE THE COMPANY'S TRAPS FROM THE PAST.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>There was an orchard. When I was very young there were cows and a dairy at the end of the street. And when you think about what it means to drink milk from cows that are eating grass that's on the grounds of a chemical factories. And we had a well. We had well-water.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>NOW, AT 60 YEARS OLD ... PEGGY WONDERS IF THE WELL-WATER SHE DRANK AS A KID MAY HAVE BEEN CONTAMINATED BY AMERICAN CYANAMID.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>I don't think those conversations were had. I know that they weren't had in my house.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>WHAT THE FAMILY DID TALK ABOUT WAS HER AUNT'S WORK AT AMERICAN CYANAMID. MARY-LOUISE VEGA WAS A RESEARCH SCIENTIST AT THE PLANT.</p>
<p>HER CLAIM TO FAME WAS INVENTING A TYPE OF GLOW STICK USED BY THE MILITARY CALLED CYALUME.</p>
<p><strong>Peggy Fussell</strong></p>
<p>The joke was, you know, at some point we're all gonna glow.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>AMERICAN CYANAMID OFFICIALLY TURNED OFF THE LIGHTS IN 1999 WHEN THEY STOPPED MANUFACTURING IN BRIDGEWATER.</p>
<p>THEN... POOF.</p>
<p>BUILDINGS WERE DEMOLISHED THE FOLLOWING YEAR... AND TODAY IT'S HARD TO IMAGINE A SPRAWLING FACTORY ON THE SITE.</p>
<p>WHERE PEGGY'S GRANDMOTHER AND AUNT WORKED... CYANAMID'S OFFICES AND LABS... IS NOW A SHOPPING CENTER AND A STADIUM FOR THE MINOR LEAGUE SOMERSET PATRIOTS.</p>
<p>PEGGY'S CHILDHOOD HOME IS NOW A STARBUCKS.</p>
<p>JENNY KETROW... A FORMER BRIDGEWATER RESIDENT... SAYS HER DAD AND GRANDFATHER USED TO WORK ON THE AMERICAN CYANAMID SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Jenny Ketrow</strong></p>
<p>Sometimes my mom still talks about it, my dad would come home with, like, pink dye or red dye soaked into his undergarments, and she would do the laundry separate from our laundry. And, you know, especially, like, a couple of jobs, he had jackhammering out dye in a vat that was, you know, like, sending humans in there to do that?</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>THE FAMILY HAD A COMPLICATED RELATIONSHIP WITH AMERICAN CYANAMID. ON ONE HAND... IT WAS A SOURCE OF PRIDE TO HAVE RELATIVES WORK THERE. ON THE OTHER HAND... BY THE TIME JENNY WAS BORN IN 1984... IT WAS ALREADY LISTED AS A SUPERFUND SITE.</p>
<p><strong>Jenny Ketrow</strong></p>
<p>You also feared it because &quot;Wow, I could die at this job. You know, I'm basically risking my life for my family and for my livelihood. But, you know, I can put a roof over my head and feed everybody and have a sense of pride, like, I can afford the nicer things.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SHE SAYS ONE OF HER DAD'S JOBS WAS TO ROW A BOAT OUT ONTO THE PONDS. THERE... HE WOULD STIR THE WATER TO KEEP THE CHEMICALS FROM POOLING TOGETHER.</p>
<p><strong>Jenny Ketrow</strong></p>
<p>I remember him saying, like, he would have to go sometimes with a scientist or, like, a lab technician and go take samples. So, they had a metal rowboat. I don't think they really had anything other than maybe, like, a jumpsuit to wear, but not like a safety jumpsuit, more like a denim jumpsuit, the typical work wear that the guys wore.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>JENNY REMEMBERS BEING TOLD THE STORY ABOUT AN EMPLOYEE WHO ALMOST FELL INTO THE POND BECAUSE THE BOTTOM OF THEIR BOAT HAD ROTTED OUT.</p>
<p>SHE BELIEVES THIS HAPPENED BECAUSE THE POND WATER WAS SO TOXIC IT DISSOLVED THE BOAT'S METAL.</p>
<p><strong>Jenny Ketrow</strong></p>
<p>And at one point I guess something reacted with the chemicals and one of the boats started to have rot to it. One of the safety procedures was, like, check the bottom of the boat, make sure it's sound, make sure it's safe before we put it in. And then my father put it in, and then the new guy was just about to jump in. But the boat kind of sank and deteriorated. And my father grabbed the new guy and just threw him back onto the platform. I'm pretty sure that was my father's last day on that detail because I think he told his supervisor, like, &quot;Look, you know, I have a family. I'm not doing this. Like, this is not, no.&quot;</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>HER HOPE IS THAT THESE PONDS WILL BE CLEANED UP SOON.</p>
<p><strong>Jenny Ketrow</strong></p>
<p>Just turn it back into nature. And maybe that'll help with some of the flooding that's coming through because that area it still floods. Pretty much anytime we have a nor'easter hurricane, remnants of tropical storms, it floods. So let nature have it back.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' Host</strong></p>
<p>ALL OF THIS LAND... KNOWN AS THE HILL PROPERTY... WAS REMOVED FROM THE SUPERFUND LIST IN 1998.</p>
<p>THE REMAINING 435 ACRES OF THE SITE WERE BOUGHT BY PFIZER IN 2009.</p>
<p>THAT COMPANY'S NOW RESPONSIBLE FOR CLEANING IT UP.</p>
<p><strong>Mark Schmidt -- EPA Remedial Project Manager</strong></p>
<p>You know, we learned a lot through Irene. Ida, we learned even more, so there's still quite a bit of resiliency work that's going to go into the next phase of work.</p>
<p><strong>Jordan Gass-Poore' -- Host</strong></p>
<p>SECURING THE AMERICAN CYANAMID SITE MEANS A FEWS THINGS.</p>
<p>AFTER HURRICANE IDA DEVASTATED THE NORTHEAST IN 2021...</p>
<p>SOME FACILITIES WERE RELOCATED TO AREAS NOT WITHIN A FLOODPLAIN... OTHER PARTS WERE MOVED TO HIGHER GROUND... AND AN ON-SITE WEATHER STATION WAS PUT ON THE PROPERTY.</p>
<p>THE TOXIC ACID TAR IN IMPOUNDMENTS 1 AND 2 HAVE BEEN REMOVED AND ARE BEING TREATED OFFSITE BECAUSE THEY'RE AT RISK OF BEING FLOODED.</p>
<p>CLEANUP AT AMERICAN CYANAMID HAS DRAGGED ON FOR DECADES.</p>
<p>SINCE BEING DESIGNATED A SUPERFUND SITE NEARLY 40 YEARS AGO... ONLY ABOUT 80 ACRES HAVE BEEN CLEANED UP.</p>
<p>IT'S EXPECTED TO TAKE FIVE-TO-TEN MORE YEARS FOR CLEANUP TO BE COMPLETE.</p>
<p>HAZARD IS A SPACE NOT JUST FOR LEARNING ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES... BUT FOR ENGAGING OUR COMMUNITIES IN CONVERSATION AROUND THE CLEANUP OF THESE TOXIC PLACES.</p>
<p>DO YOU HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT SUPERFUND SITES IN NEW JERSEY? DO YOU LIVE NEAR ONE? IF SO... I WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU. SEND ME A TWEET USING #HAZARDNJ.</p>
<p>OR LEAVE ME A VOICE MEMO AT... <a href="mailto:HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG" target="_blank">HAZARD@MYNJPBS.ORG</a>.</p>
<p>WE MAY PLAY YOUR COMMENTS IN A FUTURE EPISODE.</p>
<p>HAZARD NJ IS AN NJ SPOTLIGHT NEWS PRODUCTION.</p>
<h3 id="credits" tabindex="-1">Credits</h3>
<p>Hazard NJ is written, edited and hosted by Jordan Gass-Poore’</p>
<p>Executive Producer – Jamie Kraft</p>
<p>Executive in Charge of Production – Joe Lee</p>
<p>Associate Producer – Michael Sol Warren</p>
<p>Production Assistant – Chris Pandza</p>
<p>Production Manager – Chloe Motisi</p>
<p>Additional research by Betsy Laikin</p>
<p>Sound Designer &amp; Engineer – Mark Bush</p>
<p>Audio Recording Engineer – Frank Brown</p>
<p>Music composed by Nick Pennington</p>
<p>Artwork by Matthew Fleming</p>
<p>Animated trailer created by Everest Strayer</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="47570048" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/m8jfsh/Hazard-Episode-One_American-Cyanamid_MB_05172022.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:19:49</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hazard Podcast - New Jersey: Trailer</title>
		<link>https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/trailer/?source=rss</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 02:59:43 GMT</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>Jordan Gass-Poore</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="true">https://hazardpodcast.com/episode/trailer/</guid>
        <itunes:image href="https://hazardpodcast.com/img/HazardAlbumCover.jpg" />
		<description>New podcast series highlights the intersection of pollution and climate change in the Garden State. Coming May 18.</description>
        <itunes:subtitle><![CDATA[New podcast series highlights the intersection of pollution and climate change in the Garden State. Coming May 18.]]></itunes:subtitle>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<iframe title="Trailer" style="border: none;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&pbad=0&i=mupbp-121bf17-pb&square=1&share=1&download=1&fonts=Arial&skin=f6f6f6&font-color=auto&rtl=0&logo_link=episode_page&btn-skin=7&size=300" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe>
<h2 id="the-hazard-podcast-coming-soon!" tabindex="-1">The Hazard Podcast, coming soon!</h2>
<p>They’re the most polluted places in the country, and no state has more than New Jersey.</p>
<p>There are 114 toxic Superfund sites scattered across the Garden State, and that number is growing. As cleanup efforts drag on for those sites, in some cases for nearly 40 years, climate change is reshaping the ways in which their pollution may threaten people living nearby.</p>
<p>Hazard NJ is a new podcast that digs through the muck of each contaminated site to give a clearer picture of what the threat is and what it will take to clean it up before it’s too late. Hosted by journalist Jordan Gass-Poore’ and produced by NJ Spotlight News, Hazard NJ is a limited series with the first episode coming on May 18.</p>
<p>Don’t miss a thing: Subscribe to Hazard NJ on <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/hazard-nj/id1622849571" target="_blank">Apple Podcasts</a>, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/30cCzv4iuGTIdr44eyHIfS?si=3w9tD2Z-QNa5coc8l4RIYw" target="_blank">Spotify</a>, <a href="https://music.amazon.com/podcasts/f36c7ea7-0e39-48be-b9aa-a2914be8a837/hazard-nj" target="_blank">Amazon Music</a> and more.</p>
<p>This episode is sponsored by:</p>
<p>Peril and Promise is a public media initiative from The WNET Group, reporting on the human stories of climate change and its solutions. You can learn more at <a href="http://pbs.org/perilandpromise" target="_blank">pbs.org/perilandpromise</a>. Major funding for Peril and Promise is provided by Dr. P. Roy Vagelos and Diana T. Vagelos with additional funding from The Marc Haas Foundation, Sue and Edgar Wachenheim III, and the Cheryl and Philip Milstein Family.</p>
<p>Read the episode script below or <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/e/2PACX-1vTfCt0SSMrhpZoZc65G52IrdEJotP1I39EdU4YCeDNQPMOOFcxR5DIYr4pE02OGSDHsS3vbdxPF3tLP/pub" target="_blank">open in a new window</a>:</p>
<iframe class="iframe-doc" src="https://docs.google.com/document/d/e/2PACX-1vTfCt0SSMrhpZoZc65G52IrdEJotP1I39EdU4YCeDNQPMOOFcxR5DIYr4pE02OGSDHsS3vbdxPF3tLP/pub?embedded=true"></iframe>
]]></content:encoded>
        <enclosure length="9103808" type="audio/mpeg" url="https://mcdn.podbean.com/mf/download/8mnfvr/Hazard_Trailera9yp5.mp3" />
        <itunes:episodeType>full</itunes:episodeType>
        <itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit>
        <itunes:duration>00:03:47</itunes:duration>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
